<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Opinion on Ian Ames - I help multidisciplinary teams deliver services in a user centred way.</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/opinion/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Opinion on Ian Ames - I help multidisciplinary teams deliver services in a user centred way.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/opinion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Delivery Tactics - Slicing thin or deep?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/slicing-thin-or-deep/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/slicing-thin-or-deep/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/shedlife_mug.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A mug of tea in my #shedlife mug&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A key part of agile delivery is working out what small changes can deliver the most value. It can be hard to get agreement on what is small enough to be valuable, getting this balance right is extremely difficult and context specific, hence why MVP’s (minimum viable products) are much maligned.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are two main approaches that can be used, you can either ‘slice thin’ deliver a small part of every step of the user journey; or ‘slice deep’ focus your effort on improving one part of the end to end service journey. Deciding which way to go depends on context, below are some things I try and consider with teams and stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 things I learned about Delivery Management from learning to navigate very large Ships.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/10-things-i-learned-from-marine-navigaton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/10-things-i-learned-from-marine-navigaton/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;25 years ago a young and naive me went to university to study Marine Navigation, My hope was that I could use the skills I learnt to travel the world and get paid whilst doing it. To my horrow I learnt fairly quickly that the reality is that most ships are in port for less than 24 hours and most time is spent at sea.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After university I found myself in the crazy world of IT and since digital delivery and product management. Nevertheless I learn’t a number of things that have served me well in my career in the subsequent years. Here’s what they were:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Product Prioritisation is triage</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/product-prioritisation-is-triage/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/product-prioritisation-is-triage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triage&#34;&gt;Triage&lt;/a&gt; is used in medicine when acute care cannot be provided for lack of resources. The process rations care towards those who are most in need of immediate care, and who&#xA;benefit most from it. More generally it refers to prioritisation of medical care as a whole. I have some personal experience of using triage from my time as a mountain rescue volunteer.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We would often train for scenarios where the number of casualties was more than our capacity to treat them all. Most of the volunteers weren&amp;rsquo;t medical professionals (myself included) so our processes were simple. Our priority was to stabilise casualties and transport them to medical care as quickly and safely as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What does great collaboration in local government look like?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/what-does-great-collaboration-in-local-government-look-like/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/what-does-great-collaboration-in-local-government-look-like/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a soft spot for local government, it&amp;rsquo;s where most people&amp;rsquo;s interactions with government happen, and yet it is also one of the most underfunded parts. Arguably constraint is the mother of invention and local government doesn&amp;rsquo;t get enough credit for the work they do to to deliver services for citizens effectively and cheaply. So I asked twitter to share with me some examples of great collaboration in local gov, here&amp;rsquo;s some great examples that were shared:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Would a Great Onboarding Experience Look Like?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/what-would-a-great-onboarding-experience-look-like/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/what-would-a-great-onboarding-experience-look-like/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I joined Surevine my onboarding experience was fantastic, but I wanted to see if there was anything more we could do to make it even better, so back in June I asked twitter what would a great onboarding experience look like?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As always the responses were great. This post summarises what I learned:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;onboarding-starts-way-before-a-person-joins-a-company&#34;&gt;Onboarding starts way before a person joins a company&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If someone wants to work with you, they will be thinking about it way before onboarding starts. When people are looking for a new job, they want to know what a company is like to work for, almost as much as the salary and perks. No one wants to work somewhere that&amp;rsquo;s not going to motivate them or make them miserable. Sharing how you work as a company gives candidates an insight into the sort of organisation you are, and whether they might want to work there. Blogs and videos about how you work and publishing your company handbook on the web are great ways to provide that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on Map Camp</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/reflections-on-map-camp-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/reflections-on-map-camp-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year I was finally able to attend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.map-camp.com/_pages/2019-10-15_London/&#34;&gt;MapCamp 2019&lt;/a&gt; with ~600 other people at Sadlers Wells Theatre, London. MapCamp is a conference introducing and describing the technique of &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/wardleymaps/on-being-lost-2ef5f05eb1ec&#34;&gt;Wardley Mapping&lt;/a&gt;, a tool for mapping strategy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I first came across Wardley Maps a couple of years ago through the medium book. I found it compelling, Simon Wardley has a lovely humble style of writing. He described how he went from ‘bumbling CEO’ to ‘having a vague idea of what I was doing’. That self-deprecating style just drew me in, and I found a lot I could relate to in my work. However, I could never get the hang of mapping and I hoped going to MapCamp would help me have that aha! moment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Essential Steps for an Effective Project Kick Off</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/essential-steps-for-an-effective-project-kick-off/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/essential-steps-for-an-effective-project-kick-off/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kick-off’s are a great way of bringing a new team together at the start of a new project or phase of a project. The aim is to allow the team to get to know one another and to allow all the team members to understand the goals and objectives.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I recently helped facilitate a kick-off for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/agile-delivery/how-the-alpha-phase-works&#34;&gt;alpha phase&lt;/a&gt; of the ‘Protect’ service (working title). Although Protect had been through a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/agile-delivery/how-the-discovery-phase-works&#34;&gt;discovery phase&lt;/a&gt;, circumstances meant that the Alpha team was quite different to the Discovery team. This meant that we needed to spend more time than perhaps usual bringing everyone up to speed. Our kick-off lasted 3.5 days. the structure was:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mountaineering and a Rant About Risk Management</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/mountaineering-and-a-rant-about-risk-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/mountaineering-and-a-rant-about-risk-management/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I love hill climbing and mountaineering, ever since I was dragged up Pen-Y-Fan and got mild hypothermia in the scouts at about the age of 13. One of the best things yomping up hills has taught me is the nature of risk. So I was a bit surprised when I saw this tweet from Vasco Duarte:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Friends, let&amp;#39;s collect a list of domains where Risk ELIMINATION is priority #1: Climbing; Air travel industry; what else? &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/modernAgile?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#modernAgile&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/agile?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#agile&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/NoEstimates?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#NoEstimates&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/lean?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#lean&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/kanban?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#kanban&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>User Research Is the Most Frustrating Thing Ever</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/user-research-is-the-most-frustrating-thing-ever/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/user-research-is-the-most-frustrating-thing-ever/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m the scrum master for a small team developing a new service for a government agency. The team has been working in an agile way for 20 months. I have been with them for 15 of those months.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Our team is made up of user researchers, a designer, a BA, developers and testers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dealing with users isn’t new to me, before joining my current team I worked in IT operations and service management, dealing with angry and frustrated users was a day to day part of the role.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
