<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>heritage on Ames World</title>
    <link>https://ames.world/tags/heritage/</link>
    <description>Recent content in heritage on Ames World</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>MIT</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://ames.world/tags/heritage/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Plymouth, Route 2 - Millbay Mini</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/hidden-plymouth-route2-millbay-mini/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/hidden-plymouth-route2-millbay-mini/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m slightly overwhelmed by how well &lt;a href=&#34;https://ames.world/posts/hidden-plymouth-route2-millbay-mini/&#34;&gt;Route 1&lt;/a&gt; has been received I have had some lovely feedback and suggestions for future routes. One such suggestion is to do something shorter that children can take part in, so where better than around Millbay. I can test it with my own kids as they go to Plymouth School of Creative Arts which is the starting point for this route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/d/embed?mid=16cgN0xxCOX9BJIeOksILtykuBDKNyCk_&amp;hl=en&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;480&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are loads of quirky little features in and around Millbay, its relatively flat and the route is only 2km. If the walk doesn’t wear the little ones out, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.plymouth.gov.uk/parksnatureandgreenspaces/findpark/westhoepark&#34;&gt;West Hoe park&lt;/a&gt; is within walking distance too. The route starts outside the school and if you are driving there are three car parks nearby, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.co.uk/maps/@50.3689901,-4.1520366,3a,75y,115.98h,93.85t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1stpjtGYcS0qblHYZvv3xgww!2e0!7i16384!8i8192&#34;&gt;Martin Street&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.plymouth.gov.uk/parkingandtravel/findsomewherepark/pavilionscarpark&#34;&gt;Pavilions&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.myringgo.co.uk/parkinglocator/2320&#34;&gt;Brunel Way&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately they are all Pay and Display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-docks.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Millbay Docks&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;points-of-interest&#34;&gt;Points of Interest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;octagon-brewery&#34;&gt;Octagon Brewery&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the school head the short distance up Martin Street to the junction with Sawrey Street, here you will find the old Octagon Brewery, now Docwra Bros. car body shop.
The brewery was founded in 1861 and incorporated in 1899. It continued until 1954 when it was sold to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simonds_Brewery&#34;&gt;H&amp;amp;G Simonds&lt;/a&gt;. The following year the company was liquidated. On the side of the building is a small plaque:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Octagon Brewery&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the late 19th century there were three major breweries supplying ales and beers for public houses throughout the ‘Three Towns’ of Plymouth, Stonehouse and Devonport.
The Octagon Brewery was one of the many smaller ones started about 1899. It later owned many taverns throughout the ‘Three Towns.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These pubs displayed the distinctive brewery logo of an OB within an octagon shape. Some of the bottled favourites included ‘OB’ stout, Pale Ale, and Indian Pale Ale No 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/octogon-brewery.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Octogon brewery plaque, as described above&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinctive logo can still be seen today in the windows of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tripadvisor.co.uk/Attraction_Review-g186258-d3312659-Reviews-Dolphin_Hotel-Plymouth_Devon_England.html&#34;&gt;Dolphin Hotel&lt;/a&gt; on the Barbican, one of Plymouth’s most popular pubs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/dolphin-hotel.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The Octagon Brewery company logo built into the windows of the Dolphin Hotel on the Barbican.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-phoenix&#34;&gt;The Phoenix&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a short distance up Sawrey street is the Phoenix Tavern, alas no longer a tavern. The closed pubs project has some &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.closedpubs.co.uk/devon/plymouth_phoenix.html&#34;&gt;interesting pictures of the pub in the 1930’s&lt;/a&gt;. On the side of the building is another interesting plaque.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phoenix Hall Roller Skating Rink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roller skating took England by storm and by the late 19th century Plymouth had half a dozen rinks. In May 1880 the Phoenix Hall Rink was one of the last to open. Another rink, Pavilion New Skating Rink was located nearby in Martin Street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various skating prizes could be won. These were usually silver cups or medals but, on special occasions, prizes could even include live chickens or a pig to take home!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/the-phoenix.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The plaque on the side of the Phoenix Tavern as decribed above&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;millbay-stars&#34;&gt;Millbay stars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the Phoenix Tavern walk back south down Phoenix St and cross Millbay Road. Head back towards the mini roundabout at the entrance to Millbay docks on the wall you will see a number of Hollywood style stars. These show all the famous people who have berthed in Millbay, the vessel they arrived on, and the year. The stars include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walt Disney, Normandie, 1935.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charles Laughton, Champlain, 1935.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gloria Swanson, Queen Mary, 1938.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jack L Warner, Queen Mary, 1938.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maurice Chevalier, Manhattan, 1938.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sabu, Paris, 1938&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laurence Olivier, Ile de France, 1939.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vivien Leigh, Ile de France, 1939.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gene Autrey, Manhattan, 1939.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boris Karloff, Italia, 1950.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Judy Garland, Ile de France, 1951.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charlie Chaplin, Mauritania, 1951.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alan Ladd, Ile de France, 1952.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bing Crosby, Liberte, 1952.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sarah Vaughan, Liberte, 1953.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lena Horne, Liberte, 1956.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Duke Ellington, Ile de France, 1958.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-stars.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;One of the Millbay stars, this one is forWalt Disney who traveled on the Normandie&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;gold-bullion&#34;&gt;Gold bullion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing the ‘Gold’ bullion statue has been removed whilst a new retirement home is built on adjacent land, however it will be restored so is worth a mention for the future. The statue commemorates the practice of storing large quantities of bullion in the open on the dockside with a single policeman to guard it. This was common in the 1930’s with gold being sent to and from America, Australia and South Africa from the docks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/gold-bullion.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The gold ingots aren’t currently there but will be restored once the adjacent building work is completed.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between 1932 and 1934 over a million pounds of gold and silver ingots and sovereigns were landed at the docks following the groundbreaking salvage from the P&amp;amp;O liner &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pandosnco.co.uk/egypt.html&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Egypt&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;’ which sank off the coast of France in a decade earlier in 1922.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;endurance-blue-plaque&#34;&gt;Endurance Blue Plaque&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the gold bullion head east down Millbay road to Isambard Kingdom Brunel Way, turn right and head up it. At the time of writing there are hoardings up along the road with interesting Plymouth facts on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the road you reach Millbay docks where you will find a memorial stone and blue plaque commemorating Ernest Shackleton setting sail onboard the Endurance on the 8th August 1914.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roald_Amundsen&#34;&gt;Roald Amundsen’s&lt;/a&gt; success reaching the South Pole in 1911 (and the subsequent death of one of Plymouth’s most famous sons, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Falcon_Scott&#34;&gt;Robert Falcon Scott&lt;/a&gt;) Shackleton was aiming to complete the grandly titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial_Trans-Antarctic_Expedition&#34;&gt;‘Imperial Trans-Antarctic expedition’&lt;/a&gt;, crossing Antarctica from one side to the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/endurance-plaque.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The Shackleton Endurance blue plaque.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The expedition came into jeopardy when the Endurance became trapped in the sea ice, and was ultimately crushed and sank in the Weddell Sea. The 28 man crew found themselves stranded on the pack ice with no hope of rescue. They camped on the ice for &lt;strong&gt;6 months&lt;/strong&gt; drifting slowly northwards. Eventually the ice became too unstable and the crew were stranded on the small uninhabited Elephant Island after taking to the ships boats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shackleton and 5 of his crew then rowed &lt;strong&gt;800 miles&lt;/strong&gt; to South Georgia island in their 22.5 ft boat the ‘James Caird’. They were aiming to seek help from whaling outposts on the island and to come back and rescue the remaining 23 men. The journey was gruelling, through heavy seas and freezing conditions but after 14 days they successfully reached the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be a further 3 months before Shackleton would be able to rescue the men he left behind, due to the start of the southern winter. The government of Uruguay loaned him a ship to affect the rescue and amazingly all 28 men of the ‘Endurance’ survived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;west-hoe-road-signs&#34;&gt;West Hoe Road signs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the docks head up the 35 steps (count them with the kids) from Willoughby Way to West Hoe Road. You will find many old signs on the dock boundary wall. These are reclaimed signs from businesses and facilities in the docks. We only managed to find the Carruthers cranes and Royal Navy and Marines recruitment signs. Apparently there is also Singer sewing machines sign from the sailmakers, and ‘Armstrongs’ which used to be on the rail bridge at the docks mouth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/caruthers.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Carruthers cranes safety notices&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/navy-sign.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Join the Navy, good pay and prospects!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;millbay-docks&#34;&gt;Millbay docks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Millbay takes its name unsurprisingly from being the site of tidal mills as early as the 12th century. The docks however really took off in the 19th century. Millbay pier was built in 1844 and the following year the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SS_Great_Britain&#34;&gt;SS Great Britain&lt;/a&gt; berthed here during her maiden voyage to New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-pier.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;View from Millbay Pier today.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1846 the Great Western Dock company were granted an act of Parliament to provide full facilities for shipping in the docks. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isambard_Kingdom_Brunel&#34;&gt;Isambard Kingdom Brunel&lt;/a&gt; designed the new docks and the majority of the original dock walls survive today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Millbay quickly became a busy commercial dock and by the 1870’s started to become a busy terminus for trans-atlantic visitors. It was known as the ‘route that cuts the corner off’ as passengers could disembark at Plymouth and get a fast train to London, thus avoiding the longer sea journey to Southampton or Tilbury. In the early 20th century 6 million passenger landed or embarked for America from the docks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1912 the surviving crew of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.plymouthherald.co.uk/news/history/plymouths-haunting-steps-nowhere-story-3796478&#34;&gt;Titanic&lt;/a&gt; landed at Millbay docks in secrecy and were taken by train to Southampton. There is a memorial inside Millbay marina, however it is not accessible to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/titanic-crew.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The crew of the Titanic landing at Millbay docks after the ships demise.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today the docks are undergoing major regeneration new houses and flats have been built, the school, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kingpointmarina.co.uk/&#34;&gt;King point marina&lt;/a&gt; (including the lovely &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thedockplymouth.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Dock Restaurant&lt;/a&gt;) have also been developed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building continues with the second phase of homes and retirement apartments underway, plus proposals for a hotel and shops are out for public consultation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-apartments.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Millbay docks today.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;millbay-park&#34;&gt;Millbay Park&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you continue along West Hoe Road, there is a strangely shaped park on the Eastern side of West Hoe Road. The park is terraced with a football pitch at the peak, the flat space gives away its use as a barracks between 1845 and 1856. Before this however, the area was a gaol for prisoners of war. Initially it was constructed to house 1500 American prisoners of war during the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Revolutionary_War&#34;&gt;War of Independence (1777–1783)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-gaol.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Mill prison, previously called Mill gaol was designed and built to house prisoners of war.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Napoleonic wars the prison held 11,000 French and American prisoners of war. It was at this time in 1806 that the prisoners were marched the 15 miles to Princetown on Dartmoor to build Dartmoor Prison (to contain even more prisoners of war!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today little remains of this history other than a couple of plaques on the gates of the park. The first commemorates the first American sailors held prisoner and reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this site was Mill (Old Mill — Millbay) Gaol where over 1500 American sailors were held in captivity during the war for American independence 1777–1783.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-gaol-plaque.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Millbay Gaol Plaque as described above.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second commemorates the barracks being turned over for public recreational usage (in a suitably clipped and bossy tone):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subject to military regulations this recreation ground, formerly the site of Millbay barracks, was opened for public use on the day of the coronation of King George V and Queen Mary. 22nd June 1911.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-barracks-plaque.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Millbay barracks plaque as described above.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;eddystone-lighthouse-pavement&#34;&gt;Eddystone Lighthouse Pavement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just opposite the park in front of the Salumi restaurant is a paved circle which doesn’t look like much, until you notice the strange shape of the slabs. These are the groundbreaking interlocking patterns of the stone blocks developed by John Smeaton to build the Eddystone Lighthouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/eddystone-lighthouse-pavement.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The Eddystone lighthouse pavement with the Duke of Cornwall hotel in the background.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interlocking blocks were so successful that the lighthouse stood for 123 years, indeed the rock it was built on wore away before the blocks did forcing it to be replaced. Indeed the lighthouse still stands today proudly on Plymouth Hoe 259 years after it was first constructed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look closely there is a rather grisly plaque embedded in the pavement. It reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the 1st December 1755 fire destroyed John Rudyard’s Eddystone lighthouse. As flames reached the roof of the tower a worker, Henry Hall (aged 84) looked up and managed to swallow a blob of molten metal which lodged in his stomach. He died of lead poisoning twelve days later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/eddystone-memorial.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The grisly Eddystone plaque described above&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;duke-of-cornwall-hotel&#34;&gt;Duke of Cornwall Hotel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://thedukeofcornwall.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Duke of Cornwall&lt;/a&gt; dominates the skyline of Millbay and stands grandly in Victorian splendour. It was Plymouth’s first luxury hotel, the South Devon railway company recognised the need for luxury accommodation as first class travel increased to and from the docks due to the ‘route the cuts the corner off’ mentioned earlier. The hotel’s popularity matched the fortunes of the docks, peaking in the 1930&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/duke-of-cornwall-advert.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;An advert for the Duke of Cornwall from 1897. It looks much the same today.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the second world war, the hotel was embroiled in scandal as the family running the hotel were strongly tied to the fascist party. Due to Plymouth’s military importance the family were placed on MI5’s suspect list and in 1944 they were forced to leave the hotel before the Allied invasion of France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1970’s the hotel faced the threat of being pulled down primarily because of the lack of car parking, despite being listed in 1975. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Betjeman&#34;&gt;Sir John Betjeman&lt;/a&gt; helped lead the fight for it’s survival describing it as “one of the finest examples of Victorian gothic architecture he had ever seen.’ the hotel’s future was thankfully secured in 1988 after the terraced garden had been changed to a car park.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;millbay-station-the-pavillions&#34;&gt;Millbay Station (the Pavillions)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little remains today as a reminder that the Pavilions was once the location of Plymouth’s primary railway station. The only remaining features are two stone pillars outside the main entrance with no real explanation as to what they are or why they are there. They are in fact the posts that made up the forecourt entrance to the station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-station-pillars.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The entrance pillars to Millbay Station, cannon damage from World War II can still be seen on them.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The station was built in 1849 by the South Devon railway as the terminus of its line from Exeter. It was originally a 7ft broad gauge railway but was converted to 4ft 8½in standard gauge in 1892 after the Great Western railway had acquired the South Devon in 1876.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1941 the station was closed to passengers after being bombed. Traces of cannon damage can still be seen on the posts. In 1969 the station was closed to good trains, apart from through traffic to the docks. Then finally in 1971 the station was closed for good. Twenty years later the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.plymouthpavilions.com/Online/default.asp&#34;&gt;Pavilions leisure complex&lt;/a&gt; was opened on the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-station.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Millbay station with the Duke of Cornwall behind it, notice the enormous wide gauge rails.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the Pavilions it’s a short walk downhill back to the school. I hope you enjoy the route.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Plymouth, Route 1 - Stoke to Mutton Cove</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/hidden-plymouth-route1-stoke-to-mutton-cove/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/hidden-plymouth-route1-stoke-to-mutton-cove/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This route starts at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.co.uk/maps/place/Stoke+Car+Park/@50.3805872,-4.1651648,15z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x0:0x880e5bffe7b91f5d!8m2!3d50.3805872!4d-4.1651648&#34;&gt;Stoke Village Car Park&lt;/a&gt;, which is free to park. It then climbs to what was once the highest point in Plymouth, before descending to sea level and back again.
I have mapped the route on Strava so you can download it to a GPS, or print out the map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/stoke-mutton-cove-route.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Route map&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/stoke-mutton-cove-route-profile.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Elevation Profile&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also run the route so you can see a fly through below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;embedly-card&#34; data-card-controls=&#34;0&#34; data-card-key=&#34;f1631a41cb254ca5b035dc5747a5bd75&#34;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.relive.cc/view/vNOPKV2J2vR?r=embed-site&#34;&gt;Relive &#39;New phone&#39;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;script async src=&#34;https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/platform.js&#34; charset=&#34;UTF-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;points-of-interest&#34;&gt;Points of interest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;blockhouse-park&#34;&gt;Blockhouse Park&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the city expanded toward Roborough this was the highest point in Plymouth and the 360˚ view from the Redoubt is one of the best in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/blockhouse_park.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The view north from Blockhouse Park redoubt, on the left is the dockyard that the fort was built to protect.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Mount Pleasant &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Redoubt&#34;&gt;Redoubt&lt;/a&gt;’ was first built in 1780 to protect the dockyard. According to a plaque at the entrance to the park it was modified in 1811 and had become obsolete by 1860.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A larger information board in the redoubt shows what it would have looked like and provides more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/mount_pleasant_redoubt.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The information board in the redoubt.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;clarendon-house&#34;&gt;Clarendon House&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you leave Blockhouse park and come down Home Park, you are greeted with the imposing sight of Clarendon House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/clarendon_house.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Clarendon House&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the right hand side of the main entrance is a plaque which states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the years 1940 to 1947 this building was the training centre for the Polish Navy and Headquarters of the Polish Navy Southern Command following the outbreak of World War II. This Plaque was unveiled on 20th May 2001, by the Lord Mayor of Plymouth, Councillor David Viney and Mr Stanislaw Szwabski chairman of Gydnia city council, to commemorate the 25th Anniversary of the twinning of Plymouth and Gydnia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The building itself appears older than from the 1940’s. The excellent National Libraries of Scotland Historic maps website allows you to view old Ordnance Survey maps overlaid on modern maps. According to the 1854 to 1863 OS map, it appears that Clarendon house was previously an orphanage, the ‘Royal British Female Orphan Asylum.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/royal_british_female_orphan_asylum.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;A section of the 1854 to 1863 Ordnance Survey Map showing Clarendon House as the ‘Royal British Female Orphan Asylum.’ Image Courtesy of National Libraries of Scotland and Ordnance Survey.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This led me to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.childrenshomes.org.uk&#34;&gt;www.childrenshomes.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; who have a detailed and fascinating page about the history of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.childrenshomes.org.uk/DevonportRoyal/&#34;&gt;Royal British Female Orphan Asylum&lt;/a&gt;. Clarendon House’s foundation stone was laid on April 23rd 1845 and according to the website it sounded quite the event:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ceremony was witnessed by the Lord Lieutenant of Cornwall, the Mayors and Corporations of Plymouth and Devonport, the Magistrates of the County and Borough, the Commissioners of the town, the heads of Departments Naval and Military Officers, and many others who walked in procession to the site. It was said that the rich combination of masonic, civic naval and military uniforms, the military music, and the presence of well-dressed and beautiful females, attracted a crowd of 30,000 spectators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hms-doris-memorial&#34;&gt;H.M.S. Doris Memorial&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After passing Clarendon house the route takes you through the attractive cottages and town houses of Acre Place to Devonport Park, in my opinion the most beautiful park in Plymouth. Following the spherical central path offers sweeping views of the river Tamar and the dockyards below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/hms-doris-memorial.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;H.M.S. Doris Memorial with Higher Lodge in the background.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually you come to the H.M.S. Doris Memorial. For a long time I mistakenly assumed the gun was one of the field guns used in the Boer war and commemorated in the annual Naval gun carry. The gun is actually a captured machine gun.
The crew of H.M.S. Doris did have to drag a ships gun hundred of miles inland on an improvised carriage but it was much bigger than a field gun. The image below shows the 4.7 inch gun being fired at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Magersfontein&#34;&gt;Battle of Magersfontein&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/4.7-inch-field-gun.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Image courtesy of Imperial War Museum&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;raglan-gatehouse&#34;&gt;Raglan Gatehouse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just down from Devonport park on a rather long straight, and fairly bleak road is the Raglan Barracks gatehouse. The barracks are no more having been demolished in the 1970’s but the grade II listed gatehouse remains, albeit in a rather sorry state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/raglan_gate.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Raglan Barracks Gatehouse today.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The barracks were built between 1853 and 1858 during the Crimean Wars. The gate was designed by Captain Francis Fowke who also designed the Royal Albert Hall and parts of the Victoria and Albert Museum. The Devonport online website provides a comprehensive history of the barracks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it hard to imagine the sheer size of the barracks parade ground. It doesn’t feel possible that such a large space existed just behind this building now that it is surrounded by flats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/changing-of-colours.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Changing of the colours on the enormous Raglan barracks parade ground in 1895. The gatehouse is in the background.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;devonport-guildhall-column-and-egyptian-house&#34;&gt;Devonport Guildhall, Column and Egyptian House&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devonport Guildhall is a legacy to the fact that the ‘City of Plymouth’ is a relatively recent creation. The three towns of Plymouth, Devonport and Stonehouse were merged in 1914 to become the city of Plymouth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Correction. Wendy Andrews on Facebook has informed me that the three towns united in 1914 but didn’t become a city until 1928&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before then the guildhall had been the administrative centre of Devonport, the largest and most prosperous of the towns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/devonport.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;An engraving from circa 1825 showing Devonport Guildhall, the base of Devonport Column, the Egyptian styled library and the chapel.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Guildhall, Column and Egyptian House were designed by the architect &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Foulston&#34;&gt;John Foulston&lt;/a&gt; who features heavily in Plymouth historical architecture. Originally there was also a chapel but during the extensive bombing of World War II it was destroyed. Indeed most of the surrounding area was destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/bombed_devonport.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Children play in the rubble left from the extensive bombing of Devonport during World War II.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A combination of the move of administrative power from the area, and the destruction of World War II led to the Guildhall falling into disuse. The column was also closed to the public in the 1950’s. The Egyptian house (one of only two buildings of this style in the country) started as a school, then a library and, would eventually become a social club which it still is today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The surrounding area, Ker street, has been through two regenerations since the war. The first was a post-war high density set of flats which dwarfed the historic buildings. The poorly planned blocks led to social problems arising and the area of Devonport became a less desirable place to live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/ker_st_flats.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The post war flats built in Ker Street dwarf the Guildhall in 2005. Photo Courtesy Devonport Online.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2007 work was started in regenerating Ker Street aiming to reduce the density of the street and try to address the social issues of the area. Happily the Guildhall and Column was given a restoration grant and have been &lt;a href=&#34;https://devonportguildhall.org/history/&#34;&gt;painstakingly restored by the Real Ideas Organisation&lt;/a&gt;. The column is now a visitor attraction and the view is worth the climb up the 137 granite steps. The Guildhall is used for weddings, craft fairs and other events, it is also home to the excellent Column House bakery. The future is less certain for the Egyptian House having recently been sold by the owners of the social club after 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Correction. Mandie Leaves, the owner of the social club has informed me that it is still up and running and anyone is welcome to pop in. I for one will visit for a look inside.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/devonport_guildhall.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Devonport Guildhall, Column and Egyptian House today, a very similar view to 1825.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mutton-cove-and-mount-wise-pools&#34;&gt;Mutton Cove and Mount Wise Pools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short distance from the Guildhall is Mutton Cove, a charming harbour with views across the Tamar to Cornwall. I’m struggling to find any information about the history of the cove, so please comment if you have any leads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to the west is Slipway Number 1 and the ‘King Billy’ figurehead. Slipway No 1 is the oldest covered slip in any Royal Navy dockyard. Built in around 1763, the roof wasn’t added until 1814.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/number-one-slip.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The view from Mutton Cove, with Covered Slip No 1 and ‘King Billy’ figurehead on the right.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In front of the slip is the ‘King Billy’ figurehead, originally it was the figurehead on the 120 gun ship H.M.S. King William. When the ship was redesigned for steam power in 1859 the figurehead was replaced with a smaller one and the original was displayed in front of the slip. In the 1990’s the original figurehead was found to have significant rot and a fibreglass replica was made and now stands in its place. The original figurehead is now at home in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://devonportnhc.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Devonport Naval Heritage centre&lt;/a&gt;, and is being restored before being moved to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theboxplymouth.com/&#34;&gt;‘the Box’&lt;/a&gt;, Plymouth’s new museum, when it opens in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along from Mutton Cove is Richmond Walk and the Mount Wise swimming pools. Richmond Walk was built in the 1790’s and 1800’s to provide local people with access to the shore as the Naval command at Mount Wise continued to expand. The swimming pools were built in 1924 and refurbished in 2000. They continue to be used today and are extremely popular in the summer months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/mount-wise-pools.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;A typical queue for Mount Wise pools on a sunny summer day.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just along from Mount Wise Pools is Blagdon’s boatyard. In 1831 this was the the site of Victoria Cottages. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Darwin&#34;&gt;Charles Darwin&lt;/a&gt; lodged here before embarking on H.M.S. Beagle to the Galapagos Islands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stonehouse-creek-and-devonport-high-school-for-boys&#34;&gt;Stonehouse Creek and Devonport High School for Boys&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richmond Walk ends at the excellent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jollyjacks.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Jolly Jacks restaurant&lt;/a&gt;, from there it is a short distance to Stonehouse Bridge. The bridge was designed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Smeaton&#34;&gt;John Smeaton&lt;/a&gt;, (of Smeaton’s lighthouse fame) and opened in 1773 to join Devonport with the neighbouring town of Stonehouse. Stonehouse creek, which the bridge crosses, was filled in as far as Millbridge in 1972 to form the recreational grounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/stonehouse-creek.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The recreation grounds behind Stonehouse Bridge, a rare piece of flat land in Plymouth!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the north side of the old creek is Devonport High School for boys. This imposing building was originally the Stoke Military Hospital and was built in 1797 for the British Army by Napoleonic prisoners of war. The design was based on the Naval hospital to the south of the creek, now the Millfields private estate. The Naval hospital was state of the art for its time and will be the subject of future articles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Stoke Military Hospital closed in 1945 after 148 years of use, initially the buildings then became two schools, Tamar High School and Devonport High School for Boys. Tamar High was closed and absorbed into DHSB in 1989.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/dhsb.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Devonport High School for Boys, originally the Stoke Military Hospital&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;millbridge&#34;&gt;Millbridge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the building of Stonehouse Bridge, Mill Bridge was the route across Stonehouse Creek to Stonehouse and Plymouth. Nowadays its not even obvious it was a bridge at all but originally both Stonehouse Creek and Victoria Park to the North East were open bodies of water (Victoria Park was known as the rather foreboding Deadlake). In 1813 the artist Turner sketched the view North towards Stoke Damerel showing the mill and bridge in the foreground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/turner_millbridge.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Turner’s Sketch of Millbridge and Stoke Damerel in 1813. Image courtesy of the Tate.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first bridge was built in 1525 and was more of a dam to use the tidal power of the Deadlake to drive the mill. At its height the mill had three wheels driving 5 pairs of millstones however operation ended in the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Millbridge head North up Molesworth Road past Georgian and Victorian mansions to return to Stoke Village.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
