<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>software development on Ames World</title>
    <link>https://ames.world/tags/software-development/</link>
    <description>Recent content in software development on Ames World</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>MIT</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://ames.world/tags/software-development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Things I Learned From Remote Working</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/10-things-i-learned-from-remote-working/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/10-things-i-learned-from-remote-working/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally published on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.surevine.com/10-things-learnt-remote-working/&#34;&gt;surevine blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 months ago, I took the next step in my career and joined Surevine as a Team Lead. There were many things that first attracted me to the company, but one major benefit was that it’s totally remote, and so learning how to work collaboratively whilst remote was a challenge that really interested me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sureviner’s are spread all over the country, and my team alone covers a geographical area that stretches from Durham to Plymouth. Although I’m only 3 months in, you learn pretty quickly what works and doesn’t when it comes to remote work. Here’s what I have discovered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-be-specific-about-how-you-communicate&#34;&gt;1. Be specific about how you communicate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By far the most important thing I’ve found about remote work is that it’s much more necessary to be specific when you communicate. It’s far too easy to misconstrue meaning without body language clues you get from face to face. Here at Surevine the very first thing we do with new starters is talk them through &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.surevine.com/distributed-not-disengaged/&#34;&gt;how we communicate&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve seen the same thing at remote meetups such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://agileintheether.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Agile in the Ether&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Establishing ground rules at the beginning makes communication easier and more effective. The only thing that surprises me is that this isn’t more prevalent in traditional work environments. Effective communication is key to shared understanding whether you’re working remotely or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-im-so-much-more-productive&#34;&gt;2. I’m so much more productive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working in your own space with very few distractions does wonders for productivity. I’ve previously found open-plan offices can ruin an agile team’s effectiveness, and when I used to work in an office I would regularly have to work late just to have space and time to get anything done. With remote working, I’m set up just the right way for me; we use statuses a lot to show colleagues our availability meaning that finding the time in the day to get stuff done is not an issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/workspace.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;My workspace at home, set up just the way I like it, standup desk, widescreen monitor and whiteboard&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-sometimes-remote-working-just-doesnt-cut-it&#34;&gt;3. Sometimes, remote working just doesn’t cut it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no getting away from it, sometimes it’s just necessary to get together face to face. At Surevine we’re not shy about this. If it makes sense to get the team together, then we do. Booking travel and co-working spaces is simple, and we try to book spaces that are relatively central to the whole team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a policy of using trains as much as possible, as public transport is much better for the environment, but it also allows us to continue to work whilst travelling (in fact I’m writing this post on a train right now!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because people are taking the time to travel there is much more commitment to making meetings a success — nobody wants to spend a couple of hours on a train for nothing. We prepare clear agenda’s with expected outcomes, for which I tend to use the phrase ‘We will know this agenda item is complete when…’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a day to day basis, we are just starting to explore how techniques such as mob programming could work remotely to help improve collaboration, although this needs to be balanced with keeping up our productivity. But as they say, there is nothing more useless than doing something efficiently, that shouldn’t have been done at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once a quarter we get together as a company to collaborate, we call them RLMs (Real Life Meetings), which can seem rather strange, meeting someone in the flesh for the first time who you know well and work with day to day remotely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-status-updates-can-feel-a-little-paranoid-if-you-havent-used-them-before&#34;&gt;4. Status updates can feel a little paranoid if you haven’t used them before&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regularly posting what you are up to can feel weird at first, if you have come from a low trust environment it can feel as if you are being watched. Why does everyone need to know what I’m up to? What are you going to do with that data?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s not the purpose of status updates, it&amp;rsquo;s intended to show colleagues your interrupt-ability. If you’re free to take calls, set yourself to free. If you’ve gone to the kitchen to get a cup of tea, or really need to get your head down and concentrate, set an away status. It avoids your colleagues wasting time when you’re not available, and avoids you being interrupted when you need to focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-remember-to-have-some-fun&#34;&gt;5. Remember to have some fun!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Super productivity and laser clear meetings all sound great for a business, but not a lot of fun. I’ve found a few times that I have forgotten to add the human element to meetings. This runs the risk of de-energising the team and I’ve become more aware of the need to inject some fun into some meetings after all happy people are productive people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a few things we do at Surevine specifically: Nic, one of the other team leads, introduced a down tools session to just get together and hang out and get to know one another, which has grown and is now open to the whole company. On Friday’s we run ‘Techcellence’ a chance for Sureviner’s to come along and talk about whatever is of interest them, which, despite the name, can range from tech to history to food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;6-its-easy-to-be-distracted-at-home&#34;&gt;6. It’s easy to be distracted at home.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been surprised at how easily distracted I am, but it’s not uncommon. We regularly talk about techniques for getting down and focusing. Some folks like white noise, some like to use the Pomodoro technique, others (like me) like to visualise their work on a board and move things to ‘done.’ The difference from office work is that we actually talk about this stuff and look at ways to improve it. Offices are just as distracting, but rarely have I had a conversation about what I can do to make that better, it’s just accepted as part of office life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;7-remember-to-get-out-of-the-house&#34;&gt;7. Remember to get out of the house!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my first few weeks, I found I wasn’t really leaving the house and I was getting irritable and restless. It sounds obvious, but I just wasn’t spending enough time outside. Now I aim to go for a walk around my local park before starting work, and often at lunch too. The fresh air resets my brain and helps me reconnect with the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;8-one-remote-all-remote&#34;&gt;8. One remote, all remote.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We find that when working with clients who are office-based, often remote calls become a group of people huddled around a laptop. The amount this affects effective communication cannot be understated, even with standalone mics. We, therefore, try to operate a one-person remote, all remote policy to make communication more effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;9-there-is-no-perfect-video-conference-solution&#34;&gt;9. There is no perfect video conference solution.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use a whole bunch of VC tools because there’s no perfect one. Primarily we use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Hangouts — Generally easiest way to setup a VC with clients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slack calls — The pencil feature that allows everyone to draw on the screen is useful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We used to use zoom which was excellent for being able to see everyone in the call, but the recent security bug has meant we have stopped using it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;10-remote-work-makes-it-easier-to-inspect-and-adapt&#34;&gt;10. Remote work makes it easier to inspect and adapt.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best thing by far about remote work is that it’s more obvious when things aren’t as effective as they can be. Often in office environments, poor working practices and communication are accepted as the ‘norm’, whereas a remote company is wholly dependent on effective communication and working practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This forces remote teams to pay more attention and to adjust and improve. This results in teams who are extremely effective at working together and getting things done.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mountaineering and a Rant About Risk Management</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/mountaineering-and-a-rant-about-risk-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/mountaineering-and-a-rant-about-risk-management/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I love hill climbing and mountaineering, ever since I was dragged up Pen-Y-Fan and got mild hypothermia in the scouts at about the age of 13. One of the best things yomping up hills has taught me is the nature of risk. So I was a bit surprised when I saw this tweet from Vasco Duarte:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Friends, let&amp;#39;s collect a list of domains where Risk ELIMINATION is priority #1: Climbing; Air travel industry; what else? &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/modernAgile?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#modernAgile&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/agile?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#agile&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/NoEstimates?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#NoEstimates&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/lean?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#lean&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/kanban?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#kanban&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Vasco Duarte (@duarte_vasco) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/duarte_vasco/status/964122429147811841?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 15, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a lot of respect for Mr Duarte, his work in with the #NoEstimates agenda and his focus on measuring data and forecasting over, estimation and guesswork is interesting and inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However I couldn’t agree with this point and didn’t make the case well in the limitations of twitter. So in the spirit of cooperation and shared understanding I thought I would describe why I believe risk cannot be eliminated and trying to can actively slow you down and have the reverse effect. Please let me know your thoughts in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/pen-y-fan.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Pen Y Fan a mountain South Wales, covered in snow.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-youve-decided-to-go-and-climb-a-mountain&#34;&gt;So you’ve decided to go and climb a Mountain.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good for you, its great to get out into the wilderness, but are you prepared for the journey ahead? At the most basic level have you thought about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where you are going and your ability to navigate and walk the route? What the weather is going to do? How much food and drink you’ll need? How long you expect to be out for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the above you will have packed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A navigation aid of some sort&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Appropriate clothes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enough food and drink for the duration of your walk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then you think about all of the risks that could befall you on the walk.
What happens if I have an accident whilst I’m out? What if the weather turns bad? What if I run out of water? What if the river I need to cross is in spate? What if I encounter an unexpected terrain or a steep ascent?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you also pack:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A comprehensive first-aid kit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A full set of waterproofs and hat and gloves, just in case the weather turns bad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An extra canteen of water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A rope, harness and basic climbing gear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now your pack is about half as heavy again and you know you won’t be able to walk at the same speed as with a lighter pack. You’ll be out for longer, so you now need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extra food and drink&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re pack is heavier again, with a bag this size, the walk is turning into an overnight expedition so you pack:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A tent or bivouac&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sleeping bag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A stove;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enough food and drink for an overnight expedition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/heavy_load.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;2 people with severely overloaded backpacks&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of trying to eliminate all risks has significantly slowed you down and as a result exposed you to other risks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A heavier pack reduces your footing on poor terrain increasing your likelihood of injuring yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A longer trip increases the likelihood the weather will deteriorate increasing the risk of exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mountain-climbing-is-about-trade-offs&#34;&gt;Mountain climbing is about trade offs.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The definition of risk is the impact of an event versus the probability of it occurring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk = Impact * Probability.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where most risk management fails is in measuring probability effectively, a few methodologies such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imo.org/en/OurWork/safety/safetytopics/pages/formalsafetyassessment.aspx&#34;&gt;Formal Safety Assessment&lt;/a&gt; used in the maritime industry and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nrc.gov/reading-rm/doc-collections/fact-sheets/probabilistic-risk-asses.html&#34;&gt;Probabilistic Risk Assessment&lt;/a&gt; used in the nuclear industry do this reasonably well by assessing data on previous accidents and near misses, however even this doesn’t handle &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_swan_theory&#34;&gt;Black Swan&lt;/a&gt; events well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming up with a plan to eliminate all risks without understanding the likelihood of that risk occurring can actively slow you down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/simple_risk_matrix.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;A simple risk matrix, impact versus probability&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets look back at our example. I set off in May in sunshine, the forecast is a windy day with a chance of showers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a high probability of showers, the impact will be I get damp and miserable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3(P)*1(I) = 4(R)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a low probability it will snow, the impact will be I get hypothermia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1(P)*3(I) = 4(R)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The risk is the same because whilst the likelihood of snow is low, the impact is much higher.
So do I take a hat and gloves and a thicker jacket?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No because the extra gear affects the weight I need to carry and therefore energy usage. I make the trade off of lightness and speed (mitigate risk) over preparing for the risk of hypothermia with more clothes (eliminate risk).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These sorts of trade offs happen all the time when out on the hills or climbing, as maintaining speed is a more effective risk strategy than trying to eliminate all risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Policies are organizational scar tissue. They are codiﬁed overreactions to unlikely-to-happen-again situations.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jason Fried (@jasonfried) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jasonfried/status/2758624714?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 21, 2009&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eliminating all risks, even low probability, high impact ones will reduce your speed, introducing higher probabilities of things going wrong. In my experience, optimising for speed will reduce risk far more than trying to eliminate them all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know your experiences and thoughts in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving &#39;Find&#39; for the Find Property Information Service</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/improving-find-for-the-find-property-information-service/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/improving-find-for-the-find-property-information-service/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://search-property-information.service.gov.uk/&#34;&gt;Find Property Information&lt;/a&gt; is a GOV.UK service being developed by HM Land Registry which aims to provide a simple summary of property information. Recently we have improved our ‘postcode search’ functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-did-we-do-this&#34;&gt;Why did we do this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first iteration of searching was developed over a year ago, we knew the limitations of it, but it was ‘good enough’ for the early stages of the service. This allowed us to move onto developing other features. Since then the quality of search has crept up the list of user issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-were-the-problems-with-the-old-search&#34;&gt;What were the problems with the old search?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a mixture of design and technical issues with our old search:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When users come to the service they think in terms of addresses, but our search results displayed land titles. This meant the results were jarring, it was especially unclear if there was more than one ‘title’ for a given address.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We hadn’t updated the address information we get from Ordnance Survey for over a year, so new builds wouldn’t show in the service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search results were confusing because of the order of the displayed addresses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We limited search results to a maximum of 50 on the false assumption this was the terms of the Ordnance Survey Addressbase licence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/search_results_before.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Search results before improvement, results were ‘titles’ rather than addresses - which the user searched for - causing confusion.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-did-we-improve-it&#34;&gt;How did we improve it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on feedback we’d been collecting we had a good handle on the types of problems people had, and a strong hypothesis that people would be more successful if we flipped the results. We aimed to stop showing what we have got (how we’ve documented the world), and start showing a familiar model of places (how user’s think of the world).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are familiar with what a postcode is, and what it contains — they use this all the time, when they are getting a parcel delivered, or sending a letter, or using their satnav.
There is a point at which we, currently, ask people to pick a particular property record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we now do that as a separate steps. previously we had wrapped multiple decisions into one step, which was too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So whilst we still need, currently, to introduce the concept of titles and tenures, we do this in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/search_results_after.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The new search results are much clearer and align to what our users expect to see next.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-did-we-build-it&#34;&gt;How did we build it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Find Property Information team consists of 12 people from different disciplines, we sometimes struggled to communicate effectively and stay focused due to the sheer numbers of communication pathways between team members. We had a hunch that the size of the team was slowing down our delivery so we decided to use postcode search as a good opportunity to test it. We separated out 4 people to focus solely on delivering improved search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team came up with a number of technical approaches and chose the one that would deliver the most value. There were other potentially better solutions, but would have taken longer to implement. Building services is always a trade off between building what’s needed now, and envisioning future use cases. There are risks to both approaches, too bare bones and it can be difficult to change the solution in future, too blue sky and time and energy can be wasted on features and functions that aren’t actually needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the whole we saw a lot of benefits from the small team. The small size meant that our processes could be much more lightweight, much less time was spent planning and discussing work, if a problem came up or a change needed to happen, it was much easier to solve as it was just a quick chat to discuss the problem, think of how to solve it and move on.
The team progressed well and improved our address search component, built a title-api for retrieving titles per address, and ‘plugged into’ an audit-api for collating what was happening within the service for troubleshooting and audit needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we reached a point where we needed to ‘plug-in’ what had been built back into the service. We needed to consider how we could deliver the functionality that had been built iteratively into the service without getting in the way, or breaking any of the other work being done by the rest of the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;agile-doesnt-equal-no-planning&#34;&gt;Agile doesn’t equal No Planning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a reached a point where we needed to get the team back together and consider how to move postcode into the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We came up with a high-level plan to deploy each of the new api’s in a way that wouldn’t impact the service or cause any downtime. It was also an iterative plan so by breaking the releases down into small chunks we could de-risk the change and rollback easily if any particular part did go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/whiteboarding.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Planning agile style, team members gathered around a whiteboard&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also wanted to assure ourselves that the search was as good as we thought it would be so we included: a comprehensive set of automated acceptance tests; manual eyeballing; and tests to verify our hypothesis of what we expected to happen when the changes were in production.
The hardest part of testing was finding a decent baseline to ‘prove our search was good. We knew our existing search was inconsistent so it made for a very poor baseline. We had other services that also had search functionality so we did some investigation into these services to test their viability as baselines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we found was that whilst on the whole they were good enough as a baseline, they all had slight discrepancies or weird results mainly due to data quality either from us or from our address suppliers. The Addressbase dataset has over 28 million address points, and our register data is over 24 million titles. Both of these datasets change daily and when they are as large as that even a 1% error rate can equal hundreds of thousands of data rows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Improving the quality of these two datasets wasn’t going to be possible so instead we attempted to understand the problems a bit better so that at least if users did encounter issues we could offer them an onward journey or understand why. We produced a ‘wall of weird’ of postcodes we knew behaved strangely in existing services and added these to our test baseline to see what happened in our service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/wall_of_weird.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The wall of weird, a whiteboard where we captured all the strange search behaviour we identified, so that we could validate we had fixed them as we improved the service.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-did-we-release-it&#34;&gt;How did we release it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we had a test and deploy plan that was detailed enough to give us direction, but lightweight enough to change when things inevitably changed or went wrong. And a few things did go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We hoped to release an updated address index into the service as a standalone iteration. However, when testing it, we found it had more of an impact on the user experience than we were comfortable with, so we had to bundle the change in with the ‘main’ release.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a result the main release became bigger than expected and we had to schedule in downtime, adding a number of additional steps and approvals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We found the title-api performed within thresholds but not as well as we would like, we found that search results had spikes of long response times. Whilst only affecting 2% of users, scaling up to actual usage volumes could equal hundreds of unsatisfied people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That final problem was the biggest challenge we faced, we hadn’t seen it in any of our lower test environments, but then again our pre-prod environment is the one that most resembles live. At first we didn’t have a good handle on exactly how big the issue was so we created some performance scripts to allow us to monitor response times whilst under heavy load. The scripts confirmed the scale of what we were seeing, but didn’t give us any further clues as to what was causing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally we decided that the benefits of the new search functionality exceeded the risks of some users having slow performance. We came up with a plan for measuring production performance and agreed to set some time aside to improve it should we see it happening in PROD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally we were in a position where we were ready to release. We had to turn the service off for an hour but pre-warned users of the downtime. The change itself went very smoothly and we were deployed and tested within 50 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-do-we-know-whether-it-has-been-successful&#34;&gt;How do we know whether it has been successful?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The measure of success that was most pressing was whether PROD would see the same performance issues that we saw in the test environment. It took a few days to build a sample of traffic but sure enough we did see the same problem. By then however we had given a bit more thought as to a plan for improving the performance. After the first release the refactored code went into production, drastically improving performance times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/before_performance.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Initial performance times, good but not excellent. Most responses within 2 seconds&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial performance times, good but not excellent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/after_performance.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Production responses following improvements, most responses in under 0.1 seconds!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Production responses following improvements, note the change in scale!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of our hypotheses of what would happen in Production have so far played out to be true:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the sample we tested our search is as good as existing HMLR services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Addresses changed in the past year now return in our search results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our new audit-api is collecting audit data successfully.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important change is that search is dropping down our ‘Top issues for our users’ chart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-next&#34;&gt;Whats next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will continue to learn more about how search is performing in the service, shipping to Production is the only true point where you really start to learn about how people use your service and how it works at scale so I’m sure we will need to make a few changes based on feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also have some work we want to do, to replace our address component with an address-api that is being built by colleagues in another team. This ‘common component’ will reduce maintenance overhead and ensure more consistency between services in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
