<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Ames World</title>
    <link>https://ames.world/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Ames World</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>MIT</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://ames.world/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What Would a Great Onboarding Experience Look Like?</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/what-would-a-great-onboarding-experience-look-like/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/what-would-a-great-onboarding-experience-look-like/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I joined Surevine my onboarding experience was fantastic, but I wanted to see if there was anything more we could do to make it even better, so back in June I asked twitter what would a great onboarding experience look like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always the responses were great. This post summarises what I learned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;onboarding-starts-way-before-a-person-joins-a-company&#34;&gt;Onboarding starts way before a person joins a company&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone wants to work with you, they will be thinking about it way before onboarding starts. When people are looking for a new job, they want to know what a company is like to work for, almost as much as the salary and perks. No one wants to work somewhere that&amp;rsquo;s not going to motivate them or make them miserable. Sharing how you work as a company gives candidates an insight into the sort of organisation you are, and whether they might want to work there. Blogs and videos about how you work and publishing your company handbook on the web are great ways to provide that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interviews are an important part of building a great experience. All too often it’s forgotten that interviews are a two-way process. The candidate is assessing your company too. If they don’t like what they see, they won’t accept, and worse still they’ll pass on their experience to their peers. At Surevine we try to make interviews as realistic as possible, but fun too. We run “Day in the life” interviews, a chance for a candidate to show how they would work with the team on a real-world scenario. The whole team then gets to know the candidate and see what they can bring to the team in a real practical sense. Most importantly, it gives the candidate a real insight into how we work that traditional interviews do not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as Josh Abbot points out, all too often someone is successful and offered a job, and then they hear nothing but silence whilst they work off their notice, sometimes for months. This can be really disconcerting, so make sure to keep in regular contact. Use the time to introduce other people in the company to the new person in a way that&amp;rsquo;s pressure-free and without expectation, they don’t work for you yet!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;It’s a great point Ian and something thats often overlooked. Personally I think “onboarding” should start before your first day. All too many people now have 3 month notice periods and that time gap can cause all sorts of issues....&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Josh Abbott (@JoshDigitalTech) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/JoshDigitalTech/status/1139777258925805569?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 15, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure you use the time to get the new person setup on all the systems they will use, there is nothing more disheartening than starting a new role and not be able to access anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Get them set up on all the company systems before they get there. Makes such a difference to being able to get settled in the first few days.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Roger Swannell (@rogerswannell) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rogerswannell/status/1139599891699818497?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 14, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-first-day&#34;&gt;The first day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was so much good advice given on making the first day a success. Luke R suggested making the first day a Wednesday to reduce the cognitive load of the first week, and to ensure they you aren’t distracted by the inevitable Monday interruptions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Have found starting people on a Wednesday not a Monday helps. Day 1 meet and greet, Day 2 this is your role etc, Day 3 work at home and do mandatory training. Weekend to recover. 5 days in a new role is overload before starting&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Luke Radford (@radfordln) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/radfordln/status/1139578762834665472?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 14, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strong trend was people wanted to know what the companies history, mission and strategy was and how they contributed to it, this was the most overriding theme in the feedback:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;“What are your/the high-level goals?” I want to know how you see the big picture, and also that there’s high-level buy-in to solve it. Without that, it’s often hard to do anything meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Simon Worthington (@51M0NW) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/51M0NW/status/1139598199243628544?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 14, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;- corporate strategy and other guidances, &amp;#39;&amp;#39;purpose&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&lt;br&gt;- what they want me to do / expect from me (results, communication, way of working, tools to use etc), &amp;#39;&amp;#39;needs&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&lt;br&gt;- org structure, who&amp;#39;s who, team(s) to work with, anything that I should be aware, &amp;#39;&amp;#39;who&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Akiko Kato (@somewellplus) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/somewellplus/status/1139654309887598594?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 14, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I like at lot of what others are saying. Culture, history, values.&lt;br&gt;Communication channels and expectations.&lt;br&gt;Security details like users / email etc and access to them.&lt;br&gt;What you can say no to.&lt;br&gt;Any regular meetings.&lt;br&gt;Any team members with specific needs or preferences.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; harry bailey (@HarryBailey) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/HarryBailey/status/1139589337417494530?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 14, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;1. Company history, values, culture &amp;amp; vision&lt;br&gt;2. Office tour - where everything is and how to use things like the fancy coffee maker!&lt;br&gt;3. Meet the team&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Trainual (@trainual) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/trainual/status/1139576906662027265?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 14, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was closely followed by more pragmatic advice such as, where can I get good coffee, how do I communicate with my team, what are the unwritten rules of the company, and where are the toilets!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;1. Where’s good coffee&lt;br&gt;2. The important stakeholders (and politics/management lines)&lt;br&gt;3. Institutional blockers&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Deadliftbear (@deadliftbear) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/deadliftbear/status/1139577282568294400?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 14, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;- The expectations of your output over the first couple of weeks.&lt;br&gt;- Who you ask when you have a question.&lt;br&gt;- office access and layout. Toilets, kitchen, meeting etc.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;All essentially hygiene items, but then 3 is nowhere near enough.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; harry bailey (@HarryBailey) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/HarryBailey/status/1139585708736360448?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 14, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;What’s the dress code?&lt;br&gt;Do I bring my own coffee mug? &lt;br&gt;What do people do for lunch?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You’ll tell me what to do, I want to know how to do it and what’s the culture.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; nicola_tallett (@nicola_tallett) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nicola_tallett/status/1139615220559765505?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 14, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Great question. 1. Time with each team member. 2. Systems &amp;amp; processes that will help me work. 3. Loos, coffee point/cafes, meeting spaces.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ed Griffin (@EdjGriffin) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/EdjGriffin/status/1139803268148633601?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 15, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great template for sharing the important day to day stuff with new starters is &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@hiresarahcarter&#34;&gt;Sarah Carter’s&lt;/a&gt; induction &lt;a href=&#34;https://trello.com/b/8AEffW1t/dragon-age-induction-board&#34;&gt;trello board&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve borrowed this board a number of times, including at Surevine, and it saves me so much time remembering to collate the useful but small information that gets forgotten about once you have been somewhere more than a couple of weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each new person can make their own copy and refer back to it over time, and it can get constantly refined and improved based on feedback. I couldn’t recommend it enough. In fact, if you want good advice on anything recruitment or people based follow Sarah!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/induction_board.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;A screenshot of Sarah Carter’s induction board, the default template is tongue in cheek based on Dragon Age!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;buddying-up&#34;&gt;Buddying up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a lot of suggestions to give people a buddy. Sometimes it can be intimidating asking questions of your direct report, even if you try to make it not the case. Having a buddy gives the new person someone they can ask the ‘stupid questions’ without fear of looking or feeling stupid. It helps them to get to know another face in the company too and to get a perspective that they may not get from you. It’s a great way to develop existing peoples leadership skills too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spending time with the team was high on the list, giving the team and the new candidate the chance to bond and get to know each other is really important. Going out for lunch together on the first day or week is a great way to form relationships without the distractions of the office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Hey Ian nice to meet you. 👋 Coming from a big consulting firm, first the Timesheet, knowing your Gallup strengths and everyone gets a brother or sister to help you. 😊&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; leeeshaari (@leeesdesign) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/leeesdesign/status/1139777536827826177?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 15, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Have some set tasks and training goals prepared, and a first day team lunch is always a good idea&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Sophie Ashcroft (@ms_s_ashcroft) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ms_s_ashcroft/status/1139843154562211841?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 15, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this post is useful if you are looking to improve your hiring processes, happily most of the suggestions were already implemented at Surevine, but we have made some changes based on the feedback to help improve our onboarding experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on Map Camp</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/reflections-on-map-camp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/reflections-on-map-camp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year I was finally able to attend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.map-camp.com/_pages/2019-10-15_London/&#34;&gt;MapCamp 2019&lt;/a&gt; with ~600 other people at Sadlers Wells Theatre, London. MapCamp is a conference introducing and describing the technique of &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/wardleymaps/on-being-lost-2ef5f05eb1ec&#34;&gt;Wardley Mapping&lt;/a&gt;, a tool for mapping strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first came across Wardley Maps a couple of years ago through the medium book. I found it compelling, Simon Wardley has a lovely humble style of writing. He described how he went from ‘bumbling CEO’ to ‘having a vague idea of what I was doing’. That self-deprecating style just drew me in, and I found a lot I could relate to in my work. However, I could never get the hang of mapping and I hoped going to MapCamp would help me have that aha! moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MapCamp started bright and early at 08:45. Simon opened the event with a condensed version of his classic example of the battle of Thermopylae as described by that staple of business, the SWOT diagram. He highlighted how traditional business tools failed to provide a sense of space and purpose (movement).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/swot_thermopylae.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;A topographical map of the battle of Thermopylae alongside a tongue-in-cheek SWOT analysis of the battle. It makes the case that the SWOT diagram fails to give any insight into what to do next. Credit: Simon Wardley&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t come across a Wardley map before, it is a sort of value chain map on steroids, it starts at user needs and branches out down the chain to all of the components required to deliver that need. As with a value chain, the things closest to user needs are the most visible. However, what it also maps is where each of those components is in their lifecycle. By adding this detail, and the direction the component is moving on the map (are you, or your competitors, moving from being custom-built to a product for example) you are able to make decisions on the best approach to take to developing or managing the component and where to invest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/service_wardley_map.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;An example map showing components of a service, and where they are in their evolution. From there you can choose what approach to take for each component. Credit: Simon Wardley&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/wardley_patterns.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Example patterns to apply to components depending on where they are in their evolution. Credit Simon Wardley&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simon quickly re-iterated the basics of a map, before introducing the first speakers, &lt;a href=&#34;https://salfreudenberg.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Dr Sal Freudenberg&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@mrchrisadams&#34;&gt;Chris Adams&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;climate-change-and-mapping--sal-freudenberg-and-chris-adams&#34;&gt;Climate change and Mapping — Sal Freudenberg and Chris Adams&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sal opened their talk by describing the extent of the climate crisis and the work she has been doing with &lt;a href=&#34;https://extinctionrebellion.uk/&#34;&gt;Extinction Rebellion&lt;/a&gt; to raise awareness and push for action. Her talk was all at once terrifying and inspiring and set the scene nicely to introduce the work Chris has been doing to use maps to highlight what impact a strategy can have on climate change. He introduced two strategies, firstly identify components that can be commoditised, commodities are more efficient through economies of scale and therefore use less CO2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/chris_adams.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Chris Adams describing strategy one for lowering CO2, move components towards commodity services.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strategy 2 is to actively green your service if you are already working out the cost to provide your service, then there are stats available from the ONS to work out the carbon cost. I didn’t catch the citation but Chris said that the ONS estimated that every £10,000 of cost has a 3.2-tonne CO2 cost. Therefore it is possible to calculate the environmental impact of your business and use a map to identify where moving components to cheaper provision, or specific green providers can have an impact on your businesses carbon budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/chris_adams2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Chris Adams describing strategy two for lowering CO2, identify components that can be ‘greened’&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key insight.&lt;/em&gt; Chris raised the point that if developers were builders they are expected to know about things that are harmful to their customers, such as asbestos. Shouldn’t we have similar expectations of software engineers that we know the impact or potential harm of the tools and materials of their trade?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-best-move--andrew-clay-shafer&#34;&gt;What is the best move? — Andrew Clay Shafer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up was &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@littleidea&#34;&gt;Andrew Clay Shafer&lt;/a&gt;, there were a few moments at MapCamp when I could feel my brain being stretched in new and unexpected ways, and Andrews talk was the first. I found his presenting style difficult, but that forced me to pay attention. I don’t confess to understand all of it, it was a sort of well-ordered stream of consciousness, and yet it is the presentation I made the most amount of notes on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He started by talking about how a normal human can become fluent in a new language in 6 months, but most won’t because our needs are met — We only learn anything to the level we need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two kinds of players:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Players who want things to be better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Players who want better for themselves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So play a different game based on the type of person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/andrew_clay_shafer.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Andrew Clay Shafer highlighting factors that determine peoples (and organisations) individual motivations&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aha! Went my little brain, of course! I have a tendency to naively assume everyone wants things to be better (most people do in my experience) but thats not always the case. Also, my idea of better may not be the same as someone else&amp;rsquo;s. Find out about who you are playing with before deciding how to play with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew moved on to talk about OODA loops (Observe, Orient, Decide, Act) which was developed by Air Force Colonel John Boyd to improve aerial combat strategies. One thing Andrew said made my brain pop again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going faster without a model to measure against is useless&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and most interestingly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sampling too much is spending time and resources you might not have, and may cause inaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second point resonated with me, I have seen many projects get stuck in analysis-paralysis because the fear of the unknown has been more prevalent than choosing a direction and observing what happens. I think if I’m honest with myself often those measures have been derived on gut feel rather than alignment to any perceived strategy beyond the vision of the project, something to dwell on more (but not so much I move into inaction!!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key insight.&lt;/em&gt; Think about what your competitors are doing when producing a map, what gaps or opportunities do the directions they take present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;open-source-and-maps--adrian-cockcroft&#34;&gt;Open Source and Maps — Adrian Cockcroft&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up was &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@adrianco&#34;&gt;Adrian Cockcroft&lt;/a&gt; who I was very excited to see as his work at NetFlix was some of the first things I read when moving my thinking from ITIL based robustness to Devops based resilience and responsiveness. Adrian is now at AWS and he described some of the working practices there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a lot of ideas in there that I liked and have strongly advocated for myself, such as service-based multi-disciplinary teams and a ‘you wrote it, you run it’ culture. What I found most interesting was that they separated ‘Product’ and ‘Business’ as two distinct areas to integrate into the team, the responsibilities listed under ‘Business’ were ones I always assumed to be the responsibility of a delivery lead, it made me think more about where my role sits in other peoples perceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/adrian_cockcroft.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Adrian’s tongue in cheek BusProdDevOps slide. What I found most interesting was the separation of ‘Business’ and ‘Product’, most of the Business accountabilities are what I always associate with ‘Delivery’.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another subject that caught my mind was Amazon’s approach to reporting, reporting occurred weekly to the following schedule:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Monday — Service Team.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review last weeks operations dashboards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review last weeks revenue/growth/goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tuesday — Groups of Services.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roll up the reviews&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wednesday — CEO/VP level view of everything.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review all operations, spin the wheel, learnings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review entire business revenue/growth/goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first thought was “jeez that’s a lot of reporting overhead, how do they find any time to get any work done?” There were three things in retrospect that I could see make this manageable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/adrian_cockcroft2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The AWS weekly reporting cycle.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly as with software (and nearly everything), shorter cadences don’t necessarily mean more gets done, just that focus stays on what’s important. A weekly report would be much smaller in size than a fortnightly or monthly report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it was clear in the language that the team had responsibility for hitting their goals, this reporting wasn’t a report up and absolve responsibility setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally and most interestingly was the ‘roulette wheel of reporting’ at senior level. As with any large organisation, it’s impossible to be on top of all things all the time. The roulette wheel has all the service team names on it, every week the wheel is spun and whichever team is landed upon reports to senior management. This means all teams need to be prepared each week to report but reduces reporting overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key insight.&lt;/em&gt; I can see how the ‘trust but verify’ model of reporting could save a lot of overhead time but still provide assurances things are being managed the right way, its one to keep in mind as we expand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;capability-mapping--emily-webber&#34;&gt;Capability Mapping — Emily Webber&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up was &lt;a href=&#34;https://emilywebber.co.uk/about-me/&#34;&gt;Emily Webber&lt;/a&gt; describing her approach to mapping capabilities and skills in organisations. I’m privileged enough to have worked with Emily first hand when she helped the Delivery Community at Land Registry to map our capabilities and skills. The presentation was a good reminder of the principles and practices of building good communities of practice and there was a tons of practical advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly Emily described the difference between skills and capabilities, the two are used interchangeably often but the distinction helps to judge where a person is in their development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skills are abilities that people can learn, develop and demonstrate.
Capabilities are the application of knowledge, skills and experience to achieve an outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capabilities can be assessed through 3 ‘lenses’, What capabilities does a person demonstrate individually, for their team, or for their practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/emily_webber.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Emily’s capability lenses, and the focus areas for short, medium and long term development.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These lenses can then be used to identify development needs for &lt;em&gt;Now&lt;/em&gt; (0–6 months), &lt;em&gt;Next&lt;/em&gt; (6–24 months), and &lt;em&gt;Future&lt;/em&gt; (2–5 years). Individual and team needs are often easily identified but practice needs can develop in isolation and un-aligned to organisational needs without a community of practice. Communities of practice are a group of people in the same role, but may not work together day to day, for example all the testers in the organisation would make a sensible test community of practice, in that community they can share approaches taken to solve common problems, share standard approaches, and advocate for particular training or tooling needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily then moved onto how to identify the capabilities of a Community of Practice, in 3 steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, she asks, 3 questions of the group:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you do day to day?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What don’t you do that you think you should?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you do, that you think you shouldn’t?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, she identified the themes, what are the common capabilities that emerge for that practice (and what are the practices that are being done by that community, which should probably be done elsewhere).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/emily_webber2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Some of my old colleagues front and centre in Emily’s presentation, woo!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, an assessment is done to discover, what skills are needed to do these things well. The assessment has 4 assessments for each skill and capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have no experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can follow others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can do it on my own&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can lead on this&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and finally an indicator of whether this is an area the individual wants to develop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/emily_webber3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The 4 questions to ask when assessing skills and capabilities, as listed above.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By collecting this up, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to see areas to focus deliberate practice, training, and recruitment for skills. In my experience this worked well at HMLR it gave us to focus as a community on common areas for development and allowed us to act as a collective to advocate for training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been thinking about how to apply this model to Surevine where our ‘communities’ are much smaller, usually no more than 2 or 3 people, I also wonder if applying some ideas from Wardley mapping such as visibility, and how developed a capability may be to help make decisions on how a practice may be developing and where to focus for future needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key insight.&lt;/em&gt; Putting the good things I learnt with Emily into practice at a smaller organisation should be possible, but it will be interesting to see what different approaches we take to community development where our communities are single digits in size, and lots of people identify as ‘multidisciplinary’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mapping-as-a-sensemaking-practice-within-digital-ecosystems--roser-pujades&#34;&gt;Mapping as a sensemaking practice within digital ecosystems — Roser Pujades&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lse.ac.uk/management/people/academic-staff/rpujadas&#34;&gt;Roser Pujades&lt;/a&gt; from UCL. Roser provided perhaps my biggest insight from the day. Perhaps because of the way that the Wardley Maps book is written (Simon, moves from unclear CEO to using mapping to understand the strategy and succeed) it&amp;rsquo;s a very personal context, I always associated Wardley mapping as a personal, isolated activity. Amongst other things Roser made it clear that mapping is more powerful when done as a group activity, its a canvas to define a perspective and to be challenged and changed, the more knowledge and experience that goes into it the more accurate it will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roser also proposed an extension to maps to show ubiquity, how many are providing this or working on this problem, seemed sensible although the prospect of 3d maps when I’m struggling with the 2d versions made my head melt a little bit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/roser_pujades.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Roser’s proposed 3D Wardley Map to demonstrate Ubiquity.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key insight.&lt;/em&gt; As with most things in life, mapping works best as a group effort, something I hadn’t thought about before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;managing-for-serendipity--liz-keogh&#34;&gt;Managing for Serendipity — Liz Keogh&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lizkeogh.com&#34;&gt;Liz Keogh&lt;/a&gt; is another personal hero, her excellent blog posts on &lt;a href=&#34;https://lizkeogh.com/cynefin-for-everyone/&#34;&gt;Cynefin&lt;/a&gt; have really helped me get to a good understanding of the sense-making framework. I’ve personally found Cynefin easier to understand and use than Wardley Mapping, probably because in my day to day work I’m more involved in project delivery than strategy. Cynefin is a great tool to move beyond cargo cult agile and to use an appropriate framework depending on whether your project is obvious, complicated, complex, or chaotic. Having early conversations about this helps to pick an appropriate approach and avoids misunderstanding later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/liz_keogh.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Liz describing the Cynefin framework and the most appropriate approach to sense-making for each domain.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liz’s talk focused on the Complex domain, she used Ludicorp as an example. Ludicorp released a web-based MMO called Game Neverending, in it players could share photos and chat. This feature was far more successful than the game itself so the company pivoted and Flickr was born. Similarly the IM tool Slack emerged from the online game Glitch. These were both good examples of managing in a complex domain, where it is necessary to probe-sense-respond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My go-to approach has always been to use the lean startup approach, formulate a hypothesis, build something to test hypothesis, analyse and change based on whether hypothesise is true or not. Liz introduced another brain warping moment, it is better to measure for coherence than a hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What! Sacrilege! Hypothesis are the foundation of the scientific method, how can this be wrong, screamed my brain. But hypothesis assumes a certain amount of certainty, you need to know something about a system in order to make a hypothesis about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/liz_keogh2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Liz describing coherence and why in uncertainty it may be more useful than hypothesis.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liz described Coherence as “A realistic reason for thinking our probe might have a positive impact — a sufficiency of the evidence to progress.” Hypotheses generally measure one thing. If we change x we expect to see y happen. Liz’s point was in uncertainty it is necessary to be broader, it takes a number of probes (with associated hypothesis) to make sense in uncertainty, don’t rely on single measures and don’t be afraid of having just enough evidence to proceed, i.e. not every hypothesis needs to be successful to provide evidence to continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key insight.&lt;/em&gt; Find more people to challenge my thinking!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;maps-and-security--mario-platt&#34;&gt;Maps and Security — Mario Platt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After lunch I went to the practical session on Mapping and Security it turned out to be another presentation rather than an exercise but none the less useful for it. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.securitydifferently.com/&#34;&gt;Mario Platt&lt;/a&gt; talked us through how he had used maps to identify trends in infosec. It showed how maps could be used for skills mapping, which led nicely from Emily’s earlier talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/mario_platt.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Mario describing examples of resilient and robust approaches in InfoSec.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mario also used maps to show security trends, and showed how robust solutions were now primarily commodity services, I was surprised resilient solutions were mapped as genesis/custom-built, it feels like we have been talking about resilience &amp;gt; robustness for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key insight.&lt;/em&gt; Security moves slow!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;maps-and-the-un--mark-craddock&#34;&gt;Maps and the UN — Mark Craddock&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I snuck out of the Maps and Security session slightly early to see &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mcraddock&#34;&gt;Mark Craddock&lt;/a&gt; talk about the work the UN has been doing to use mapping in the UN to come up with a data strategy that aligned to the UN’s 17 sustainable development goals. Here the sheer scale of what Mark was describing, trying to get different data agencies from across the globe working towards common goals, really blew my mind, trying to get an organisation to work towards the same goals feels hard enough sometimes. Mark spoke about using mapping to think about business models in platform terms, identifying movement towards commoditisation to enable rapid innovation by focusing on the stuff that&amp;rsquo;s core to what they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/mark_craddock.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Mark stating NCSC research showing serverless makes security easier in the cloud.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark gave an example of census costs in different countries, in the UK the forthcoming census has an estimated cost of £900m and only happens once every 10 years. Meanwhile, in Denmark, their citizen data is much better structured and managed so they can run the equivalent of a census with an overnight batch job (I paraphrase as I didn’t catch the exact time but it was days not years).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally and interestingly Mark introduced a way where you can help get involved in mapping parts of the UN strategy, something I’m going to look into as a way of practising Wardley Mapping, you can find out more at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1wDoDSeSRwCMtYxRoT8mSGga1Z-d3sx-FG2ekW4isr-A/edit&#34;&gt;UN Global Platform handbook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key insight.&lt;/em&gt; Platform thinking aligned to Wardley Mapping makes a lot of sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;beginning-your-mapping-journey--chris-daniel&#34;&gt;Beginning your mapping journey — Chris Daniel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my final session of the day, I went to the practical session led by a very lively and engaging &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/wardleymaps&#34;&gt;Chris Daniel&lt;/a&gt;. He gave us a quick overview of mapping with some basic examples of where different examples would fall on the evolution scale. He then asked us to break into teams and map the ‘Perfect New Years Party.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our merry band quickly came up with the idea of providing a place to leave kids for a new years celebration, which seemed like a unique enough angle as most other teams were aiming at the adult market. We found quickly that most of our ideas fell into the commodity space and we got a little stuck at that point, but as we plugged away at it we started to think about what was likely to be our high costs areas, and how could we innovate towards reducing them, leading inevitably perhaps to IOT robot Carers on the Blockchain. &lt;a href=&#34;https://strategy-madlibs.herokuapp.com/&#34;&gt;Strategy Generator&lt;/a&gt; would have been proud!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/chris_daniel.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Our attempted Wardley Map for ‘Saasy NYE’ - Sitters as a service.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key insight.&lt;/em&gt; As I had started to learn throughout the day, doing the exercise as a group worked much better than my previous lone attempts at mapping. It became most useful after we had mapped what we thought the current landscape was and started to ask ourselves, so what next? A point I hadn’t reached before on my own, and where I suspect its real benefit lies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this post gives you an idea of what MapCamp was about, I certainly feel like I learnt more about what mapping is, and more importantly some different approaches from where I was getting stuck, most obviously not doing it on my own. If you were there, what were your key insights?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Things I Learned From Remote Working</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/10-things-i-learned-from-remote-working/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/10-things-i-learned-from-remote-working/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally published on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.surevine.com/10-things-learnt-remote-working/&#34;&gt;surevine blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 months ago, I took the next step in my career and joined Surevine as a Team Lead. There were many things that first attracted me to the company, but one major benefit was that it’s totally remote, and so learning how to work collaboratively whilst remote was a challenge that really interested me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sureviner’s are spread all over the country, and my team alone covers a geographical area that stretches from Durham to Plymouth. Although I’m only 3 months in, you learn pretty quickly what works and doesn’t when it comes to remote work. Here’s what I have discovered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-be-specific-about-how-you-communicate&#34;&gt;1. Be specific about how you communicate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By far the most important thing I’ve found about remote work is that it’s much more necessary to be specific when you communicate. It’s far too easy to misconstrue meaning without body language clues you get from face to face. Here at Surevine the very first thing we do with new starters is talk them through &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.surevine.com/distributed-not-disengaged/&#34;&gt;how we communicate&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve seen the same thing at remote meetups such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://agileintheether.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Agile in the Ether&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Establishing ground rules at the beginning makes communication easier and more effective. The only thing that surprises me is that this isn’t more prevalent in traditional work environments. Effective communication is key to shared understanding whether you’re working remotely or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-im-so-much-more-productive&#34;&gt;2. I’m so much more productive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working in your own space with very few distractions does wonders for productivity. I’ve previously found open-plan offices can ruin an agile team’s effectiveness, and when I used to work in an office I would regularly have to work late just to have space and time to get anything done. With remote working, I’m set up just the right way for me; we use statuses a lot to show colleagues our availability meaning that finding the time in the day to get stuff done is not an issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/workspace.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;My workspace at home, set up just the way I like it, standup desk, widescreen monitor and whiteboard&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-sometimes-remote-working-just-doesnt-cut-it&#34;&gt;3. Sometimes, remote working just doesn’t cut it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no getting away from it, sometimes it’s just necessary to get together face to face. At Surevine we’re not shy about this. If it makes sense to get the team together, then we do. Booking travel and co-working spaces is simple, and we try to book spaces that are relatively central to the whole team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a policy of using trains as much as possible, as public transport is much better for the environment, but it also allows us to continue to work whilst travelling (in fact I’m writing this post on a train right now!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because people are taking the time to travel there is much more commitment to making meetings a success — nobody wants to spend a couple of hours on a train for nothing. We prepare clear agenda’s with expected outcomes, for which I tend to use the phrase ‘We will know this agenda item is complete when…’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a day to day basis, we are just starting to explore how techniques such as mob programming could work remotely to help improve collaboration, although this needs to be balanced with keeping up our productivity. But as they say, there is nothing more useless than doing something efficiently, that shouldn’t have been done at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once a quarter we get together as a company to collaborate, we call them RLMs (Real Life Meetings), which can seem rather strange, meeting someone in the flesh for the first time who you know well and work with day to day remotely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-status-updates-can-feel-a-little-paranoid-if-you-havent-used-them-before&#34;&gt;4. Status updates can feel a little paranoid if you haven’t used them before&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regularly posting what you are up to can feel weird at first, if you have come from a low trust environment it can feel as if you are being watched. Why does everyone need to know what I’m up to? What are you going to do with that data?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s not the purpose of status updates, it&amp;rsquo;s intended to show colleagues your interrupt-ability. If you’re free to take calls, set yourself to free. If you’ve gone to the kitchen to get a cup of tea, or really need to get your head down and concentrate, set an away status. It avoids your colleagues wasting time when you’re not available, and avoids you being interrupted when you need to focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-remember-to-have-some-fun&#34;&gt;5. Remember to have some fun!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Super productivity and laser clear meetings all sound great for a business, but not a lot of fun. I’ve found a few times that I have forgotten to add the human element to meetings. This runs the risk of de-energising the team and I’ve become more aware of the need to inject some fun into some meetings after all happy people are productive people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a few things we do at Surevine specifically: Nic, one of the other team leads, introduced a down tools session to just get together and hang out and get to know one another, which has grown and is now open to the whole company. On Friday’s we run ‘Techcellence’ a chance for Sureviner’s to come along and talk about whatever is of interest them, which, despite the name, can range from tech to history to food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;6-its-easy-to-be-distracted-at-home&#34;&gt;6. It’s easy to be distracted at home.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been surprised at how easily distracted I am, but it’s not uncommon. We regularly talk about techniques for getting down and focusing. Some folks like white noise, some like to use the Pomodoro technique, others (like me) like to visualise their work on a board and move things to ‘done.’ The difference from office work is that we actually talk about this stuff and look at ways to improve it. Offices are just as distracting, but rarely have I had a conversation about what I can do to make that better, it’s just accepted as part of office life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;7-remember-to-get-out-of-the-house&#34;&gt;7. Remember to get out of the house!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my first few weeks, I found I wasn’t really leaving the house and I was getting irritable and restless. It sounds obvious, but I just wasn’t spending enough time outside. Now I aim to go for a walk around my local park before starting work, and often at lunch too. The fresh air resets my brain and helps me reconnect with the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;8-one-remote-all-remote&#34;&gt;8. One remote, all remote.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We find that when working with clients who are office-based, often remote calls become a group of people huddled around a laptop. The amount this affects effective communication cannot be understated, even with standalone mics. We, therefore, try to operate a one-person remote, all remote policy to make communication more effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;9-there-is-no-perfect-video-conference-solution&#34;&gt;9. There is no perfect video conference solution.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use a whole bunch of VC tools because there’s no perfect one. Primarily we use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Hangouts — Generally easiest way to setup a VC with clients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slack calls — The pencil feature that allows everyone to draw on the screen is useful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We used to use zoom which was excellent for being able to see everyone in the call, but the recent security bug has meant we have stopped using it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;10-remote-work-makes-it-easier-to-inspect-and-adapt&#34;&gt;10. Remote work makes it easier to inspect and adapt.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best thing by far about remote work is that it’s more obvious when things aren’t as effective as they can be. Often in office environments, poor working practices and communication are accepted as the ‘norm’, whereas a remote company is wholly dependent on effective communication and working practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This forces remote teams to pay more attention and to adjust and improve. This results in teams who are extremely effective at working together and getting things done.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Story Crowdsourcing Game</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/story-crowdsourcing-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/story-crowdsourcing-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Emily Webber recently asked if I could run an 8-minute workshop to energise people at the beginning of her regular &lt;a href=&#34;https://agileintheether.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Agile in the Ether remote meetup&lt;/a&gt;. (It is a very friendly meetup and well worth checking out).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/agile_ether.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Screenshot of the Agile in the Ether attendees&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the detail of the game I facilitated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objective&#34;&gt;Objective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell a story that develops iteratively and everyone in the group contributes to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruction&#34;&gt;Instruction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each person adds a sentence to a story, but has to repeat the preceding sentences first, then nominates the next person to go. (It may help for the facilitator to start).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Person 1: ‘Once upon a time there was a girl called Sam.’&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Person 2: ‘Once upon a time there was a girl called Sam. She liked to ride bikes.’&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Person 3: ‘Once upon a time there was a girl called Sam. She liked to ride bikes. Especially Harley Davidson’s.’&lt;/em&gt;
etc etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-this-demonstrates&#34;&gt;What this demonstrates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How something can change in unexpected ways when you iterate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How continually adding can slow down and break things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The challenge of communication in large groups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cognitive load (remembering all the sentences towards the end).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing things down (documentation) can sometimes help for complex tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;feedback&#34;&gt;Feedback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback in the session was positive, attendees felt it was a good icebreaker and a good simple introduction to complexity. If you run this too, let me know how it went in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IPv4 Addressing</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/ipv4-addressing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/ipv4-addressing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I briefly touched on IPv4 addresses in the TCP/IP suite. In summary IPv4 addresses are:
Dot-separated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;32 bits long and represented in decimal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are just over 4 billion available addresses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore it is necessary to use subnetting to separate networks and duplicate IP addresses from one another.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/ipv4-binary.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;An IPv4 address shown in both binary and decimal dot notations&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ipv4-structure-and-what-it-represents&#34;&gt;IPv4 structure and what it represents&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we know IP addresses are 32 bits long and that they are separated into 4 decimal numbers by dot separation (this is known as dotted decimal), therefore each number must represent 8bits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as a reminder a bit is a binary digit, it can only represent a 0 or 1.
Each 8 bit group is called an octet. If we were to look at the dotted decimal number 192.168.2.1 in binary it would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11000000.10101000.00000010.00000001&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait what how did we make that leap? If you haven’t worked with binary before this can be a bit of a curveball. The best way I think of binary is to imagine how counting would have evolved if instead of 10 fingers we only had one on each hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So humans count in base 10 (decimal) because fingers, whereas computers, count in Base 2 (binary) because computers are basically a bucket load of on and off switches.
So if we look at one octet that is all 1’s (and I’m pushing the limits of medium’s formatting here):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;would be equal to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2⁷ + 2⁶ + 2⁵ + 2⁴ + 2³ + 2² + 2¹ + 2⁰&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in other words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;128 + 64 + 32 + 16 + 32 + 16 + 8 + 4 + 2 +1
equals 255.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/skipster2k2/9fe8184c907184fa23b5f1435feb6912.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or in reverse if we took the first octet in our initial example, 192. 192 is made up of 128 + 64, therefore in 1’s and 0’s looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;128, 64, 32, 16, 32, 16, 8, 4, 2, 1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 , 1 , 0 , 0 , 0 , 0 , 0 , 0&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/skipster2k2/e268f0e0fec1abf43e9b14d3ffff0266.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;subnetting&#34;&gt;Subnetting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier IPv4 only has a puny 4 billion addresses. In order to be able to allocate more addresses, we use subnetting to divide the internet into separate sub-networks, where the same IP addresses can be used in each subnet, but cannot talk to one another directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subnets are allocated via a subnet mask, this defines how many bits are to be allocated to the network, and how many for the host. A subnet tells the hosts within it that they can all talk to each other without passing through a router.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;classful-networks&#34;&gt;Classful networks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some standard defined subnets called Classful networks. The table below shows the three classes available for public use and the number of hosts you can allocate to them. The more observant amongst you may have noticed that the available hosts are 2 less than the total number of permutations, 2^(32-n) that’s because the .0 address is always reserved as the network address, and the highest number address is reserved as the broadcast address. Internet or Public IPs are assigned and managed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iana.org/&#34;&gt;IANA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/skipster2k2/cf6ac01f1a22a290f3ba4c31edde134b.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other classes but they are not publicly available and are reserved for uses such as by the military.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you will see the subnet mask displayed after an IP address as such:
192.168.2.1/16 this is called CIDR (Classless inter domain routing) notation and is a simple way of showing the IP and the number of bits assigned to the network. For classful networks this is always a full octet, and so will equal /8, /16 and /24 for Class A, B, and C subnets respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;classless-networks&#34;&gt;Classless networks.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classless networks are simply any subnet mask that doesn’t fit the classful pattern.
Say for example you had a network of 157.28.0.0 with a subnet mask of 255.255.0.0 (i.e. a class B network). You want to create 4 networks for that IP address but they all need to be bigger than 254 hosts. That means making the subnet mask class C isn’t going to work as you won&amp;rsquo;t have enough hosts in each network, allocating the whole of the 3rd octet to the network is too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to calculate what the 3rd octet will be we need to calculate the number of bits to dedicate to the network. As we found out earlier, the binary value of a decimal number is 2^n so if we need 4 networks we need to work out the square root of 4, which is 2. Therefore we need to change 2 bits from host (0) to network (1). In other words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11000000&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can use our binary to decimal table to calculate the decimal value:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/skipster2k2/e32a3fbc25e78dba8300ce702604a7b8.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;128 + 64 is 192. So our subnet mask is 255.255.192.0. We can also work out the CIDR notation is /18 as that is the number of bits we have assigned to the network (the first two octets plus the first 2 bits of the 3rd octet). Cool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we need to work out what the 4 networks within that subnet will be. Firstly we can ignore the first two octets, as they are 255.255. so we know for all 4 networks they will be 157.28.x.x&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we need to look at the variations of bits that we have allocated to the network (in this example the first 2 bits. The table below shows us all the permutations of bit setting we can have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/skipster2k2/bf627c64c7c4addcd6e228fa3d1e33d3.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So from this, we know that our 4 networks are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network 1: 157.28.0.0/18&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network 2: 157.28.64.0/18&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network 3: 157.28.128.0/18&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network 4 157.28.192.0/18&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, now we know the 4 networks we can work out what the IP range for each one is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at network 1, we now won&amp;rsquo;t change the bits assigned to the network and are instead interested in the bits assigned to the host, so the first 2 and last 2 IP addresses in binary will look like the table below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/skipster2k2/bca52e160c4a447bafd484d40fcd06d6.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t forget that the first two bits in the 3rd octet can’t change because they are assigned to the network, not the hosts. It’s worth knowing here that the first and last IP in a network range are reserved. The first IP is the network address (in this case 157.28.0.0) and the last is the broadcast address (157.28.63. 255) the address for all hosts on the network to broadcast datagrams to one another. In which case our first network range is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;157.28.0.1 to 157.28.63.254.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s work out the rest of the ranges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/skipster2k2/3011d0358dd89db58ad256721ea00d94.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Translated to decimal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network 1: 157.28.0.1 to 157.28.63.254&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network 2: 157.28.64.1 to 157.28.127.254&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network 3: 157.28.128.1 to 157.28.191.254&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network 4: 157.28.192.1 to 157.28.255.254&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ta da!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TCP/IP Protocol Suite</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/tcp-ip-protocol-suite/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/tcp-ip-protocol-suite/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TCP/IP is a set of protocols that form the backbone of the internet. As I described in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ames.world/posts/the-osi-model/&#34;&gt;OSI model post&lt;/a&gt;, TCP (Transmission Control Protocol) provides reliable, ordered, and error-checked delivery of a stream of bytes between applications running on hosts. IP (Internet Protocol) is the protocol for shifting packets around between hosts in the network layer. The TCP/IP suite, however, contains a whole bunch of protocols beyond these two. (Fun fact: If to devices are communicating in a network with TCP/IP they are called network hosts. If they are using anything else they are called network nodes.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all real-world implementations TCP/IP &lt;em&gt;sort of&lt;/em&gt; follows the OSI Model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All models are wrong but some are useful — George Box&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/tcp-vs-osi.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Image showing the OSI model compared to the TCP/IP protocol suite. This is explained in detail below.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tcpip-applications&#34;&gt;TCP/IP Applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t spend ages on TCP/IP applications but real-world context helped me make a bit more sense of the host layers in the OSI model. I had a bit of a hard time getting my head around the difference between application programs and the application layer. TCP/IP helped me suss out what was meant. For example when I open a web browser — an application program, it makes a call to HTTP — the protocol in the application layer of the OSI stack. The web browser itself is not represented in the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a whole bunch of protocols operating at this level to ensure different applications can access the network. Some common examples are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HTTP (HyperText Transfer Protocol):&lt;/strong&gt; the rules for handling hypertext documents and hyperlinks, i.e. the world wide web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SMTP (Simple Mail Transfer Protocol):&lt;/strong&gt; The rules for sending emails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;POP3(Post Office Protocol) and IMAP (Internet Message Application Protocol):&lt;/strong&gt; The rules for receiving emails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FTP (File Transfer Protocol):&lt;/strong&gt; The rules for sending files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SSH: (Secure Shell):&lt;/strong&gt; The rules for managing network services securely over the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;transmission-control-protocol-tcp&#34;&gt;Transmission Control Protocol (TCP)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because most communication on the internet requires a reliable connection, TCP has become the dominant protocol. It operates at the network layer of the OSI model and it establishes a reliable connection through a process called the three-way handshake:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host 1 sends a Synchronisation (SYN) Request to Host 2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host 2 receives the request and sends back a Synchronisation Acknowledgement (SYN/ACK) request back to Host 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On receipt of the SYN/ACK Host 1 sends a final Acknowledgement (ACK) back to Host 2 and the connection is established.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data transfer (in the form of bytes) then takes place between the two hosts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This virtual circuit setup is called overhead. Additionally, the hosts don’t rely solely on the initial requests to ensure the reliability of the connection but instead will continue to check periodically to ensure it is still established and that data is flowing properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s all great if one application is making a request but as we have seen there are loads of applications and the higher layers making requests. This can often be at a faster speed than the supporting network and can cause bottleneck issues. TCP manages this demand with a process called Flow Control. Flow control is a pull system (which as an agile delivery lead makes me very happy). The receiver is responsible for telling the sender that it has received data and it is ok to send more. Lovely!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The segments delivered are acknowledged back to the sender upon their reception.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any segments not acknowledged are retransmitted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Segments are sequenced back into their proper order upon arrival at their destination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A manageable data flow is maintained in order to avoid congestion, overloading, and data loss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works well most of the time but it is still possible for the transmitting host to send a burst of data that is too much for the receiver to cope with. What happens then? The receiving host has a memory allocation called a buffer and it stores the burst of datagrams in this memory. (The origin of the dreaded ‘buffering’ message when viewing videos on the internet, a data-heavy process).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if the sender is so fast, it sends a massive stream of datagrams before the host has a chance to acknowledge it, and that is larger than the buffer? TCP has a plan for this too, in this scenario the receiving host sends a Not Ready indicator back to the sender, this is like an emergency brake and stops the sender from transmitting any more data until the host has had a chance to process the data in its buffer. Once the receiving host has done this it then transmits a Go indicator to the sender to resume data transfer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly the data is transferred in order from sender to receiver, this sequencing means that should any of the three failure scenarios mentioned above occur, both hosts know how far they have got through the transfer in order to resume after the failure is rectified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These multiple levels of fault tolerance mean that TCP is a very reliable connection-oriented protocol because it has the following characteristics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A virtual circuit is set up (such as a three-way handshake).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It uses sequencing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It uses acknowledgements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It uses flow control.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it is possible to reduce the robustness of this process for the sake of throughput through a control called Windowing. As you can imagine, acknowledging every datagram received back to the host could be a hefty process for large file transfers. Windowing defines how many data segments (measured in bytes) can be sent before an acknowledgement is required back from the receiving host. For example, a window of 3 would mean that 3 bytes of data can be sent before the receiver needs to send the sender and acknowledgement. The larger the size of the window, the bigger the risk of a buffer overflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how is sequencing ensured if the receiver only acknowledges every few data segments? This is done with acknowledgements. Say Host A wants to transmit the segments 123456789 with a window of 3 to Host B.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host A sends 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host A sends 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host A sends 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host B receives 123 and so acknowledges by requesting 4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host A sends 4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host A loses connection whilst trying to send 5.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host A sends 6&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host B now realises it is missing 5 so requests 5.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host A sends 5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host B now requests 7&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;etc etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;internet-protocol-ip&#34;&gt;Internet Protocol (IP)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet Protocol is concerned with addressing — ensuring data gets from the right source to the right destination. It sits unsurprisingly in the network layer of the OSI model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are currently two versions of the protocol in active use, IPv4 and IPv6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ipv4&#34;&gt;IPv4&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IPv4 is the most well-known version. When most people talk about IP addresses they are describing an IPv4 address. They are made up of 4 dot-separated numerical values called octets. Each value is a decimal representation of a binary value. I will cover what this means (and how to calculate IP addresses and subnet masks in Week 2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IPv4 is a 32 bit pool of addresses, this means that it is possible to have 4,294,967,296 (4 billion) addresses. This sounds like a lot but we have already nearly run out of IPv4 public addresses. Public addresses are those that are distributed by IANA (The Internet Assigned Number Authority) and are the IP representation of internet domain names. You can have many networks using the same IP addresses provided they are contained behind a subnet. A subnet is a logical subdivision of an IP network and can be described as Classful or Classless. This will be covered in more detail in Week 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An IPv4 address looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;193.168.2.1/24&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where 192.168.2.1 is the host address and /24 is the subnet. The subnet can also be represented in dot-separated format, in the case of /24 this will be 255.255.255.0&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ipv6&#34;&gt;IPv6&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IPv6 are 128-bit addresses, they are colon separated and represented in hexadecimal. The IPv6 pool of addresses is 340,282,366,920,938,463,463,374,607,431,768,211,456 or 340 billion billion billion billion addresses!! As a result, they don&amp;rsquo;t have a need for subnet’s. IPv6 headers are much smaller than IPv4 addresses, uses IPSec by default (encrypts the packets whilst being sent) it also broadcasts by default in Multicast mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example IPv6 address looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2001:0DB8:0000:0000:0000:FF00:0042:8329&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is ok to remove all leading zeroes from an address:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2001:DB8:0:0:0:FF00:42:8329&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And consecutive zeroes can be removed and represented by double colons. Although only once within the sequence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2001:DB8::FF00:42:8329&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;network-access-or-link-layer&#34;&gt;Network Access or Link Layer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TCP/IP protocol suite is designed to be device agnostic and so doesnt concern itself too much with the link layer. As with the OSI model the link layer is concerned with moving packets between network hosts and includes protocols for translating logical IP addresses to physical MAC addresses such as the ARP (Address Resolution Protocol).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The OSI Model</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/the-osi-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/the-osi-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The OSI model is designed to ensure compatibility of network devices (and their operating systems) regardless of manufacturer. OSI stands for Open Systems Interconnection and is defined by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iso.org/ics/35.100/x/&#34;&gt;International Standard Organisation (ISO)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model has seven layers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presentation layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transport layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which can be remembered by either of two mnemonics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All People Seem To Need Data Processing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or from the bottom up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please Do Not Throw Sausage Pizza Away&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/osi.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Graphic showing the 7 OSI layers in detail, this is explained below.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-host-layers&#34;&gt;The Host Layers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first 4 layers of the model really work at the operating system/software level, within the host:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;application-layer&#34;&gt;Application Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the application layer a tad confusing, it doesn’t concern application programs as such but enables software to access network resources by providing the interface to the layers down the stack. It concerns itself with ensuring that other hosts in the network have the resources necessary to make a connection. It coordinates partnering applications and ensures that data integrity and error recovery procedures are in place. The application layer is only activated when it is apparent that access to the network will be needed soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;presentation-layer&#34;&gt;Presentation Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation layer presents the data to the application layer. It is responsible for encoding and decoding data ready for transmission. The standard defines how data should be formatted. Data compression, decompression, encryption, and decryption are all tasks fulfilled within this layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;session-layer&#34;&gt;Session Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session layer is responsible for making sure that requests to the network from applications are only sent to and from that application. It ensures that data isn’t shared with other requesting applications on the host. It does this by creating, managing and removing a session for each application request to the network. It also coordinates communication between systems and defines which mode (discussed in &lt;a href=&#34;https://ames.world/posts/data-communication-fundamentals/&#34;&gt;data communication fundamentals&lt;/a&gt;) the transmission will be: simplex, half-duplex, or full-duplex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;transport-layer&#34;&gt;Transport Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transport layer is responsible for inserting data into a data stream and pushing it out from the host onto the network. This is where the Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) and the lesser-known UDP (User Datagram Protocol) do their thing. They are the rules for how to send the data from one host to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key difference is that TCP provides reliable, ordered, and error-checked delivery of a stream of bytes between applications running on hosts, whereas UDP is much more laissez-faire about data stream reliability. UDP is a connectionless protocol, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t care if the connection is broken, it values latency over reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-media-layers&#34;&gt;The Media Layers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next three layers are known as the media layers and are concerned with actually moving the data between hosts, starting with the:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;network-layer&#34;&gt;Network Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The network layer concerns itself with figuring out where devices on a network are so that it can figure out the path the data needs to take through the network to get from the sender to the receiver. The network layer manages logical device addressing (IP addresses) primarily through the use of routers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two types of packets are used at the Network layer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Packets&lt;/strong&gt; are used to transport user data through the internetwork. Protocols used to support data traffic are called routed protocols. Two examples of routed protocols are Internet Protocol (IP) and Internet Protocol version 6 (IPv6), (which is next weeks topic, stay tuned folks!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Route-Update Packets&lt;/strong&gt; are used to update neighbouring routers about the networks connected to all routers within the internetwork. Protocols that send route-update packets are called routing protocols, and some common ones are &lt;em&gt;Routing Information Protocol (RIP), RIPv2, Enhanced Interior Gateway Routing Protocol (EIGRP),&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Open Shortest Path First (OSPF).&lt;/em&gt; Route-update packets are used to help build and maintain routing tables on each router.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The route update packets are important as it helps ensure that data packets end up at the right network. I’m going to make up an analogy of how sending a letter would work if the postal service worked like routers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to send a letter to an address in Plymouth, I live in Birmingham.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So I send my letter to the Birmingham router.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Birmingham router sends the letter to the Plymouth router.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Plymouth router checks its network to see if it knows about the host.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it does it acknowledges the letter (packet) and sends it out to the Plymouth network for delivery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it doesn’t it drops the letter (packet) and broadcasts an updated route-update packet to the Birmingham router and all adjacent routers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Routers know about where stuff is by maintaining a routing table. A routing table contains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Network Addresses.&lt;/strong&gt; These are protocol-specific network addresses. A router must maintain a routing table for individual routing protocols because each routing protocol keeps track of a network that includes different addressing schemes, like IP and IPv6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interface.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the exit interface a packet will take when destined for a specific network. I.e. whether the packet needs to enter the network behind the router or be forwarded onto another router.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metric.&lt;/strong&gt; This value equals the distance to the remote network. Different routing protocols use different ways of computing this distance. Some routing protocols, namely RIP, use something called a hop count — the number of routers a packet passes through en route to a remote network. Other routing protocols alternatively use bandwidth, delay of the line, and even something known as a tick count, which equals 1/18 of a second, to make routing decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key attributes of a router are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Routers, by default, won’t forward any broadcast or multicast packets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Routers use the logical address in a Network layer header to determine the next-hop router to forward the packet to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Routers can use access lists, created by an administrator, to control security on the types of packets that are allowed to enter or exit an interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Routers can provide Layer 2 bridging functions if needed and can simultaneously route through the same interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Layer 3 devices (routers, in this case) provide connections between virtual LANs (VLANs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Routers can provide quality of service (QoS) for specific types of network traffic. You can define that voice traffic takes precedence over data traffic for example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-link-layer&#34;&gt;Data Link Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Data Link layer provides the physical transmission of the data and handles error notification, network topology, and flow control. This means the Data Link layer ensures that messages are delivered to the proper device on a LAN using hardware (MAC) addresses and translates messages from the Network layer into bits for the Physical layer to transmit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To take our letter from Birmingham to Plymouth analogy further. The router knows enough that the letter needs to go somewhere in Plymouth. Devices in the data link layer know the exact address in Plymouth to deliver the letter to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Data Link layer formats the message into pieces called a data frame and adds a customized header containing the destination and source hardware (MAC) address. This added information forms a sort of capsule that surrounds the original message to ensure once it has passed through the internetwork to get to a rough location, the devices in the data link layer have enough information to ensure it arrives at the exact destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each time a packet is sent between routers, it’s framed with control information at the Data Link layer. However, that information is stripped off at the receiving router, and only the original packet is left completely intact. This framing of the packet continues for each hop until the packet is finally delivered to the correct receiving host. The packet itself is never altered along the route; it’s only encapsulated with the type of control information required for it to be properly passed on to its destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data link layer has specifications defined by the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE). It has two sub-layers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Media Access Control (MAC)&lt;/strong&gt; Defines how packets are placed on the media. Contention media access is “first come, first served” access, where everyone shares the same bandwidth — hence the name. Physical addressing is defined here, as are logical topologies. What’s a logical topology? It’s the signal path through a physical topology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Line discipline, error notification (not correction), ordered delivery of frames, and optional flow control can also be used at this sublayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Logical Link Control (LLC)&lt;/strong&gt; is responsible for identifying Network layer protocols and then encapsulating them, an LLC header tells the Data Link layer what to do with a packet once a frame is received. It works like this: A host receives a frame and looks in the LLC header to find out where the packet is destined — say, the IP protocol at the Network layer. The LLC can also provide flow control and sequencing of control bits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The IEEE work on standards is done by a number of subcomittees of a project known as 802. The 802 standards apply to different parts of the data link layer but the two most significant ones are 802.3 which defines standards for Ethernet networks and 802.11 which defines standards for wireless networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;physical-layer&#34;&gt;Physical Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last one hooray! The Physical layer does two important things: it sends bits and receives bits and it communicates directly with the various types of actual communication media. Different kinds of media represent these bit values in different ways. Some use audio tones (bring back 56k modems yeah!), and others employ state transitions—changes in voltage from high to low and low to high. Specific protocols are needed for each type of media to describe the proper bit patterns to be used, how data is encoded into media signals, and the various qualities of the physical media&amp;rsquo;s attachment interface such as electrical, mechanical, procedural, and functional requirements for activating, maintaining, and deactivating a physical link between end systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;encapsulation-and-headers&#34;&gt;Encapsulation and Headers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all cool but what does this all actually mean in practice? Well, the OSI layers mean that the different functions fulfilled within each layer are encapsulated from one another. Basically, each layer doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to know how something is done, just that it is done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a host transmits data across a network to another device, it’s wrapped with protocol information at each layer of the OSI model. This information is called the header. Each layer communicates only with its corresponding layer on the receiving device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To communicate and exchange information, each layer uses Protocol Data Units (PDUs). These hold the control information attached to the data at each layer of the model. They’re usually attached to the header in front of the data field but can also be in the trailer, or end, of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a transmitting device, the data-encapsulation method works like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User information is converted to data for transmission on the network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data is converted to segments, and a reliable connection is set up between the transmitting and receiving hosts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Segments are converted to packets or datagrams, and a logical address is placed in the header so each packet can be routed through an internetwork. A packet carries a segment of data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packets or datagrams are converted to frames for transmission on the local network. Hardware (Ethernet) addresses are used to uniquely identify hosts on a local network segment. Frames carry packets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frames are converted to bits, and a digital encoding and clocking scheme is used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there we have it, a very large summary of how data gets from one computer to another.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Communication Fundamentals</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/data-communication-fundamentals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/data-communication-fundamentals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/data_components.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Diagram showing the fundamental components of a data network, described in this article.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concerns the basics of networking, starting with some common terminology of data transmission. This can be summarised as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sender has some data they want to send to a receiver.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That data needs to be converted into a message for sending.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The message needs to be transmitted via some form of medium.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The receiver needs to be able to turn that signal back into the data that has been sent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore a system is needed to agree on rules between the sender and receiver about how the data will be converted into a signal, transmitted and converted back to data, this is called a &lt;em&gt;protocol&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order for this system to be effective it needs to ensure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delivery&lt;/strong&gt;, to the correct destination.
&lt;strong&gt;Accuracy&lt;/strong&gt;, to ensure the data received is the same as what was sent.
&lt;strong&gt;Timeliness&lt;/strong&gt;, there is a minimum of delay in transmission of the signal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This effectiveness can be hampered by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attenuation&lt;/strong&gt;, the distance between sender and receiver is too far to be effective. (using the example of talking, if the receiver is too far away to hear the sender shouting at them, their signal is suffering from attenuation).
&lt;strong&gt;Noise&lt;/strong&gt;, there is interference with the signal. (using the talking example, if there is a stereo on when the sender and receiver are communicating then the receiver may not hear what is being said and has to ask for the sender to repeat themselves).
&lt;strong&gt;Delay&lt;/strong&gt;, the signal takes longer than is required to be transmitted. (the sender and receiver are trying to have a quick-fire conversation but can only use postal letters).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;messaging&#34;&gt;Messaging&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For computers and other electronic devices, when messages are sent they take the form of analog or digital signals.
Analog transmissions are broadcast as a wave and the protocol of the signal knows where each part of the wave corresponds to a particular part of data. so the peak of the wave may be an A, the trough of the wave a B.
Digital transmission is via a series of voltage pushes, where a positive ‘push’ equals 1, and no push is 0. The sequence can then be translated to bits.
In both scenarios, the message can be distorted by the three reasons given above resulting in degradation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;transmission&#34;&gt;Transmission&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we know the medium by which the message will be broadcast the next consideration is how to transmit it. There are two ways to transmit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guided&lt;/strong&gt;. The message is sent directly to where it is supposed to go. Taking our non-computer analogy, this would be a letter. Only the receiver receives the sent data. In the case of computers. This is primarily via cables, such as Twisted Pair, Coax or Fibre Optics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unguided&lt;/strong&gt;. The message is broadcast so that anyone can receive it, For non-computer analogy, this would be talking in a crowded (but quiet room, maybe a library!) anyone within range can receive the signal. For computers, this is primarily WiFi or Bluetooth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These transmissions can be sent in three different modes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simplex&lt;/strong&gt;, only the sender can transmit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Half duplex&lt;/strong&gt;, the sender and receiver can transmit but not at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full duplex&lt;/strong&gt;, both the sender and receiver can send at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network Fundamentals</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/network-fundamentals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/network-fundamentals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/network_fundamentals.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;An image showing a number of colourful Cat5 cables with the banner ‘Network fundamentals’&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network fundamentals explores how computer networks are designed to enable the sharing of data taking into account three key requirements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance.&lt;/strong&gt; The sharing of data and resources doesn’t degrade the computers on the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reliability.&lt;/strong&gt; The network doesn’t fall over all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security.&lt;/strong&gt; Data is only shared with those that should have access to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;types&#34;&gt;Types&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peer to Peer&lt;/strong&gt; is where every node on the network has equal access to the network and each node shares data and resources. The advantages are you don’t have to fork out for servers, or administrators to manage the network. The disadvantages are that every user of the network has to ensure they have an access token for every host on the network, this doesn’t scale well and is a nightmare to manage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Client-Server&lt;/strong&gt; is where there is a centralised server managing users access tokens and credentials (in the case of a windows network via active directory). The advantages are that this scales well for large networks, users only have one set of credentials which know what roles and permissions the user has to resources on the network. Additionally, servers have more grunt so can manage multiple requests so performance is better. The disadvantages are it’s more expensive and requires administrators of the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;network-scale&#34;&gt;Network Scale&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on how big your network is, defines the best approach to designing it, there are a number of different designs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local Area Network.&lt;/strong&gt; LAN’s interconnect hosts within a small geographical area, usually an office. LAN’s are usually owned by the same company, and can be as big as a room, a floor, a building, or a campus of buildings. The course says data rates are faster than LAN’s. However, I’m not sure how true this is, Dark fibre networks, usually used in WAN’s can have speeds up to 10GBps, most LAN’s I have come across are rarely faster than 1Gbps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metropolitan Area Network.&lt;/strong&gt; MAN’s interconnect hosts within a city sized area. MAN’s can be owned and utilised as public utilities or may be used to connect companies or campuses covering lots of buildings in a citywide area. They are often used to connect LAN’s in different buildings together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wide Area Network.&lt;/strong&gt; WAN’s connect hosts that are ‘geographically dispersed, usually over 100km apart. Similar to MAN’s a WAN can be thought of as a number of LAN’s connected together via transmission lines and routers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Area Network.&lt;/strong&gt; PAN’s are localised networks of a couple of metres for personal devices to communicate with one another. The devices may or may not belong to the person in question. PANs can be used for communication among the personal devices themselves (intrapersonal communication), or for connecting to a higher level network and the Internet (an uplink). PAN technology includes It can be made possible using IrDA, Bluetooth and USB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;physical-topology&#34;&gt;Physical Topology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physical topology&lt;/strong&gt; describes how we connect hosts together (primarily in cabled networks). There are 4 types: Star, Extended Star, Bus and Ring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Star topology&lt;/strong&gt; is where all hosts are connected to one another via a central network device such as a hub or switch. This is a really common topology as it is easy to extend and the impact of cable failure is low as it only affects one device. However, if the hub or switch goes bang the whole network is down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bus topology&lt;/strong&gt; is where all hosts are connected via one big pipe, all the devices can directly connect to one another with no device hops between them. However, if there is a fault in the Bus it affects all the devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extended Star&lt;/strong&gt; is a hybrid of star and bus topologies, where two star networks are connected to one another via a bus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ring topology&lt;/strong&gt; is where all hosts are connected to each other directly via network cards to the hosts next to one another. The advantages are that there is no need for a central network device such as a hub or switch. If the ring network is multi-directional, it can handle cable failure. However, if a host in the network fails, the network fails, it is also difficult to extend.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Essential Steps for an Effective Project Kick Off</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/essential-steps-for-an-effective-project-kick-off/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/essential-steps-for-an-effective-project-kick-off/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kick-off’s are a great way of bringing a new team together at the start of a new project or phase of a project. The aim is to allow the team to get to know one another and to allow all the team members to understand the goals and objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently helped facilitate a kick-off for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/agile-delivery/how-the-alpha-phase-works&#34;&gt;alpha phase&lt;/a&gt; of the ‘Protect’ service (working title). Although Protect had been through a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/agile-delivery/how-the-discovery-phase-works&#34;&gt;discovery phase&lt;/a&gt;, circumstances meant that the Alpha team was quite different to the Discovery team. This meant that we needed to spend more time than perhaps usual bringing everyone up to speed. Our kick-off lasted 3.5 days. the structure was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day 1 (half day). High level overview and get to know each other.
Day 2. User’s and organisational goals.
Day 3. Look for opportunities and map a flow.
Day 4. Build a hypothesis driven backlog and do a retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;monday&#34;&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the team had to travel Monday morning so we started in earnest at lunchtime. We had deliberately hired a space away from the office to avoid distractions and to help free up the teams thinking away from their usual workspace and routines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of Monday was to set the scene of our project within the wider context of HM Land Registry’s transformation programme, and to allow the team to get to know one another and how we like to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/objective.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Paul describing how our objective fits into the overall strategy.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scene setting described:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What the digital programme is seeking to achieve and what is expected from us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long the Alpha will run for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A high level view of what we learned in Discovery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the scene was set, we did a ‘What are we seeking to achieve in Alpha.’ Session. This involved the team jotting down all the outputs and outcomes we expected to produce by the end of Alpha. This ensured the team understand the problem space, and helped get buy-in to what needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally we ran through &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@cassierobinson/a-user-manual-for-me-d3a851fbc694&#34;&gt;‘A user manual for me’&lt;/a&gt; session by Cassie Robinson. This helped us get a feel for how each of us likes to work. Based on that, we generated a team charter to help us reflect on how we work in future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/nicolette.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Nicolette adding her ‘user manual’ cards.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/team_charter.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Team Charter&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tuesday&#34;&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday was user research day, the aim of the day was to understand who the users of our service are, and what expectations and motivations they have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spent time going through the user research outputs from Discovery. This allowed us to get a feel for what our users found difficult, and what their expectations were when they used the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/angie.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Angie keeping the team engaged in user research by asking us to guess ‘who said that?’&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We did an exercise to look at the process from a fraudulent persona. How would we take advantage of the current system? It was a lot of fun pretending to be ‘evil’ but it also drove home some of the challenges we face in protecting citizens property rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day we had a quick checkpoint to ensure we were on track and we were getting out what we expected to from the outcomes we had identified on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday evening we went out as a team for a meal, to get to know one another better in a non-work context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wednesday&#34;&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of Wednesday was to get into the problem space in more detail. We started with the current flow for the service and identified the obvious risks and opportunities that the flow presented. The previous days persona exercises really helped with this as we had a lot more empathy for where the process would support or fail people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/jayti.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Jayti leading the team through the pain points in the existing processes.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we mapped out a new flow, this was hard. There are some difficult technical and usability challenges we face and we found ourselves going down a few rabbit holes. It wasn’t until Gordon, our architect, suggested mapping out what we think the perfect flow would be, then identify the challenges, that we really managed to get into what the service could look like. We succeeded and had a white-boarded service journey by the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thursday&#34;&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday was backlog building day. We now understood our users, had a proposed service journey, and a good feel for the technical complexity. How were we going to verify that this was correct though?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We chose to use Hypothesis Driven Development as a way of structuring our cards. The template was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We believe that {&lt;em&gt;the hypothesis&lt;/em&gt;} will allow {&lt;em&gt;the outcome of the hypothesis&lt;/em&gt;} we will know this is true when {&lt;em&gt;the measure of success&lt;/em&gt;}.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty of this model was that we weren’t committing to outputs, but outcomes. Some of what we hold to be true at the beginning of the project will undoubtedly turn out to be false. The important thing is to identify early and cheaply what is true and what is not. The other nice thing about this style is that it worked for both technical and non-technical stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/ian.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The team contemplating how we could measure a particular hypothesis we have identified.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course as with any system, there were certain exceptions that disproved the rule. We didn’t get hung up on that, if there was a task to be done that was a no brainer, we just captured it instead of fretting about getting it to fit the format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All models are wrong, but some are useful. — George Box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally we ran a retrospective to discover what had worked well and what we could improve for next time. We used the &lt;a href=&#34;https://retromat.org/en/?id=19&#34;&gt;retrospective sailing game&lt;/a&gt; to identify what had gone well, what was slowing us down, what we were worried would get in our way in future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;10-things-i-learned-from-the-kick-off&#34;&gt;10 things I learned from the kick-off.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Space to think and concentrate is important, booking external space really helps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a plan for the week, but dont be afraid to let things run if its going in a good direction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a large room with desks in the central area to make conversations easy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/hypothesis_wall.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;A central desk with lots of space around the walls made taking conversations from desk to wall really easy.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of wallspace is vital, but have paper or magic whiteboard at hand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A projector gives you flexibility to bring up stuff on computers on any wall when needed and doesn&amp;rsquo;t clutter the space like a television.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spending time understanding users and their needs before diving into the service helped us validate how our proposed flow would work for them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoiding going down rabbit holes is a good skill, but in kick-off it can be necessary to go a little bit down rabbit holes to rule things out, or understand potential issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encourage everyone to contribute to the vision, objectives and direction of the service. They will be much more committed to its success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make time to get to know one another as part of the working period, but also socially, this helps gel the team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/avatars.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Some of the avatars the team chose to represent them in the ‘user manual of me’ exercise. Shaggy from Scooby Doo, a bike sprocket, action figures and a clapper board.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Injecting a sense of urgency, but also enthusiasm for what we are doing is vital.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mountaineering and a Rant About Risk Management</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/mountaineering-and-a-rant-about-risk-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/mountaineering-and-a-rant-about-risk-management/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I love hill climbing and mountaineering, ever since I was dragged up Pen-Y-Fan and got mild hypothermia in the scouts at about the age of 13. One of the best things yomping up hills has taught me is the nature of risk. So I was a bit surprised when I saw this tweet from Vasco Duarte:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Friends, let&amp;#39;s collect a list of domains where Risk ELIMINATION is priority #1: Climbing; Air travel industry; what else? &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/modernAgile?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#modernAgile&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/agile?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#agile&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/NoEstimates?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#NoEstimates&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/lean?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#lean&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/kanban?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#kanban&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Vasco Duarte (@duarte_vasco) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/duarte_vasco/status/964122429147811841?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 15, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a lot of respect for Mr Duarte, his work in with the #NoEstimates agenda and his focus on measuring data and forecasting over, estimation and guesswork is interesting and inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However I couldn’t agree with this point and didn’t make the case well in the limitations of twitter. So in the spirit of cooperation and shared understanding I thought I would describe why I believe risk cannot be eliminated and trying to can actively slow you down and have the reverse effect. Please let me know your thoughts in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/pen-y-fan.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Pen Y Fan a mountain South Wales, covered in snow.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-youve-decided-to-go-and-climb-a-mountain&#34;&gt;So you’ve decided to go and climb a Mountain.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good for you, its great to get out into the wilderness, but are you prepared for the journey ahead? At the most basic level have you thought about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where you are going and your ability to navigate and walk the route? What the weather is going to do? How much food and drink you’ll need? How long you expect to be out for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the above you will have packed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A navigation aid of some sort&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Appropriate clothes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enough food and drink for the duration of your walk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then you think about all of the risks that could befall you on the walk.
What happens if I have an accident whilst I’m out? What if the weather turns bad? What if I run out of water? What if the river I need to cross is in spate? What if I encounter an unexpected terrain or a steep ascent?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you also pack:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A comprehensive first-aid kit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A full set of waterproofs and hat and gloves, just in case the weather turns bad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An extra canteen of water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A rope, harness and basic climbing gear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now your pack is about half as heavy again and you know you won’t be able to walk at the same speed as with a lighter pack. You’ll be out for longer, so you now need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extra food and drink&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re pack is heavier again, with a bag this size, the walk is turning into an overnight expedition so you pack:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A tent or bivouac&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sleeping bag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A stove;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enough food and drink for an overnight expedition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/heavy_load.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;2 people with severely overloaded backpacks&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of trying to eliminate all risks has significantly slowed you down and as a result exposed you to other risks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A heavier pack reduces your footing on poor terrain increasing your likelihood of injuring yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A longer trip increases the likelihood the weather will deteriorate increasing the risk of exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mountain-climbing-is-about-trade-offs&#34;&gt;Mountain climbing is about trade offs.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The definition of risk is the impact of an event versus the probability of it occurring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk = Impact * Probability.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where most risk management fails is in measuring probability effectively, a few methodologies such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imo.org/en/OurWork/safety/safetytopics/pages/formalsafetyassessment.aspx&#34;&gt;Formal Safety Assessment&lt;/a&gt; used in the maritime industry and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nrc.gov/reading-rm/doc-collections/fact-sheets/probabilistic-risk-asses.html&#34;&gt;Probabilistic Risk Assessment&lt;/a&gt; used in the nuclear industry do this reasonably well by assessing data on previous accidents and near misses, however even this doesn’t handle &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_swan_theory&#34;&gt;Black Swan&lt;/a&gt; events well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming up with a plan to eliminate all risks without understanding the likelihood of that risk occurring can actively slow you down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/simple_risk_matrix.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;A simple risk matrix, impact versus probability&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets look back at our example. I set off in May in sunshine, the forecast is a windy day with a chance of showers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a high probability of showers, the impact will be I get damp and miserable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3(P)*1(I) = 4(R)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a low probability it will snow, the impact will be I get hypothermia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1(P)*3(I) = 4(R)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The risk is the same because whilst the likelihood of snow is low, the impact is much higher.
So do I take a hat and gloves and a thicker jacket?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No because the extra gear affects the weight I need to carry and therefore energy usage. I make the trade off of lightness and speed (mitigate risk) over preparing for the risk of hypothermia with more clothes (eliminate risk).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These sorts of trade offs happen all the time when out on the hills or climbing, as maintaining speed is a more effective risk strategy than trying to eliminate all risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Policies are organizational scar tissue. They are codiﬁed overreactions to unlikely-to-happen-again situations.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jason Fried (@jasonfried) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jasonfried/status/2758624714?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 21, 2009&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eliminating all risks, even low probability, high impact ones will reduce your speed, introducing higher probabilities of things going wrong. In my experience, optimising for speed will reduce risk far more than trying to eliminate them all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know your experiences and thoughts in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving &#39;Find&#39; for the Find Property Information Service</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/improving-find-for-the-find-property-information-service/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/improving-find-for-the-find-property-information-service/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://search-property-information.service.gov.uk/&#34;&gt;Find Property Information&lt;/a&gt; is a GOV.UK service being developed by HM Land Registry which aims to provide a simple summary of property information. Recently we have improved our ‘postcode search’ functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-did-we-do-this&#34;&gt;Why did we do this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first iteration of searching was developed over a year ago, we knew the limitations of it, but it was ‘good enough’ for the early stages of the service. This allowed us to move onto developing other features. Since then the quality of search has crept up the list of user issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-were-the-problems-with-the-old-search&#34;&gt;What were the problems with the old search?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a mixture of design and technical issues with our old search:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When users come to the service they think in terms of addresses, but our search results displayed land titles. This meant the results were jarring, it was especially unclear if there was more than one ‘title’ for a given address.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We hadn’t updated the address information we get from Ordnance Survey for over a year, so new builds wouldn’t show in the service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search results were confusing because of the order of the displayed addresses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We limited search results to a maximum of 50 on the false assumption this was the terms of the Ordnance Survey Addressbase licence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/search_results_before.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Search results before improvement, results were ‘titles’ rather than addresses - which the user searched for - causing confusion.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-did-we-improve-it&#34;&gt;How did we improve it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on feedback we’d been collecting we had a good handle on the types of problems people had, and a strong hypothesis that people would be more successful if we flipped the results. We aimed to stop showing what we have got (how we’ve documented the world), and start showing a familiar model of places (how user’s think of the world).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are familiar with what a postcode is, and what it contains — they use this all the time, when they are getting a parcel delivered, or sending a letter, or using their satnav.
There is a point at which we, currently, ask people to pick a particular property record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we now do that as a separate steps. previously we had wrapped multiple decisions into one step, which was too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So whilst we still need, currently, to introduce the concept of titles and tenures, we do this in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/search_results_after.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The new search results are much clearer and align to what our users expect to see next.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-did-we-build-it&#34;&gt;How did we build it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Find Property Information team consists of 12 people from different disciplines, we sometimes struggled to communicate effectively and stay focused due to the sheer numbers of communication pathways between team members. We had a hunch that the size of the team was slowing down our delivery so we decided to use postcode search as a good opportunity to test it. We separated out 4 people to focus solely on delivering improved search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team came up with a number of technical approaches and chose the one that would deliver the most value. There were other potentially better solutions, but would have taken longer to implement. Building services is always a trade off between building what’s needed now, and envisioning future use cases. There are risks to both approaches, too bare bones and it can be difficult to change the solution in future, too blue sky and time and energy can be wasted on features and functions that aren’t actually needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the whole we saw a lot of benefits from the small team. The small size meant that our processes could be much more lightweight, much less time was spent planning and discussing work, if a problem came up or a change needed to happen, it was much easier to solve as it was just a quick chat to discuss the problem, think of how to solve it and move on.
The team progressed well and improved our address search component, built a title-api for retrieving titles per address, and ‘plugged into’ an audit-api for collating what was happening within the service for troubleshooting and audit needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we reached a point where we needed to ‘plug-in’ what had been built back into the service. We needed to consider how we could deliver the functionality that had been built iteratively into the service without getting in the way, or breaking any of the other work being done by the rest of the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;agile-doesnt-equal-no-planning&#34;&gt;Agile doesn’t equal No Planning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a reached a point where we needed to get the team back together and consider how to move postcode into the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We came up with a high-level plan to deploy each of the new api’s in a way that wouldn’t impact the service or cause any downtime. It was also an iterative plan so by breaking the releases down into small chunks we could de-risk the change and rollback easily if any particular part did go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/whiteboarding.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Planning agile style, team members gathered around a whiteboard&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also wanted to assure ourselves that the search was as good as we thought it would be so we included: a comprehensive set of automated acceptance tests; manual eyeballing; and tests to verify our hypothesis of what we expected to happen when the changes were in production.
The hardest part of testing was finding a decent baseline to ‘prove our search was good. We knew our existing search was inconsistent so it made for a very poor baseline. We had other services that also had search functionality so we did some investigation into these services to test their viability as baselines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we found was that whilst on the whole they were good enough as a baseline, they all had slight discrepancies or weird results mainly due to data quality either from us or from our address suppliers. The Addressbase dataset has over 28 million address points, and our register data is over 24 million titles. Both of these datasets change daily and when they are as large as that even a 1% error rate can equal hundreds of thousands of data rows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Improving the quality of these two datasets wasn’t going to be possible so instead we attempted to understand the problems a bit better so that at least if users did encounter issues we could offer them an onward journey or understand why. We produced a ‘wall of weird’ of postcodes we knew behaved strangely in existing services and added these to our test baseline to see what happened in our service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/wall_of_weird.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The wall of weird, a whiteboard where we captured all the strange search behaviour we identified, so that we could validate we had fixed them as we improved the service.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-did-we-release-it&#34;&gt;How did we release it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we had a test and deploy plan that was detailed enough to give us direction, but lightweight enough to change when things inevitably changed or went wrong. And a few things did go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We hoped to release an updated address index into the service as a standalone iteration. However, when testing it, we found it had more of an impact on the user experience than we were comfortable with, so we had to bundle the change in with the ‘main’ release.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a result the main release became bigger than expected and we had to schedule in downtime, adding a number of additional steps and approvals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We found the title-api performed within thresholds but not as well as we would like, we found that search results had spikes of long response times. Whilst only affecting 2% of users, scaling up to actual usage volumes could equal hundreds of unsatisfied people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That final problem was the biggest challenge we faced, we hadn’t seen it in any of our lower test environments, but then again our pre-prod environment is the one that most resembles live. At first we didn’t have a good handle on exactly how big the issue was so we created some performance scripts to allow us to monitor response times whilst under heavy load. The scripts confirmed the scale of what we were seeing, but didn’t give us any further clues as to what was causing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally we decided that the benefits of the new search functionality exceeded the risks of some users having slow performance. We came up with a plan for measuring production performance and agreed to set some time aside to improve it should we see it happening in PROD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally we were in a position where we were ready to release. We had to turn the service off for an hour but pre-warned users of the downtime. The change itself went very smoothly and we were deployed and tested within 50 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-do-we-know-whether-it-has-been-successful&#34;&gt;How do we know whether it has been successful?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The measure of success that was most pressing was whether PROD would see the same performance issues that we saw in the test environment. It took a few days to build a sample of traffic but sure enough we did see the same problem. By then however we had given a bit more thought as to a plan for improving the performance. After the first release the refactored code went into production, drastically improving performance times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/before_performance.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Initial performance times, good but not excellent. Most responses within 2 seconds&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial performance times, good but not excellent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/after_performance.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Production responses following improvements, most responses in under 0.1 seconds!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Production responses following improvements, note the change in scale!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of our hypotheses of what would happen in Production have so far played out to be true:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the sample we tested our search is as good as existing HMLR services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Addresses changed in the past year now return in our search results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our new audit-api is collecting audit data successfully.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important change is that search is dropping down our ‘Top issues for our users’ chart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-next&#34;&gt;Whats next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will continue to learn more about how search is performing in the service, shipping to Production is the only true point where you really start to learn about how people use your service and how it works at scale so I’m sure we will need to make a few changes based on feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also have some work we want to do, to replace our address component with an address-api that is being built by colleagues in another team. This ‘common component’ will reduce maintenance overhead and ensure more consistency between services in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Plymouth, Route 2 - Millbay Mini</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/hidden-plymouth-route2-millbay-mini/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/hidden-plymouth-route2-millbay-mini/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m slightly overwhelmed by how well &lt;a href=&#34;https://ames.world/posts/hidden-plymouth-route2-millbay-mini/&#34;&gt;Route 1&lt;/a&gt; has been received I have had some lovely feedback and suggestions for future routes. One such suggestion is to do something shorter that children can take part in, so where better than around Millbay. I can test it with my own kids as they go to Plymouth School of Creative Arts which is the starting point for this route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/d/embed?mid=16cgN0xxCOX9BJIeOksILtykuBDKNyCk_&amp;hl=en&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;480&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are loads of quirky little features in and around Millbay, its relatively flat and the route is only 2km. If the walk doesn’t wear the little ones out, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.plymouth.gov.uk/parksnatureandgreenspaces/findpark/westhoepark&#34;&gt;West Hoe park&lt;/a&gt; is within walking distance too. The route starts outside the school and if you are driving there are three car parks nearby, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.co.uk/maps/@50.3689901,-4.1520366,3a,75y,115.98h,93.85t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1stpjtGYcS0qblHYZvv3xgww!2e0!7i16384!8i8192&#34;&gt;Martin Street&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.plymouth.gov.uk/parkingandtravel/findsomewherepark/pavilionscarpark&#34;&gt;Pavilions&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.myringgo.co.uk/parkinglocator/2320&#34;&gt;Brunel Way&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately they are all Pay and Display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-docks.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Millbay Docks&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;points-of-interest&#34;&gt;Points of Interest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;octagon-brewery&#34;&gt;Octagon Brewery&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the school head the short distance up Martin Street to the junction with Sawrey Street, here you will find the old Octagon Brewery, now Docwra Bros. car body shop.
The brewery was founded in 1861 and incorporated in 1899. It continued until 1954 when it was sold to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simonds_Brewery&#34;&gt;H&amp;amp;G Simonds&lt;/a&gt;. The following year the company was liquidated. On the side of the building is a small plaque:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Octagon Brewery&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the late 19th century there were three major breweries supplying ales and beers for public houses throughout the ‘Three Towns’ of Plymouth, Stonehouse and Devonport.
The Octagon Brewery was one of the many smaller ones started about 1899. It later owned many taverns throughout the ‘Three Towns.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These pubs displayed the distinctive brewery logo of an OB within an octagon shape. Some of the bottled favourites included ‘OB’ stout, Pale Ale, and Indian Pale Ale No 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/octogon-brewery.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Octogon brewery plaque, as described above&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinctive logo can still be seen today in the windows of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tripadvisor.co.uk/Attraction_Review-g186258-d3312659-Reviews-Dolphin_Hotel-Plymouth_Devon_England.html&#34;&gt;Dolphin Hotel&lt;/a&gt; on the Barbican, one of Plymouth’s most popular pubs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/dolphin-hotel.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The Octagon Brewery company logo built into the windows of the Dolphin Hotel on the Barbican.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-phoenix&#34;&gt;The Phoenix&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a short distance up Sawrey street is the Phoenix Tavern, alas no longer a tavern. The closed pubs project has some &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.closedpubs.co.uk/devon/plymouth_phoenix.html&#34;&gt;interesting pictures of the pub in the 1930’s&lt;/a&gt;. On the side of the building is another interesting plaque.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phoenix Hall Roller Skating Rink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roller skating took England by storm and by the late 19th century Plymouth had half a dozen rinks. In May 1880 the Phoenix Hall Rink was one of the last to open. Another rink, Pavilion New Skating Rink was located nearby in Martin Street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various skating prizes could be won. These were usually silver cups or medals but, on special occasions, prizes could even include live chickens or a pig to take home!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/the-phoenix.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The plaque on the side of the Phoenix Tavern as decribed above&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;millbay-stars&#34;&gt;Millbay stars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the Phoenix Tavern walk back south down Phoenix St and cross Millbay Road. Head back towards the mini roundabout at the entrance to Millbay docks on the wall you will see a number of Hollywood style stars. These show all the famous people who have berthed in Millbay, the vessel they arrived on, and the year. The stars include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walt Disney, Normandie, 1935.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charles Laughton, Champlain, 1935.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gloria Swanson, Queen Mary, 1938.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jack L Warner, Queen Mary, 1938.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maurice Chevalier, Manhattan, 1938.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sabu, Paris, 1938&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laurence Olivier, Ile de France, 1939.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vivien Leigh, Ile de France, 1939.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gene Autrey, Manhattan, 1939.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boris Karloff, Italia, 1950.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Judy Garland, Ile de France, 1951.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charlie Chaplin, Mauritania, 1951.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alan Ladd, Ile de France, 1952.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bing Crosby, Liberte, 1952.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sarah Vaughan, Liberte, 1953.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lena Horne, Liberte, 1956.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Duke Ellington, Ile de France, 1958.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-stars.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;One of the Millbay stars, this one is forWalt Disney who traveled on the Normandie&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;gold-bullion&#34;&gt;Gold bullion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing the ‘Gold’ bullion statue has been removed whilst a new retirement home is built on adjacent land, however it will be restored so is worth a mention for the future. The statue commemorates the practice of storing large quantities of bullion in the open on the dockside with a single policeman to guard it. This was common in the 1930’s with gold being sent to and from America, Australia and South Africa from the docks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/gold-bullion.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The gold ingots aren’t currently there but will be restored once the adjacent building work is completed.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between 1932 and 1934 over a million pounds of gold and silver ingots and sovereigns were landed at the docks following the groundbreaking salvage from the P&amp;amp;O liner &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pandosnco.co.uk/egypt.html&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Egypt&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;’ which sank off the coast of France in a decade earlier in 1922.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;endurance-blue-plaque&#34;&gt;Endurance Blue Plaque&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the gold bullion head east down Millbay road to Isambard Kingdom Brunel Way, turn right and head up it. At the time of writing there are hoardings up along the road with interesting Plymouth facts on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the road you reach Millbay docks where you will find a memorial stone and blue plaque commemorating Ernest Shackleton setting sail onboard the Endurance on the 8th August 1914.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roald_Amundsen&#34;&gt;Roald Amundsen’s&lt;/a&gt; success reaching the South Pole in 1911 (and the subsequent death of one of Plymouth’s most famous sons, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Falcon_Scott&#34;&gt;Robert Falcon Scott&lt;/a&gt;) Shackleton was aiming to complete the grandly titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial_Trans-Antarctic_Expedition&#34;&gt;‘Imperial Trans-Antarctic expedition’&lt;/a&gt;, crossing Antarctica from one side to the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/endurance-plaque.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The Shackleton Endurance blue plaque.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The expedition came into jeopardy when the Endurance became trapped in the sea ice, and was ultimately crushed and sank in the Weddell Sea. The 28 man crew found themselves stranded on the pack ice with no hope of rescue. They camped on the ice for &lt;strong&gt;6 months&lt;/strong&gt; drifting slowly northwards. Eventually the ice became too unstable and the crew were stranded on the small uninhabited Elephant Island after taking to the ships boats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shackleton and 5 of his crew then rowed &lt;strong&gt;800 miles&lt;/strong&gt; to South Georgia island in their 22.5 ft boat the ‘James Caird’. They were aiming to seek help from whaling outposts on the island and to come back and rescue the remaining 23 men. The journey was gruelling, through heavy seas and freezing conditions but after 14 days they successfully reached the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be a further 3 months before Shackleton would be able to rescue the men he left behind, due to the start of the southern winter. The government of Uruguay loaned him a ship to affect the rescue and amazingly all 28 men of the ‘Endurance’ survived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;west-hoe-road-signs&#34;&gt;West Hoe Road signs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the docks head up the 35 steps (count them with the kids) from Willoughby Way to West Hoe Road. You will find many old signs on the dock boundary wall. These are reclaimed signs from businesses and facilities in the docks. We only managed to find the Carruthers cranes and Royal Navy and Marines recruitment signs. Apparently there is also Singer sewing machines sign from the sailmakers, and ‘Armstrongs’ which used to be on the rail bridge at the docks mouth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/caruthers.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Carruthers cranes safety notices&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/navy-sign.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Join the Navy, good pay and prospects!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;millbay-docks&#34;&gt;Millbay docks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Millbay takes its name unsurprisingly from being the site of tidal mills as early as the 12th century. The docks however really took off in the 19th century. Millbay pier was built in 1844 and the following year the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SS_Great_Britain&#34;&gt;SS Great Britain&lt;/a&gt; berthed here during her maiden voyage to New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-pier.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;View from Millbay Pier today.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1846 the Great Western Dock company were granted an act of Parliament to provide full facilities for shipping in the docks. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isambard_Kingdom_Brunel&#34;&gt;Isambard Kingdom Brunel&lt;/a&gt; designed the new docks and the majority of the original dock walls survive today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Millbay quickly became a busy commercial dock and by the 1870’s started to become a busy terminus for trans-atlantic visitors. It was known as the ‘route that cuts the corner off’ as passengers could disembark at Plymouth and get a fast train to London, thus avoiding the longer sea journey to Southampton or Tilbury. In the early 20th century 6 million passenger landed or embarked for America from the docks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1912 the surviving crew of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.plymouthherald.co.uk/news/history/plymouths-haunting-steps-nowhere-story-3796478&#34;&gt;Titanic&lt;/a&gt; landed at Millbay docks in secrecy and were taken by train to Southampton. There is a memorial inside Millbay marina, however it is not accessible to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/titanic-crew.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The crew of the Titanic landing at Millbay docks after the ships demise.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today the docks are undergoing major regeneration new houses and flats have been built, the school, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kingpointmarina.co.uk/&#34;&gt;King point marina&lt;/a&gt; (including the lovely &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thedockplymouth.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Dock Restaurant&lt;/a&gt;) have also been developed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building continues with the second phase of homes and retirement apartments underway, plus proposals for a hotel and shops are out for public consultation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-apartments.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Millbay docks today.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;millbay-park&#34;&gt;Millbay Park&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you continue along West Hoe Road, there is a strangely shaped park on the Eastern side of West Hoe Road. The park is terraced with a football pitch at the peak, the flat space gives away its use as a barracks between 1845 and 1856. Before this however, the area was a gaol for prisoners of war. Initially it was constructed to house 1500 American prisoners of war during the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Revolutionary_War&#34;&gt;War of Independence (1777–1783)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-gaol.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Mill prison, previously called Mill gaol was designed and built to house prisoners of war.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Napoleonic wars the prison held 11,000 French and American prisoners of war. It was at this time in 1806 that the prisoners were marched the 15 miles to Princetown on Dartmoor to build Dartmoor Prison (to contain even more prisoners of war!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today little remains of this history other than a couple of plaques on the gates of the park. The first commemorates the first American sailors held prisoner and reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this site was Mill (Old Mill — Millbay) Gaol where over 1500 American sailors were held in captivity during the war for American independence 1777–1783.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-gaol-plaque.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Millbay Gaol Plaque as described above.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second commemorates the barracks being turned over for public recreational usage (in a suitably clipped and bossy tone):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subject to military regulations this recreation ground, formerly the site of Millbay barracks, was opened for public use on the day of the coronation of King George V and Queen Mary. 22nd June 1911.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-barracks-plaque.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Millbay barracks plaque as described above.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;eddystone-lighthouse-pavement&#34;&gt;Eddystone Lighthouse Pavement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just opposite the park in front of the Salumi restaurant is a paved circle which doesn’t look like much, until you notice the strange shape of the slabs. These are the groundbreaking interlocking patterns of the stone blocks developed by John Smeaton to build the Eddystone Lighthouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/eddystone-lighthouse-pavement.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The Eddystone lighthouse pavement with the Duke of Cornwall hotel in the background.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interlocking blocks were so successful that the lighthouse stood for 123 years, indeed the rock it was built on wore away before the blocks did forcing it to be replaced. Indeed the lighthouse still stands today proudly on Plymouth Hoe 259 years after it was first constructed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look closely there is a rather grisly plaque embedded in the pavement. It reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the 1st December 1755 fire destroyed John Rudyard’s Eddystone lighthouse. As flames reached the roof of the tower a worker, Henry Hall (aged 84) looked up and managed to swallow a blob of molten metal which lodged in his stomach. He died of lead poisoning twelve days later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/eddystone-memorial.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The grisly Eddystone plaque described above&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;duke-of-cornwall-hotel&#34;&gt;Duke of Cornwall Hotel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://thedukeofcornwall.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Duke of Cornwall&lt;/a&gt; dominates the skyline of Millbay and stands grandly in Victorian splendour. It was Plymouth’s first luxury hotel, the South Devon railway company recognised the need for luxury accommodation as first class travel increased to and from the docks due to the ‘route the cuts the corner off’ mentioned earlier. The hotel’s popularity matched the fortunes of the docks, peaking in the 1930&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/duke-of-cornwall-advert.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;An advert for the Duke of Cornwall from 1897. It looks much the same today.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the second world war, the hotel was embroiled in scandal as the family running the hotel were strongly tied to the fascist party. Due to Plymouth’s military importance the family were placed on MI5’s suspect list and in 1944 they were forced to leave the hotel before the Allied invasion of France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1970’s the hotel faced the threat of being pulled down primarily because of the lack of car parking, despite being listed in 1975. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Betjeman&#34;&gt;Sir John Betjeman&lt;/a&gt; helped lead the fight for it’s survival describing it as “one of the finest examples of Victorian gothic architecture he had ever seen.’ the hotel’s future was thankfully secured in 1988 after the terraced garden had been changed to a car park.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;millbay-station-the-pavillions&#34;&gt;Millbay Station (the Pavillions)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little remains today as a reminder that the Pavilions was once the location of Plymouth’s primary railway station. The only remaining features are two stone pillars outside the main entrance with no real explanation as to what they are or why they are there. They are in fact the posts that made up the forecourt entrance to the station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-station-pillars.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The entrance pillars to Millbay Station, cannon damage from World War II can still be seen on them.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The station was built in 1849 by the South Devon railway as the terminus of its line from Exeter. It was originally a 7ft broad gauge railway but was converted to 4ft 8½in standard gauge in 1892 after the Great Western railway had acquired the South Devon in 1876.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1941 the station was closed to passengers after being bombed. Traces of cannon damage can still be seen on the posts. In 1969 the station was closed to good trains, apart from through traffic to the docks. Then finally in 1971 the station was closed for good. Twenty years later the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.plymouthpavilions.com/Online/default.asp&#34;&gt;Pavilions leisure complex&lt;/a&gt; was opened on the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/millbay-station.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Millbay station with the Duke of Cornwall behind it, notice the enormous wide gauge rails.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the Pavilions it’s a short walk downhill back to the school. I hope you enjoy the route.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Plymouth, Route 1 - Stoke to Mutton Cove</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/hidden-plymouth-route1-stoke-to-mutton-cove/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/hidden-plymouth-route1-stoke-to-mutton-cove/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This route starts at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.co.uk/maps/place/Stoke+Car+Park/@50.3805872,-4.1651648,15z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x0:0x880e5bffe7b91f5d!8m2!3d50.3805872!4d-4.1651648&#34;&gt;Stoke Village Car Park&lt;/a&gt;, which is free to park. It then climbs to what was once the highest point in Plymouth, before descending to sea level and back again.
I have mapped the route on Strava so you can download it to a GPS, or print out the map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/stoke-mutton-cove-route.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Route map&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/stoke-mutton-cove-route-profile.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Elevation Profile&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also run the route so you can see a fly through below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;embedly-card&#34; data-card-controls=&#34;0&#34; data-card-key=&#34;f1631a41cb254ca5b035dc5747a5bd75&#34;&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.relive.cc/view/vNOPKV2J2vR?r=embed-site&#34;&gt;Relive &#39;New phone&#39;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;script async src=&#34;https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/platform.js&#34; charset=&#34;UTF-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;points-of-interest&#34;&gt;Points of interest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;blockhouse-park&#34;&gt;Blockhouse Park&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the city expanded toward Roborough this was the highest point in Plymouth and the 360˚ view from the Redoubt is one of the best in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/blockhouse_park.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The view north from Blockhouse Park redoubt, on the left is the dockyard that the fort was built to protect.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Mount Pleasant &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Redoubt&#34;&gt;Redoubt&lt;/a&gt;’ was first built in 1780 to protect the dockyard. According to a plaque at the entrance to the park it was modified in 1811 and had become obsolete by 1860.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A larger information board in the redoubt shows what it would have looked like and provides more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/mount_pleasant_redoubt.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The information board in the redoubt.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;clarendon-house&#34;&gt;Clarendon House&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you leave Blockhouse park and come down Home Park, you are greeted with the imposing sight of Clarendon House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/clarendon_house.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Clarendon House&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the right hand side of the main entrance is a plaque which states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the years 1940 to 1947 this building was the training centre for the Polish Navy and Headquarters of the Polish Navy Southern Command following the outbreak of World War II. This Plaque was unveiled on 20th May 2001, by the Lord Mayor of Plymouth, Councillor David Viney and Mr Stanislaw Szwabski chairman of Gydnia city council, to commemorate the 25th Anniversary of the twinning of Plymouth and Gydnia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The building itself appears older than from the 1940’s. The excellent National Libraries of Scotland Historic maps website allows you to view old Ordnance Survey maps overlaid on modern maps. According to the 1854 to 1863 OS map, it appears that Clarendon house was previously an orphanage, the ‘Royal British Female Orphan Asylum.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/royal_british_female_orphan_asylum.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;A section of the 1854 to 1863 Ordnance Survey Map showing Clarendon House as the ‘Royal British Female Orphan Asylum.’ Image Courtesy of National Libraries of Scotland and Ordnance Survey.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This led me to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.childrenshomes.org.uk&#34;&gt;www.childrenshomes.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; who have a detailed and fascinating page about the history of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.childrenshomes.org.uk/DevonportRoyal/&#34;&gt;Royal British Female Orphan Asylum&lt;/a&gt;. Clarendon House’s foundation stone was laid on April 23rd 1845 and according to the website it sounded quite the event:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ceremony was witnessed by the Lord Lieutenant of Cornwall, the Mayors and Corporations of Plymouth and Devonport, the Magistrates of the County and Borough, the Commissioners of the town, the heads of Departments Naval and Military Officers, and many others who walked in procession to the site. It was said that the rich combination of masonic, civic naval and military uniforms, the military music, and the presence of well-dressed and beautiful females, attracted a crowd of 30,000 spectators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hms-doris-memorial&#34;&gt;H.M.S. Doris Memorial&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After passing Clarendon house the route takes you through the attractive cottages and town houses of Acre Place to Devonport Park, in my opinion the most beautiful park in Plymouth. Following the spherical central path offers sweeping views of the river Tamar and the dockyards below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/hms-doris-memorial.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;H.M.S. Doris Memorial with Higher Lodge in the background.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually you come to the H.M.S. Doris Memorial. For a long time I mistakenly assumed the gun was one of the field guns used in the Boer war and commemorated in the annual Naval gun carry. The gun is actually a captured machine gun.
The crew of H.M.S. Doris did have to drag a ships gun hundred of miles inland on an improvised carriage but it was much bigger than a field gun. The image below shows the 4.7 inch gun being fired at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Magersfontein&#34;&gt;Battle of Magersfontein&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/4.7-inch-field-gun.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Image courtesy of Imperial War Museum&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;raglan-gatehouse&#34;&gt;Raglan Gatehouse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just down from Devonport park on a rather long straight, and fairly bleak road is the Raglan Barracks gatehouse. The barracks are no more having been demolished in the 1970’s but the grade II listed gatehouse remains, albeit in a rather sorry state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/raglan_gate.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Raglan Barracks Gatehouse today.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The barracks were built between 1853 and 1858 during the Crimean Wars. The gate was designed by Captain Francis Fowke who also designed the Royal Albert Hall and parts of the Victoria and Albert Museum. The Devonport online website provides a comprehensive history of the barracks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it hard to imagine the sheer size of the barracks parade ground. It doesn’t feel possible that such a large space existed just behind this building now that it is surrounded by flats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/changing-of-colours.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Changing of the colours on the enormous Raglan barracks parade ground in 1895. The gatehouse is in the background.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;devonport-guildhall-column-and-egyptian-house&#34;&gt;Devonport Guildhall, Column and Egyptian House&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devonport Guildhall is a legacy to the fact that the ‘City of Plymouth’ is a relatively recent creation. The three towns of Plymouth, Devonport and Stonehouse were merged in 1914 to become the city of Plymouth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Correction. Wendy Andrews on Facebook has informed me that the three towns united in 1914 but didn’t become a city until 1928&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before then the guildhall had been the administrative centre of Devonport, the largest and most prosperous of the towns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/devonport.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;An engraving from circa 1825 showing Devonport Guildhall, the base of Devonport Column, the Egyptian styled library and the chapel.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Guildhall, Column and Egyptian House were designed by the architect &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Foulston&#34;&gt;John Foulston&lt;/a&gt; who features heavily in Plymouth historical architecture. Originally there was also a chapel but during the extensive bombing of World War II it was destroyed. Indeed most of the surrounding area was destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/bombed_devonport.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Children play in the rubble left from the extensive bombing of Devonport during World War II.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A combination of the move of administrative power from the area, and the destruction of World War II led to the Guildhall falling into disuse. The column was also closed to the public in the 1950’s. The Egyptian house (one of only two buildings of this style in the country) started as a school, then a library and, would eventually become a social club which it still is today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The surrounding area, Ker street, has been through two regenerations since the war. The first was a post-war high density set of flats which dwarfed the historic buildings. The poorly planned blocks led to social problems arising and the area of Devonport became a less desirable place to live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/ker_st_flats.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The post war flats built in Ker Street dwarf the Guildhall in 2005. Photo Courtesy Devonport Online.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2007 work was started in regenerating Ker Street aiming to reduce the density of the street and try to address the social issues of the area. Happily the Guildhall and Column was given a restoration grant and have been &lt;a href=&#34;https://devonportguildhall.org/history/&#34;&gt;painstakingly restored by the Real Ideas Organisation&lt;/a&gt;. The column is now a visitor attraction and the view is worth the climb up the 137 granite steps. The Guildhall is used for weddings, craft fairs and other events, it is also home to the excellent Column House bakery. The future is less certain for the Egyptian House having recently been sold by the owners of the social club after 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Correction. Mandie Leaves, the owner of the social club has informed me that it is still up and running and anyone is welcome to pop in. I for one will visit for a look inside.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/devonport_guildhall.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Devonport Guildhall, Column and Egyptian House today, a very similar view to 1825.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mutton-cove-and-mount-wise-pools&#34;&gt;Mutton Cove and Mount Wise Pools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short distance from the Guildhall is Mutton Cove, a charming harbour with views across the Tamar to Cornwall. I’m struggling to find any information about the history of the cove, so please comment if you have any leads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to the west is Slipway Number 1 and the ‘King Billy’ figurehead. Slipway No 1 is the oldest covered slip in any Royal Navy dockyard. Built in around 1763, the roof wasn’t added until 1814.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/number-one-slip.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The view from Mutton Cove, with Covered Slip No 1 and ‘King Billy’ figurehead on the right.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In front of the slip is the ‘King Billy’ figurehead, originally it was the figurehead on the 120 gun ship H.M.S. King William. When the ship was redesigned for steam power in 1859 the figurehead was replaced with a smaller one and the original was displayed in front of the slip. In the 1990’s the original figurehead was found to have significant rot and a fibreglass replica was made and now stands in its place. The original figurehead is now at home in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://devonportnhc.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Devonport Naval Heritage centre&lt;/a&gt;, and is being restored before being moved to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theboxplymouth.com/&#34;&gt;‘the Box’&lt;/a&gt;, Plymouth’s new museum, when it opens in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along from Mutton Cove is Richmond Walk and the Mount Wise swimming pools. Richmond Walk was built in the 1790’s and 1800’s to provide local people with access to the shore as the Naval command at Mount Wise continued to expand. The swimming pools were built in 1924 and refurbished in 2000. They continue to be used today and are extremely popular in the summer months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/mount-wise-pools.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;A typical queue for Mount Wise pools on a sunny summer day.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just along from Mount Wise Pools is Blagdon’s boatyard. In 1831 this was the the site of Victoria Cottages. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Darwin&#34;&gt;Charles Darwin&lt;/a&gt; lodged here before embarking on H.M.S. Beagle to the Galapagos Islands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stonehouse-creek-and-devonport-high-school-for-boys&#34;&gt;Stonehouse Creek and Devonport High School for Boys&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richmond Walk ends at the excellent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jollyjacks.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Jolly Jacks restaurant&lt;/a&gt;, from there it is a short distance to Stonehouse Bridge. The bridge was designed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Smeaton&#34;&gt;John Smeaton&lt;/a&gt;, (of Smeaton’s lighthouse fame) and opened in 1773 to join Devonport with the neighbouring town of Stonehouse. Stonehouse creek, which the bridge crosses, was filled in as far as Millbridge in 1972 to form the recreational grounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/stonehouse-creek.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The recreation grounds behind Stonehouse Bridge, a rare piece of flat land in Plymouth!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the north side of the old creek is Devonport High School for boys. This imposing building was originally the Stoke Military Hospital and was built in 1797 for the British Army by Napoleonic prisoners of war. The design was based on the Naval hospital to the south of the creek, now the Millfields private estate. The Naval hospital was state of the art for its time and will be the subject of future articles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Stoke Military Hospital closed in 1945 after 148 years of use, initially the buildings then became two schools, Tamar High School and Devonport High School for Boys. Tamar High was closed and absorbed into DHSB in 1989.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/dhsb.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Devonport High School for Boys, originally the Stoke Military Hospital&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;millbridge&#34;&gt;Millbridge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the building of Stonehouse Bridge, Mill Bridge was the route across Stonehouse Creek to Stonehouse and Plymouth. Nowadays its not even obvious it was a bridge at all but originally both Stonehouse Creek and Victoria Park to the North East were open bodies of water (Victoria Park was known as the rather foreboding Deadlake). In 1813 the artist Turner sketched the view North towards Stoke Damerel showing the mill and bridge in the foreground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/turner_millbridge.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Turner’s Sketch of Millbridge and Stoke Damerel in 1813. Image courtesy of the Tate.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first bridge was built in 1525 and was more of a dam to use the tidal power of the Deadlake to drive the mill. At its height the mill had three wheels driving 5 pairs of millstones however operation ended in the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Millbridge head North up Molesworth Road past Georgian and Victorian mansions to return to Stoke Village.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Our Digital Team Works</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/how-our-digital-team-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/how-our-digital-team-works/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m the Delivery Team Lead for a small multi-disciplinary team in government. We are developing the service in an agile way following the &lt;a href=&#34;https://hmlandregistry.blog.gov.uk/2017/6/27/working-with-gds-to-develop-our-find-property-information-service/&#34;&gt;digital service standards developed by our colleagues at the Government Digital Service (GDS)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We recently added the ability to keep a copy of the title summary (basic information about a property). It’s a great example of what this way of working looks like in practice.
Because we can continually develop the service, we aim to deliver the features that deliver most value quickly, rather than waiting for the whole service to be finished. This allows us to validate that the things we are building are delivering the value we expect and make better decisions about whether to improve a feature further, or move onto something new, based on feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently we added the option to download a summary. User research and Live feedback was telling us that this was a feature user’s expected from the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/what_users_were_saying.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;A direct quote from a user: &#39;My document didnt print! I dont know why I regularly use my printer. You should have a save button to save the document in such cases.&#39;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;minimum-viable-feature&#34;&gt;Minimum Viable Feature.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research told us that users wanted to keep the summary, the question was how could we deliver that functionality as quickly and simply as possible to learn more. This is the concept of Minimal Viable Product (MVP) taken down a level to each feature. Deliver a simple feature quickly to learn more about how to expand and develop it further based on feedback. When developing software it can be really easy to slip into ‘edge cases’ or ‘scope creep’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes a lot of discipline to maintain focus on just the small valuable parts.
When considering ‘keeping the summary’ we discussed logging back in; seeing previous purchases; emailing the summary to users; but ultimately we went with the simplest option, generate a pdf based on the content of the summary screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/mvp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;MVP — deliver small amounts of value early, you’ll learn more about what users actually want. Credit: Henrik Kniberg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;building-services-for-all&#34;&gt;Building services for all&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This decision wasn’t without its challenges. PDF’s are not a popular choice in government due to their closed source, in-accessible nature. As civil servants, we need to ensure our services are usable by all members of the public so we take accessibility seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discussed what we were planning to do with the Open Standards Lead for government to ensure we were meeting acceptable standards. We learnt that our pdf needed to be standalone, (i.e. didn’t depend on any 3rd party servers to generate the content) and it had to meet accessibility standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When testing the pdf with a screen-reader we found our recent rebranding to HM Land Registry had some unexpected results. Screen-readers read HM as hmmm. Whilst amusing it’s a good example of the effort we put into ensuring our service is clear and concise for all users. We corrected the error and have informed our other content and development colleagues to check any references are appropriately abbreviated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;t-shaping&#34;&gt;T-Shaping&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the core tenets of agile working is the ‘pizza team’ i.e. if you can’t feed the team with two pizza’s it&amp;rsquo;s too big. The reason for this is all about communication and our &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_load&#34;&gt;cognitive capacity&lt;/a&gt;. Lines of communication between team members increases exponentially, and the more lines of communication there are, the more noise and lost messages impact the team’s ability to deliver. This has been well understood in psychology for 60 years, yet many organisations assume large complex software projects require large teams to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But small teams still need to do all the roles required to deliver a successful service, that means cross-skilling, also known as T shaping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our team has been working hard to develop this. All of our developers test each other’s work, and for the example of download, our tester Heather took the lead in the development of the feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to deliver it, she developed new skills to build a Java based pdf generator. Delivery is a team sport and the whole team contributed to its success but it was a great example of the benefits of T-shaping and instilling the right mindset. Developers who think like testers deploy fewer defects and testers who think like developers can help identify where problems are in the code speeding up defect resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;starting-continuous-delivery&#34;&gt;Starting Continuous Delivery.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agile delivery is all about making feedback cycles between the user and the development team as small as possible. In the past, we would release every 6 weeks leading to the vicious cycle below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/releases.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The big batch release conundrum. Releases go wrong, so we won’t do it often, but this results in more change being bundled into the release, increasing the likelihood of it going wrong, and the effort to test.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are now able to deploy to production at least once a sprint, and we don’t say our work is done until it is in production delivering value. When we delivered download, we deployed it at 9 o’clock in the morning with no downtime, within a minute of it being deployed we were able to see users using the feature. The sense of satisfaction to see the work you have delivered bringing value to people immediately was immeasurable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;continuous-improvement&#34;&gt;Continuous Improvement.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, that gives you a little bit of an insight into how we are starting to build, deliver, and maintain services. We have come a long way on our journey delivering in an agile way, but this isn’t the end. We are always looking at how we can continuously improve our service. Initial feedback for pdf download is positive, and therefore we have moved onto delivering the next important feature in the service, moving sign-in further back in the user journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t stand still after a feature is delivered we regularly do a ‘show and tell’ to describe how the service is performing to our product owner and we do ‘retrospective’s’ to identify where we can improve as a team, we never stop looking for ways we can improve as a team to ensure we deliver the maximum value to you our users.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 Reasons Open Plan Offices Suck for Agile Teams</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/5-reasons-open-plan-offices-suck-for-agile-teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/5-reasons-open-plan-offices-suck-for-agile-teams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently gave a presentation at the inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;https://techexeter.uk/&#34;&gt;Tech Exeter&lt;/a&gt; conference called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/IanAmes/practical-agile-tech-exeter-v2&#34;&gt;Practical agile: Lessons learned the hard way on our journey delivering digital products.&lt;/a&gt; In that presentation I claimed open plan offices are terrible team spaces, but didn&amp;rsquo;t really elaborate on why. Since then &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/_NeilParker&#34;&gt;Neil Parker&lt;/a&gt; asked on twitter to explain why I thought open plan offices are bad team environments. So here is my totally unscientific personal listicle to explain why!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-agile-teams-are-really-noisy&#34;&gt;1. Agile teams are really noisy!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And thats ok, within the team. After all a user story is a placeholder for a conversation, and lots of conversations take place to describe a design, solve a problem or get feedback on the latest user research. After all:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most efficient and effective method of conveying information to and within a development team is face-to-face conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But put lots of agile teams together in an open plan office and the noise levels can become unbearable, each team has a need to communicate, but noise volumes grow exponentially the more conversations are happening:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team A are having a conversation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team B start a conversation and talk a bit louder to be heard over Team A.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team A then increase their volume so they can be heard over Team B.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And so on ad-infinitum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are trying to concentrate on a given problem or focus on coding this can quickly become unbearable. This is why you see so many developers in open plan offices wear headphones which ironically stifles conversations from taking place in teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/headphones.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Lots of developers in an open plan office wearing headphones: Picture from http://www.mattblodgett.com/2015/06/just-wear-headphones.html&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-agile-teams-like-to-do-show-and-tells-in-their-team-space&#34;&gt;2. Agile teams like to do show and tells in their team space.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where better to demo the work you have done in the last sprint than in the team space, there is a wealth of useful information in agile team areas and stakeholders get a much richer experience being able to see the sorts of things the team are working on up on the walls. The team are in a space they are comfortable in, and have materials easily to hand to answer questions or elaborate more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in an open plan office your show and tell can easily get disrupted by people walking past the team space having a conversation, or the team across from them discussing their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of show and tell is of course disruptive to others in shared spaces too. Some teams choose to book a meeting room but I feel that the richness of the ceremony is lost as a result. I believe stakeholders subconsciously absorb the information around them in team spaces and gain a greater understanding of the product being developed when surrounded by team walls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-wall-space-is-the-prime-measure-of-currency-in-agile-teams&#34;&gt;3. Wall space is the prime measure of currency in agile teams.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agile teams love wall space, for drawing ideas, demonstrating research, or really important team metrics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/no_cake.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Important metric showing how many days since cake was last available in the team.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In open plan offices wall space is like hens teeth, instead we end up using puny whiteboards that are never quite big enough or look untidy and cluttered dotted in between desks or jutting out into floor space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-agile-teams-like-to-feel-safe&#34;&gt;4. Agile teams like to feel safe.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are communicating about everything verbally it can feel quite exposed discussing problems or issues in an open plan office. Team’s need to feel safe in their space to be able to raise concerns without fear of others judging what is going wrong in their project. Open plan offices don’t allow a team to feel like they can raise a concern without being overheard by others, reducing the effectiveness of identifying problems before they become issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/spotify_space.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Spotify team space, a good balance of team space and openness.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-agile-teams-have-fun&#34;&gt;5. Agile teams have fun.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s part of being a team, building a camaraderie, a clique. If you are in an open plan office, and you&amp;rsquo;re talking, and occasionally laughing and having fun. If you have a pointy haired boss this can be perceived as not being productive, not focusing on the work, shirking on the job. If other teams dont get to work they way you do, this can lead to resentment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/dilbert_open_plan.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Pointy haired bosses evil open plan office&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you dont have an evil pointy haired boss, team members can feel more exposed and more nervous about being themselves at work for fear of what their peers may think. If people aren&amp;rsquo;t comfortable in their work environment, their happiness and productivity drops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway I hope that explains why I think open plan offices are terrible collaboration and working spaces, let me know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are Sprints Sustainable?</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/are-sprints-sustainable/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/are-sprints-sustainable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m the scrum master for a small team developing a new service for a government agency. The team has been working in an agile way for 21 months. I have been with them for 16 of those months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few months I have been feeling more and more anxious about the sustainability of sprints as we enter a new phase for our service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use Scrum as our methodology for delivering software. Scrum at its simplest level defines a way of working to deliver small incremental changes at frequent intervals.
These intervals are called sprints, and the team makes a commitment to deliver a certain amount of work based on how much they have delivered in the past. This commitment is then tracked during the sprint and progress good or bad is reported at the end of the sprint to stakeholders in a ‘show and tell’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrum can work, I have seen it work for other teams in our organisation but my team has struggled to get to a point where we can consistently make a commitment that we know we can meet.
As a result, show and tells become extremely demoralising, and our velocity on a sprint by sprint basis looks terrible. Worse still the focus on delivering stories on time has meant we have cut corners in places and our quality has dropped away from where we would like it to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally we are entering the ‘beta’ phase of our project. We will be responsible for live support as well as delivering features. Live support by its nature is difficult to plan, you need to be able to respond to unanticipated customer requests, or degradations in your service quickly. Scrum says that if a commitment needs to be changed during a sprint, you should kill the sprint and re-plan.
Stopping and restarting sprints regularly does not feel practical or particularly sustainable. Similarly setting aside a portion of the sprint ‘just in case’ is wasteful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-how-did-we-get-here&#34;&gt;So how did we get here?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last year we have been in the difficult (although not uncommon) predicament of having a fixed scope and a fixed timescale. As any project manager will tell you if you fix scope and time, quality will drop:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/iron-triangle.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The time, cost, scope, constraint. Changing any of these can affect quality&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This certainly reflects our experience. Our quality has suffered as we struggle to meet delivering a large re-usable payment and account creation function in time for assessment and KPI deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But could we have done something different?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrum and especially point estimation encourages you to commit to work you know you can deliver (no bad thing) but when you are delivering new products using new technologies and new languages, estimation has a tendency to obey Hofstadter’s law:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It always takes longer than you expect, even when you take into account Hofstadter’s Law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outcome therefore tends to be that sprint commitments reduce in size, and therefore deadlines are put at risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team then feels responsible to try to deliver more to meet the deadline, despite the evidence and over commit. Morale then drops when that over commitment isn’t met.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://agilemanifesto.org/&#34;&gt;agile manifesto&lt;/a&gt; itself states that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agile processes promote sustainable development. The sponsors, developers, and users should be able to maintain a constant pace indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrum in the scenario we find ourselves in feels a long way from sustainable. In fact Ron Jeffries, one of the signatories of the agile manifesto has found this to be the case elsewhere and has coined the term &lt;a href=&#34;https://ronjeffries.com/articles/016-09ff/defense/&#34;&gt;Dark-Scrum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-if-there-could-be-a-different-way-of-approaching-this&#34;&gt;What if there could be a different way of approaching this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on the time/cost/scope triangle it becomes apparent Scrum attempts to reduce scope to what is achievable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However the only true constraint is time. You always have the option to change scope, cost or quality you cannot add time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes sense therefore to focus commitment on improving the time it takes to move a thing from Backlog to Done as quickly as possible rather than fixing scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;enter-kanban&#34;&gt;Enter Kanban.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kanban is often used within scrum, you regularly see backlog/doing/done boards in scrum teams. However you don’t always see all kanban principles being applied to these boards. These are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;limit-work-in-progress-wip-to-protect-constraints&#34;&gt;Limit Work in Progress (WIP) to protect constraints.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number one rule of kanban is that in order to get things from backlog to done, you need to prevent blockages in the workflow. The best way to prevent blockages is to identify the constraints in your flow and limit the amount of work in progress to however much the slowest part can handle. By doing this it is much more visible to the team where constraints are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If part of your workflow is blocked, and no other stories can therefore progress, then its extremely apparent that the issue needs resolving. Problems are identified much more quickly by this fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience dev teams are much more enthusiastic looking for ways to improve speed of delivery than they are improving their estimation techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pull-not-push&#34;&gt;Pull not push.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to protect a constraint you want to manage the flow. If you are pushing work, you very quickly build up a pile of work in front of the constraint, making merging and testing more difficult. By pulling branches into the environments; which have WIP limits; you prevent stockpiling of features and your workflow ‘jamming up’. This will be familiar to anyone using git.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;measure-cycle-time&#34;&gt;Measure cycle time.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cycle time is the time it takes for a ‘backlog item’ to get from backlog to done; and by done I mean production! I have seen many definitions of done that define ‘done’ as being signed off by a Product Owner in a test environment. For me this goes against agile principle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working software is the primary measure of progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surely the final acceptance of ‘working’ is that users are using it and are happy rather than tests have passed successfully?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly measuring cycle time and trying to speed it up comes up with tangible realistic improvements that can be implemented rather than scope reduction and managing expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;make-process-policies-explicit&#34;&gt;Make process policies explicit.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the quality gate that scrum doesn’t define as well in my opinion. Scrum has a definition of done, but kanban says to define an acceptable level for each part of the workflow not just done. This allows you to cook in the right level and type of testing to the appropriate part of the workflow and it means that stories can’t drift all the way to done without having been through some quality gates. The risk of only defining a definition of done is that the temptation can then be to ship it anyway regardless of the DoD criteria not being met, making the definition pointless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-about-forecasting-how-long-the-backlog-will-take-to-deliver&#34;&gt;What about forecasting how long the backlog will take to deliver?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something I have struggled with as a concept in scrum, most teams estimate in points, but then we are expected to forecast delivery in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have often seen this turn into ‘1 point = 1 day’ conversations as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most product backlogs fall into a standard distribution bell curve. There will be some complex large stories to deliver, there will be some tiny small stories, but most stuff will fall within 1 standard deviation of the average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/bell-curve.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;a statistical bell curve&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being the case, if we know our average speed to deliver a story, and we know how many items are on the backlog we can easily project how long a project will take to complete without the need for points based estimation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally if we want to produce ranges we can use the standard deviations to project good and bad cases early on in the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-about-quality&#34;&gt;What about quality?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how does kanban improve quality? Well we set quality constraints on the flow too. In order to proceed to the next step you must have proven x, y, z. This obviously affects cycle time but then the focus for the devs becomes how do we prove our quality targets in the most efficient way possible? Again we wont be tempted to skip quality to meet a sprint commitment because the commitment is on our delivery speed which has a much clearer inverse relationship to quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-about-standups-and-show-and-tells&#34;&gt;What about standups and show and tells?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We still standup every day and talk about what we did yesterday, what we are doing today, what is getting in the way. The key difference is that WIP limits make the ‘what is getting in the way’ question much clearer, its easier for everyone to identify and see blockers and take action accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-does-this-relate-to-sustainability-of-sprints&#34;&gt;How does this relate to sustainability of sprints?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sprints can and do work for some teams but if you find that it isn’t working for your team then kanban is worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous scrum planning meetings had been focused on how we could reduce our commitment and still meet our time and scope deadlines (which rarely produced any fruitful ideas and generally led to anxiety and uncertainty). The majority of the team started to hate planning so much that there was an in-joke that everything was a 5 pointer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we talked about moving to kanban the meeting was electric, the team immediately started talking about how we could improve our workflow? What would we do if we hit our constraint limit in different environments? How could we improve the automation of our tests and deploys? But most importantly how could we tidy up our code as we go to ensure we pass our quality gates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its early days on our kanban journey and of course when you start something new there is initial enthusiasm however I am confident that kanban is a much better focus on the correct constraint (time) and offers a level of flexibility that sprints and points based estimation did not.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>User Research Is the Most Frustrating Thing Ever</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/user-research-is-the-most-frustrating-thing-ever/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/user-research-is-the-most-frustrating-thing-ever/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m the scrum master for a small team developing a new service for a government agency. The team has been working in an agile way for 20 months. I have been with them for 15 of those months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our team is made up of user researchers, a designer, a BA, developers and testers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dealing with users isn’t new to me, before joining my current team I worked in IT operations and service management, dealing with angry and frustrated users was a day to day part of the role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However I have found user research to be one of the most frustrating parts of my current role.
When a new feature is being misused, panned or worst of all ignored I can see the frustration on the devs and testers faces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have put effort and care into nurturing this feature into existence and making sure it passes all tests and doesn’t make anything blow up. You can see them willing and hoping or worse praying that a user behaves in the way we expected them to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users never do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;How it feels to watch a user test your product for the first time. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/WqYqYoxmfq&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/WqYqYoxmfq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Farbod Saraf (@farbodsaraf) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/farbodsaraf/status/762858067218149376?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 9, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-you-should-do-it-anyway&#34;&gt;…but you should do it anyway.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If being a product owner is about delivering the best product you can, being a scrum master is about developing the best team you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bad user research session can be terrible for morale and badly handled can lead to friction in the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you should still do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;User research takes a bit of getting used to, especially if you come from a requirements driven waterfall background but it has saved our service many times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I became aware of it’s power was when the team were building a payment platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were using a shared platform with other services and were concerned about how the change of style would affect peoples perception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started worrying about how we would reconcile branding our service versus having to regression test all our current services if we did change the style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We gritted our teeth and tested the service with the current payment platform with no style changes. We expected to get destroyed we thought they style jump looked crap, we worried that users would not trust the service, we thought it looked terrible and jarring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users didn’t bat an eyelid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most responded with comments such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Oh this uses worldpay I know that.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We totally misjudged reactions and as a result we saved a ton of work restyling and regression testing our payment platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;user-research-is-a-team-sport&#34;&gt;User Research is a team sport.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So user research makes you want run into the room screaming JUST CLICK THE BUTTON RIGHT THERE!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/picard-click-the-button.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Jean Luc Picard saying just click the damn button&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But expose the team to it anyway, it teaches humility, it teaches us to question why we are building the things we are building, and it teaches us to think ‘what would I do in a user shoes.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do you do effective research without the team breaking down in tears every lab session:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stay respectful, User researchers are just the messengers, devs are just doing the best they can with what they know at the time. Stay respectful when things go wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take the dev team to labs as often as possible or if not get a live feed going.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get video feedback to the team as quickly as possible. UR feedback is important but there is nothing better for investigating strange bugs or behaviours than seeing it happen (make sure a clock is visible in the video to compare events to log files).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the time to feedback research findings and modify the backlog as a result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If possible test features in live, it is better to deploy a feature that can be improved than not to deploy and test in a less realistic environment. You can also reinforce UR findings with wider analytics evidence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are a product owner take your stakeholders to user research, let them see the consequences of decisions, how well or badly a user responds to what can feel like a good idea in a boardroom or stakeholder workshop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep testing the full service, you may want to focus on a particular feature but you always get feedback about existing features and how they all work together, does the whole flow still make sense?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The evolving visualisation of workflow in our team.</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/the-evolving-visualisation-of-workflow-in-our-team/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/the-evolving-visualisation-of-workflow-in-our-team/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m the scrum master for a small team developing a new service for a government agency. The team has been working in an agile way for 17 months. I have been with them for 12 of those months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main parts of my role is to help the team visualise the flow of work from idea to delivered. If we can see where work is (and how long it is there), we can see where it is getting blocked and I can go to work with my big unblocking hammer. This article describes the evolution of our workflow board over the past year, the problems we have identified with different approaches and the things we have tried to resolve them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-team&#34;&gt;The team&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are a multi-disciplinary team. Currently we have two user researchers, a designer, a tech architect, a business analyst, five developers, and two testers. Of course it isn’t as simple as that our developers have specialisms and the line between tester and developer is becoming more blurred with the use of test automation. To me this blurring of roles is a good thing, a team can handle blockages in backlogs more effectively if they have some knowledge of the whole process of delivery. We have also had a fair bit of churn in the team, but that’s an article for another day.&lt;br&gt;
Additionally the team has a product owner, we very much treat him as part of the team, and he is very good at considering what the team thinks needs to happen to develop the service, but ultimately he calls the shots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are supported by the webops team who build our underlying server infrastructure. We aren’t totally DevOps yet but we are working on it.&lt;br&gt;
Finally there’s me, my role is to facilitate and guide the team toward meeting their commitments. We use scrum and we operate on two week sprints commitments. A key part of my role is helping the team see where they are in delivering the commitment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-flow&#34;&gt;The flow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As anyone who has ever been stuck behind a tractor will know, you can only go as fast as the slowest thing. That’s why visualising the flow of work from backlog to done is so important. You want to identify where your constraints in delivery are and either:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limit the workflow to protect the constraint (you cant deliver more than the slowest part so don’t swamp it and make it slower).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the constraint.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A kanban board is a well established way to show flow ours has evolved as we have over the last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;board-1-the-tick-box-board&#34;&gt;Board 1. The tick box board.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This board was established when joined the team, personally I didn’t take to it as using ticks to represent where the story is didn’t make blockers stand out to me. It also did nothing to help the team think about limiting their work in progress. Stories further down the list were regularly being started before stories higher up were Done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/kanban1.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;tickbox board, a grid with stories on the y axis and steps to be done on the x. When each task is completed for a given story, the box is ticked&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its not my place to tell a team how to work, its my job to coach and mentor and point out why changes to work methods may be worth trying. The team agreed to try a new board after a particularly difficult sprint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;board-2-the-basic-kanban-board&#34;&gt;Board 2. The basic kanban board.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we tried a fairly basic kanban board with the intention of inspecting and adapting it as we identified our constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/kanban2.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;basic kanban board with 4 columns, backlog, wip - work in progress, review and done&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic kanban board had a few issues. It was easy to lose track of priority as cards moved from one column to the other. It also wasn’t always obvious when a card should move from one column to the next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crucially our team are co-located, the majority of the team are in one place but not everyone. We used pivotal tracker as the source of truth of what was going on with a story. The success of the physical board and its ease of use led to its own problem, the board was updated but often we were forgetting to update pivotal, leading to confusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;board-3-detailed-backlog-board&#34;&gt;Board 3. Detailed backlog board.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Horizontal lines were re-introduced to help keep better track of priority. Checklists above each column were also added to assist with decision making on whether the card was ready to be moved on in the flow. The board expanded physically too, a new mini board was added to the left where cards coming up for the next sprint were added to give a better heads up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/kanban3.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;detailed kanban board with 5 columns, backlog, wip - work in progress, code review, review and done. To the left of the main board is a seperate column showing what is coming in the following sprint.&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/kanban3a.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Board 3 included a clearer sprint goal to help the team judge whether they had met the overall aim of the sprint.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/kanban3b.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Board 3 also included checklists to help decision making and stimulate conversation before moving cards on.&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Board 3 helped with the priority issues. The re-addition of horizontal priority lines did lead to some concern that we were going back to the checklist board, however once the team saw cards continued to flow as with the simpler kanban board that was cleared up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Board 3 helped provide more clarity but the problem with pivotal falling behind remained.&lt;br&gt;
One crucial problem that all the boards had was that they focused on technical delivery and didn’t include user research and design. This sometimes led to confusion leading to differences between prototypes and production systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly our delivery through to production is not yet continuous. We were signing stories off in our preview environment and then not tracking the work to get the story to production. The work was being done but it was hidden from our estimation for future sprints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;board-4-mapping-the-whole-flow-is-one-board-enough&#34;&gt;Board 4. Mapping the whole flow, is one board enough?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to further improve the board, I decided to whiteboard the end to end process of idea to production. I realised that if we wanted to we could split the flow into different boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A board for user research and prototyping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A standard sprint delivery board.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A board to track production releases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/flowmap.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Whiteboarded flow map of all the steps from idea to production.&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The flow diagram wasn&amp;rsquo;t met with universal appeal. There were concerns that it was silo’ing the team, it looked to waterfall’y. But it did stimulate a lot of debate about how we deliver things and our relationship between UR/Prototyping, Delivery and Release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually we settled on two boards. A UR/Design board aimed to be a few weeks ahead of the Delivery/Release board in any given sprint. We wanted to solve the pivotal/physical board issue so we switched to trello which gave the closest physical approximation of the flexibility of a physical board in my humble opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/trellour.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Trello user research board.&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/trellodev.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Trello delivery board&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
We have only been using the boards for one sprint so far, generally they have been well received but it’s early days. There have been a few issues migrating and refining stories in the move from pivotal to trello (not as easy as you might think, I recommend this tool from little blue monkey) and I’m sure some of the columns may change especially in the UR board which we haven’t really defined in this way before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few negatives to this board:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have the priority losing issue we had with board 2 back again. We have worked around it by creating a card with a list of the priorities in it for reference if anyone gets uncertain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ideally we want to kill the release part of the flow, this needs to be automated as much as possible a-la Continuous Integration/Continuous Delivery. The fact that visualising the flow in this way helped us to identify and start to address this issue is a positive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have a nagging feeling about the loss of the tangibility of a physical card, I cant put my figure on what it is but there is something tactile about owning something physical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would be interested in your views and experiences of visualising workflow, what has worked well what hasn&amp;rsquo;t. Thanks for reading.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
