<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ames World</title>
    <link>https://ames.world/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ames World</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>MIT</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://ames.world/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/posts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/posts/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Ian Ames</title>
      <link>https://ames.world/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 21:05:37 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ames.world/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ames.world/images/ian_ames.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Headshot of Ian Ames&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;profile&#34;&gt;Profile&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am professional, enthusiastic and highly motivated with 19 years experience in IT and Digital service development and operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have delivered projects to a range of Government organisations including the Cabinet Office, NATO, Dept for
Culture Media and Sport (DCMS) and TechUK. At Land Registry I delivered their first user-centred Digital services meeting the GDS Service Standard, as well as internal projects for 4000 distributed staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have experience of a number of agile ways of working such as Scrum, Kanban, Lean Startup and DevOps. I am a certified Scrum Master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I coach and lead multi-disciplinary teams of designers, developers, user-researchers and
business analysts. I encourage new ideas and new thinking to learn quickly and continuously to improve delivery and ensure our projects meet user needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a mainstay of Plymouth&amp;rsquo;s digital community. I have organised and spoken at Agile Southwest
meetups, and have presented at the FutureSync. TechExeter, and Agile on the Beach conferences. I have also helped facilitate the excellent Agile in the Ether meetups and conference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
