<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>history on Ian Ames, Freelance Delivery Manager</title>
    <link>http://ames.world/tags/history/</link>
    <description>Recent content in history on Ian Ames, Freelance Delivery Manager</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://ames.world/tags/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Plymouth, Route 2 - Millbay Mini</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/hidden-plymouth-route2-millbay-mini/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/hidden-plymouth-route2-millbay-mini/</guid>
      <description>I’m slightly overwhelmed by how well Route 1 has been received I have had some lovely feedback and suggestions for future routes. One such suggestion is to do something shorter that children can take part in, so where better than around Millbay. I can test it with my own kids as they go to Plymouth School of Creative Arts which is the starting point for this route.
 There are loads of quirky little features in and around Millbay, its relatively flat and the route is only 2km.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Plymouth, Route 1 - Stoke to Mutton Cove</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/hidden-plymouth-route1-stoke-to-mutton-cove/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/hidden-plymouth-route1-stoke-to-mutton-cove/</guid>
      <description>This route starts at Stoke Village Car Park, which is free to park. It then climbs to what was once the highest point in Plymouth, before descending to sea level and back again. I have mapped the route on Strava so you can download it to a GPS, or print out the map.
I have also run the route so you can see a fly through below:
Relive &#39;New phone&#39;  Points of interest Blockhouse Park Before the city expanded toward Roborough this was the highest point in Plymouth and the 360˚ view from the Redoubt is one of the best in the city.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
