<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Workspace on Ian Ames - I help multidisciplinary teams deliver services in a user centred way.</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/workspace/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Workspace on Ian Ames - I help multidisciplinary teams deliver services in a user centred way.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/workspace/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Responding to Change</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/thoughts-on-responding-to-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/thoughts-on-responding-to-change/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I love the &lt;a href=&#34;https://agilemanifesto.org/&#34;&gt;agile manifesto&lt;/a&gt;, one of the things that most drew me to it was &amp;ldquo;Responding to change over following a plan&amp;rdquo;. I&amp;rsquo;ve worked on enough projects to see the benefit in changing direction when it&amp;rsquo;s clear that your plan isn&amp;rsquo;t going to help you hit your goal, and the sheer grinding death-march experience for teams when that doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However the manifesto doesn&amp;rsquo;t say much about different types of change and how best to respond to them. I have 3 mental models of change that I&amp;rsquo;ve seen in teams. I thought I would share as this is fairly early thinking (for me). I&amp;rsquo;m interested if others have seen these patterns, and what other models I&amp;rsquo;ve missed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Reasons Open Plan Offices Suck for Agile Teams</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/5-reasons-open-plan-offices-suck-for-agile-teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/5-reasons-open-plan-offices-suck-for-agile-teams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently gave a presentation at the inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;https://techexeter.uk/&#34;&gt;Tech Exeter&lt;/a&gt; conference called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/IanAmes/practical-agile-tech-exeter-v2&#34;&gt;Practical agile: Lessons learned the hard way on our journey delivering digital products.&lt;/a&gt; In that presentation I claimed open plan offices are terrible team spaces, but didn&amp;rsquo;t really elaborate on why. Since then &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/_NeilParker&#34;&gt;Neil Parker&lt;/a&gt; asked on twitter to explain why I thought open plan offices are bad team environments. So here is my totally unscientific personal listicle to explain why!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
