<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Government Digital on Ian Ames - I help multidisciplinary teams deliver services in a user centred way.</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/government-digital/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Government Digital on Ian Ames - I help multidisciplinary teams deliver services in a user centred way.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/government-digital/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on UKGovCamp 2024.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/reflections-on-ukgovcamp-2026/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/reflections-on-ukgovcamp-2026/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alright Babs, I&amp;rsquo;m on the train back from UK Govcamp. This year hosted in Birmingham for the first time, bostin! As usual its been an energising event in the dark depths of January. Birmingham city council offices we&amp;rsquo;re &lt;em&gt;beautiful&lt;/em&gt; the sort of place that inflates you with civic pride that just don&amp;rsquo;t get built anymore. I was mildly amazed at how well maintained the building was, given Brum&amp;rsquo;s well publicised financial challenges, its a credit to them they&amp;rsquo;ve managed to maintain the space, and haven&amp;rsquo;t sold it for a £1 as so often happens in crisis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on UKGovCamp 2024.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/reflections-on-ukgovcamp-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/reflections-on-ukgovcamp-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite a pretty awful journey home from UKGovCamp I&amp;rsquo;m still buzzing from it and thinking about it. I&amp;rsquo;m also horribly out of my blogging flow so you&amp;rsquo;ll have to put up with yet another ‘reflections on UKGovCamp’ post I&amp;rsquo;m afraid.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;before-i-went&#34;&gt;Before I went.&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about my reflections (meta) and understanding the headspace I was in before I went is important to give context.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To summarise it in one word: &lt;em&gt;jaded.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
