<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Ian Ames, Freelance Delivery Manager</title>
    <link>http://ames.world/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Ian Ames, Freelance Delivery Manager</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Apr 2021 16:19:55 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://ames.world/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>User Manual of Me</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/user-manual-of-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/user-manual-of-me/</guid>
      <description>User Manual of Ian Ames I&amp;rsquo;ve used Cassie Robinson&amp;rsquo;s User Manual of me template a number of times when starting projects with new teams, its a great way to quickly introduce a team to how everyone likes to work and to discuss how best to work together. It also works well in remote organisations as a way to quickly learn about colleagues you may not see on a day to day basis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hase Pino tandem review</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/hase-pino-tandem-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/hase-pino-tandem-review/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve never really seen the appeal of tandems, the poor old stoker sat at the back not able to see anything other than the pilot&amp;rsquo;s back, that was until we got a Hase Pino, quite possibly the strangest looking but most well-designed tandem there is.
The Pino is a semi-recumbent tandem, the stoker sits at the front on a recumbent seat, whilst the pilot is just behind in a standard bike configuration, the beauty of this design is that you share the same view, and your heads are close together, its easy to have a conversation even at speed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What does great collaboration in local government look like?</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/what-does-great-collaboration-in-local-government-look-like/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/what-does-great-collaboration-in-local-government-look-like/</guid>
      <description>I have a soft spot for local government, it&amp;rsquo;s where most people&amp;rsquo;s interactions with government happen, and yet it is also one of the most underfunded parts. Arguably constraint is the mother of invention and local government doesn&amp;rsquo;t get enough credit for the work they do to to deliver services for citizens effectively and cheaply. So I asked twitter to share with me some examples of great collaboration in local gov, here&amp;rsquo;s some great examples that were shared:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shedlife</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/shedlife/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/shedlife/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s been just over a year since building my office shed so I&amp;rsquo;m finally getting round to writing this post about #shedlife.
Last May I joined Surevine, a remote software company. It was my first remote role, we didn&amp;rsquo;t have any spare space in the house so I needed somewhere to be able to work. Because of the nature of our clients it needed to be somewhere where I could have conversations without being overheard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Would a Great Onboarding Experience Look Like?</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/what-would-a-great-onboarding-experience-look-like/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/what-would-a-great-onboarding-experience-look-like/</guid>
      <description>When I joined Surevine my onboarding experience was fantastic, but I wanted to see if there was anything more we could do to make it even better, so back in June I asked twitter what would a great onboarding experience look like?
As always the responses were great. This post summarises what I learned:
Onboarding starts way before a person joins a company If someone wants to work with you, they will be thinking about it way before onboarding starts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on Map Camp</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/reflections-on-map-camp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/reflections-on-map-camp/</guid>
      <description>This year I was finally able to attend MapCamp 2019 with ~600 other people at Sadlers Wells Theatre, London. MapCamp is a conference introducing and describing the technique of Wardley Mapping, a tool for mapping strategy.
I first came across Wardley Maps a couple of years ago through the medium book. I found it compelling, Simon Wardley has a lovely humble style of writing. He described how he went from ‘bumbling CEO’ to ‘having a vague idea of what I was doing’.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Things I Learned From Remote Working</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/10-things-i-learned-from-remote-working/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/10-things-i-learned-from-remote-working/</guid>
      <description>This post was originally published on the surevine blog.
3 months ago, I took the next step in my career and joined Surevine as a Team Lead. There were many things that first attracted me to the company, but one major benefit was that it’s totally remote, and so learning how to work collaboratively whilst remote was a challenge that really interested me.
Sureviner’s are spread all over the country, and my team alone covers a geographical area that stretches from Durham to Plymouth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Story Crowdsourcing Game</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/story-crowdsourcing-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/story-crowdsourcing-game/</guid>
      <description>Emily Webber recently asked if I could run an 8-minute workshop to energise people at the beginning of her regular Agile in the Ether remote meetup. (It is a very friendly meetup and well worth checking out).
This is the detail of the game I facilitated:
Objective Tell a story that develops iteratively and everyone in the group contributes to.
Instruction Each person adds a sentence to a story, but has to repeat the preceding sentences first, then nominates the next person to go.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IPv4 Addressing</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/ipv4-addressing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/ipv4-addressing/</guid>
      <description>I briefly touched on IPv4 addresses in the TCP/IP suite. In summary IPv4 addresses are: Dot-separated.
 32 bits long and represented in decimal. There are just over 4 billion available addresses. Therefore it is necessary to use subnetting to separate networks and duplicate IP addresses from one another.  IPv4 structure and what it represents So we know IP addresses are 32 bits long and that they are separated into 4 decimal numbers by dot separation (this is known as dotted decimal), therefore each number must represent 8bits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TCP/IP Protocol Suite</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/tcp-ip-protocol-suite/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/tcp-ip-protocol-suite/</guid>
      <description>TCP/IP is a set of protocols that form the backbone of the internet. As I described in the OSI model post, TCP (Transmission Control Protocol) provides reliable, ordered, and error-checked delivery of a stream of bytes between applications running on hosts. IP (Internet Protocol) is the protocol for shifting packets around between hosts in the network layer. The TCP/IP suite, however, contains a whole bunch of protocols beyond these two. (Fun fact: If to devices are communicating in a network with TCP/IP they are called network hosts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The OSI Model</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/the-osi-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/the-osi-model/</guid>
      <description>The OSI model is designed to ensure compatibility of network devices (and their operating systems) regardless of manufacturer. OSI stands for Open Systems Interconnection and is defined by the International Standard Organisation (ISO).
The model has seven layers:
 Application layer Presentation layer System layer Transport layer Network layer Data layer Physical layer  Which can be remembered by either of two mnemonics:
 All People Seem To Need Data Processing</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Communication Fundamentals</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/data-communication-fundamentals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/data-communication-fundamentals/</guid>
      <description>Concerns the basics of networking, starting with some common terminology of data transmission. This can be summarised as:
 A sender has some data they want to send to a receiver. That data needs to be converted into a message for sending. The message needs to be transmitted via some form of medium. The receiver needs to be able to turn that signal back into the data that has been sent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network Fundamentals</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/network-fundamentals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/network-fundamentals/</guid>
      <description>Network fundamentals explores how computer networks are designed to enable the sharing of data taking into account three key requirements:
Performance. The sharing of data and resources doesn’t degrade the computers on the network.
Reliability. The network doesn’t fall over all the time.
Security. Data is only shared with those that should have access to it.
Types Peer to Peer is where every node on the network has equal access to the network and each node shares data and resources.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Essential Steps for an Effective Project Kick Off</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/essential-steps-for-an-effective-project-kick-off/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/essential-steps-for-an-effective-project-kick-off/</guid>
      <description>Kick-off’s are a great way of bringing a new team together at the start of a new project or phase of a project. The aim is to allow the team to get to know one another and to allow all the team members to understand the goals and objectives.
I recently helped facilitate a kick-off for the alpha phase of the ‘Protect’ service (working title). Although Protect had been through a discovery phase, circumstances meant that the Alpha team was quite different to the Discovery team.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mountaineering and a Rant About Risk Management</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/mountaineering-and-a-rant-about-risk-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/mountaineering-and-a-rant-about-risk-management/</guid>
      <description>I love hill climbing and mountaineering, ever since I was dragged up Pen-Y-Fan and got mild hypothermia in the scouts at about the age of 13. One of the best things yomping up hills has taught me is the nature of risk. So I was a bit surprised when I saw this tweet from Vasco Duarte:
Friends, let&amp;#39;s collect a list of domains where Risk ELIMINATION is priority #1: Climbing; Air travel industry; what else?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving &#39;Find&#39; for the Find Property Information Service</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/improving-find-for-the-find-property-information-service/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/improving-find-for-the-find-property-information-service/</guid>
      <description>Find Property Information is a GOV.UK service being developed by HM Land Registry which aims to provide a simple summary of property information. Recently we have improved our ‘postcode search’ functionality.
Why did we do this? Our first iteration of searching was developed over a year ago, we knew the limitations of it, but it was ‘good enough’ for the early stages of the service. This allowed us to move onto developing other features.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Plymouth, Route 2 - Millbay Mini</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/hidden-plymouth-route2-millbay-mini/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/hidden-plymouth-route2-millbay-mini/</guid>
      <description>I’m slightly overwhelmed by how well Route 1 has been received I have had some lovely feedback and suggestions for future routes. One such suggestion is to do something shorter that children can take part in, so where better than around Millbay. I can test it with my own kids as they go to Plymouth School of Creative Arts which is the starting point for this route.
 There are loads of quirky little features in and around Millbay, its relatively flat and the route is only 2km.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Plymouth, Route 1 - Stoke to Mutton Cove</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/hidden-plymouth-route1-stoke-to-mutton-cove/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/hidden-plymouth-route1-stoke-to-mutton-cove/</guid>
      <description>This route starts at Stoke Village Car Park, which is free to park. It then climbs to what was once the highest point in Plymouth, before descending to sea level and back again. I have mapped the route on Strava so you can download it to a GPS, or print out the map.
I have also run the route so you can see a fly through below:
Relive &#39;New phone&#39;  Points of interest Blockhouse Park Before the city expanded toward Roborough this was the highest point in Plymouth and the 360˚ view from the Redoubt is one of the best in the city.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Our Digital Team Works</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/how-our-digital-team-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/how-our-digital-team-works/</guid>
      <description>I’m the Delivery Team Lead for a small multi-disciplinary team in government. We are developing the service in an agile way following the digital service standards developed by our colleagues at the Government Digital Service (GDS).
We recently added the ability to keep a copy of the title summary (basic information about a property). It’s a great example of what this way of working looks like in practice. Because we can continually develop the service, we aim to deliver the features that deliver most value quickly, rather than waiting for the whole service to be finished.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 Reasons Open Plan Offices Suck for Agile Teams</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/5-reasons-open-plan-offices-suck-for-agile-teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/5-reasons-open-plan-offices-suck-for-agile-teams/</guid>
      <description>I recently gave a presentation at the inaugural Tech Exeter conference called Practical agile: Lessons learned the hard way on our journey delivering digital products. In that presentation I claimed open plan offices are terrible team spaces, but didn&amp;rsquo;t really elaborate on why. Since then Neil Parker asked on twitter to explain why I thought open plan offices are bad team environments. So here is my totally unscientific personal listicle to explain why!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are Sprints Sustainable?</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/are-sprints-sustainable/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/are-sprints-sustainable/</guid>
      <description>I’m the scrum master for a small team developing a new service for a government agency. The team has been working in an agile way for 21 months. I have been with them for 16 of those months.
Over the last few months I have been feeling more and more anxious about the sustainability of sprints as we enter a new phase for our service.
We use Scrum as our methodology for delivering software.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>User Research Is the Most Frustrating Thing Ever</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/user-research-is-the-most-frustrating-thing-ever/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/user-research-is-the-most-frustrating-thing-ever/</guid>
      <description>I’m the scrum master for a small team developing a new service for a government agency. The team has been working in an agile way for 20 months. I have been with them for 15 of those months.
Our team is made up of user researchers, a designer, a BA, developers and testers.
Dealing with users isn’t new to me, before joining my current team I worked in IT operations and service management, dealing with angry and frustrated users was a day to day part of the role.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The evolving visualisation of workflow in our team.</title>
      <link>http://ames.world/blog/the-evolving-visualisation-of-workflow-in-our-team/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ames.world/blog/the-evolving-visualisation-of-workflow-in-our-team/</guid>
      <description>I’m the scrum master for a small team developing a new service for a government agency. The team has been working in an agile way for 17 months. I have been with them for 12 of those months.
One of the main parts of my role is to help the team visualise the flow of work from idea to delivered. If we can see where work is (and how long it is there), we can see where it is getting blocked and I can go to work with my big unblocking hammer.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
