<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Network Security on Ian Ames - I help multidisciplinary teams deliver services in a user centred way.</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/network-security/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Network Security on Ian Ames - I help multidisciplinary teams deliver services in a user centred way.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/network-security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>TCP/IP Protocol Suite</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/tcp-ip-protocol-suite/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/tcp-ip-protocol-suite/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TCP/IP is a set of protocols that form the backbone of the internet. As I described in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/blog/the-osi-model&#34;&gt;OSI model post&lt;/a&gt;, TCP (Transmission Control Protocol) provides reliable, ordered, and error-checked delivery of a stream of bytes between applications running on hosts. IP (Internet Protocol) is the protocol for shifting packets around between hosts in the network layer. The TCP/IP suite, however, contains a whole bunch of protocols beyond these two. (Fun fact: If to devices are communicating in a network with TCP/IP they are called network hosts. If they are using anything else they are called network nodes.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The OSI Model</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/the-osi-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/the-osi-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The OSI model is designed to ensure compatibility of network devices (and their operating systems) regardless of manufacturer. OSI stands for Open Systems Interconnection and is defined by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iso.org/ics/35.100/x/&#34;&gt;International Standard Organisation (ISO)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The model has seven layers:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Application layer&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Presentation layer&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;System layer&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Transport layer&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Network layer&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Data layer&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Physical layer&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Which can be remembered by either of two mnemonics:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All People Seem To Need Data Processing&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;or from the bottom up:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Communication Fundamentals</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/data-communication-fundamentals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/data-communication-fundamentals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/data_components.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Diagram showing the fundamental components of a data network, described in this article.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Concerns the basics of networking, starting with some common terminology of data transmission. This can be summarised as:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A sender has some data they want to send to a receiver.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;That data needs to be converted into a message for sending.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The message needs to be transmitted via some form of medium.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The receiver needs to be able to turn that signal back into the data that has been sent.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Therefore a system is needed to agree on rules between the sender and receiver about how the data will be converted into a signal, transmitted and converted back to data, this is called a &lt;em&gt;protocol&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In order for this system to be effective it needs to ensure:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network Fundamentals</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/network-fundamentals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/network-fundamentals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/network_fundamentals.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;An image showing a number of colourful Cat5 cables with the banner ‘Network fundamentals’&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Network fundamentals explores how computer networks are designed to enable the sharing of data taking into account three key requirements:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance.&lt;/strong&gt; The sharing of data and resources doesn’t degrade the computers on the network.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reliability.&lt;/strong&gt; The network doesn’t fall over all the time.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security.&lt;/strong&gt; Data is only shared with those that should have access to it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
