<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ways of Working on Ian Ames - I help multidisciplinary teams deliver services in a user centred way.</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/ways-of-working/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ways of Working on Ian Ames - I help multidisciplinary teams deliver services in a user centred way.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/ways-of-working/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Responding to Change</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/thoughts-on-responding-to-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/thoughts-on-responding-to-change/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I love the &lt;a href=&#34;https://agilemanifesto.org/&#34;&gt;agile manifesto&lt;/a&gt;, one of the things that most drew me to it was &amp;ldquo;Responding to change over following a plan&amp;rdquo;. I&amp;rsquo;ve worked on enough projects to see the benefit in changing direction when it&amp;rsquo;s clear that your plan isn&amp;rsquo;t going to help you hit your goal, and the sheer grinding death-march experience for teams when that doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However the manifesto doesn&amp;rsquo;t say much about different types of change and how best to respond to them. I have 3 mental models of change that I&amp;rsquo;ve seen in teams. I thought I would share as this is fairly early thinking (for me). I&amp;rsquo;m interested if others have seen these patterns, and what other models I&amp;rsquo;ve missed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>So you&#39;re thinking of becoming a delivery manager</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/so-youre-thinking-of-becoming-a-delivery-manager/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/so-youre-thinking-of-becoming-a-delivery-manager/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few months back &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/neilvass/&#34;&gt;Neil Vass&lt;/a&gt; asked in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://agileintheether.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Agile in the Ether&lt;/a&gt; slack channel for advice for people looking to move into Delivery Management roles. I posted a bunch of replies, others did too. Before slack deletes all the replies I thought I would turn them into a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-is-a-delivery-manager&#34;&gt;What is a delivery manager?&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I first started working as a delivery manager in 2015, job searches for the role mainly returned delivery driver and pizza delivery type roles, over the last 9 years the role has become much more established in both the public and private sector. For me Emily Webber’s post, &lt;a href=&#34;https://emilywebber.co.uk/what-is-an-agile-delivery-manager/&#34;&gt;Explaining the role of a delivery manager&lt;/a&gt; still holds true. It’s the person in the team responsible for ways of working, team health and happiness, and delivery support (especially in large orgs).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>User Manual of Me</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/user-manual-of-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/user-manual-of-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;user-manual-of-ian-ames&#34;&gt;User Manual of Ian Ames&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve used &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@cassierobinson&#34;&gt;Cassie Robinson&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@cassierobinson/a-user-manual-for-me-d3a851fbc694&#34;&gt;User Manual of me&lt;/a&gt; template a number of times when starting projects with new teams, its a great way to quickly introduce a team to how everyone likes to work and to discuss how best to work together. It also works well in remote organisations as a way to quickly learn about colleagues you may not see on a day to day basis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Things I Learned From Remote Working</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/10-things-i-learned-from-remote-working/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/10-things-i-learned-from-remote-working/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally published on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.surevine.com/10-things-learnt-remote-working/&#34;&gt;surevine blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3 months ago, I took the next step in my career and joined Surevine as a Team Lead. There were many things that first attracted me to the company, but one major benefit was that it’s totally remote, and so learning how to work collaboratively whilst remote was a challenge that really interested me.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sureviner’s are spread all over the country, and my team alone covers a geographical area that stretches from Durham to Plymouth. Although I’m only 3 months in, you learn pretty quickly what works and doesn’t when it comes to remote work. Here’s what I have discovered:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Story Crowdsourcing Game</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/story-crowdsourcing-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/story-crowdsourcing-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Emily Webber recently asked if I could run an 8-minute workshop to energise people at the beginning of her regular &lt;a href=&#34;https://agileintheether.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Agile in the Ether remote meetup&lt;/a&gt;. (It is a very friendly meetup and well worth checking out).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/agile_ether.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Screenshot of the Agile in the Ether attendees&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is the detail of the game I facilitated:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;objective&#34;&gt;Objective&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Tell a story that develops iteratively and everyone in the group contributes to.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruction&#34;&gt;Instruction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Each person adds a sentence to a story, but has to repeat the preceding sentences first, then nominates the next person to go. (It may help for the facilitator to start).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving &#39;Find&#39; for the Find Property Information Service</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/improving-find-for-the-find-property-information-service/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/improving-find-for-the-find-property-information-service/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://search-property-information.service.gov.uk/&#34;&gt;Find Property Information&lt;/a&gt; is a GOV.UK service being developed by HM Land Registry which aims to provide a simple summary of property information. Recently we have improved our ‘postcode search’ functionality.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-did-we-do-this&#34;&gt;Why did we do this?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Our first iteration of searching was developed over a year ago, we knew the limitations of it, but it was ‘good enough’ for the early stages of the service. This allowed us to move onto developing other features. Since then the quality of search has crept up the list of user issues.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Our Digital Team Works</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/how-our-digital-team-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/how-our-digital-team-works/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m the Delivery Team Lead for a small multi-disciplinary team in government. We are developing the service in an agile way following the &lt;a href=&#34;https://hmlandregistry.blog.gov.uk/2017/6/27/working-with-gds-to-develop-our-find-property-information-service/&#34;&gt;digital service standards developed by our colleagues at the Government Digital Service (GDS)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We recently added the ability to keep a copy of the title summary (basic information about a property). It’s a great example of what this way of working looks like in practice.&#xA;Because we can continually develop the service, we aim to deliver the features that deliver most value quickly, rather than waiting for the whole service to be finished. This allows us to validate that the things we are building are delivering the value we expect and make better decisions about whether to improve a feature further, or move onto something new, based on feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Reasons Open Plan Offices Suck for Agile Teams</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/5-reasons-open-plan-offices-suck-for-agile-teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/5-reasons-open-plan-offices-suck-for-agile-teams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently gave a presentation at the inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;https://techexeter.uk/&#34;&gt;Tech Exeter&lt;/a&gt; conference called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/IanAmes/practical-agile-tech-exeter-v2&#34;&gt;Practical agile: Lessons learned the hard way on our journey delivering digital products.&lt;/a&gt; In that presentation I claimed open plan offices are terrible team spaces, but didn&amp;rsquo;t really elaborate on why. Since then &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/_NeilParker&#34;&gt;Neil Parker&lt;/a&gt; asked on twitter to explain why I thought open plan offices are bad team environments. So here is my totally unscientific personal listicle to explain why!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are Sprints Sustainable?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/are-sprints-sustainable/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/are-sprints-sustainable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m the scrum master for a small team developing a new service for a government agency. The team has been working in an agile way for 21 months. I have been with them for 16 of those months.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Over the last few months I have been feeling more and more anxious about the sustainability of sprints as we enter a new phase for our service.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We use Scrum as our methodology for delivering software. Scrum at its simplest level defines a way of working to deliver small incremental changes at frequent intervals.&#xA;These intervals are called sprints, and the team makes a commitment to deliver a certain amount of work based on how much they have delivered in the past. This commitment is then tracked during the sprint and progress good or bad is reported at the end of the sprint to stakeholders in a ‘show and tell’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The evolving visualisation of workflow in our team.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/the-evolving-visualisation-of-workflow-in-our-team/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/the-evolving-visualisation-of-workflow-in-our-team/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m the scrum master for a small team developing a new service for a government agency. The team has been working in an agile way for 17 months. I have been with them for 12 of those months.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the main parts of my role is to help the team visualise the flow of work from idea to delivered. If we can see where work is (and how long it is there), we can see where it is getting blocked and I can go to work with my big unblocking hammer. This article describes the evolution of our workflow board over the past year, the problems we have identified with different approaches and the things we have tried to resolve them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
