<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Weeknotes on Ian Ames - I help multidisciplinary teams deliver services in a user centred way.</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/weeknotes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Weeknotes on Ian Ames - I help multidisciplinary teams deliver services in a user centred way.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/weeknotes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Unordered Note 16/01/26</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/unorderednote-160126/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/unorderednote-160126/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello happy new year! I&amp;rsquo;m falling out of the habit of weeknoting again! To be honest I&amp;rsquo;m not sure unordered notes are working for me. For me weeknotes are as much about turning my swirly thoughts into coherent thinking, keeping them swirly doesn&amp;rsquo;t help me. Anyway work will be changing very soon, hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to be able to talk about it a bit more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;whats-on-my-mind-this-week&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s on my mind this week.&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ending-things&#34;&gt;Ending things&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Getting the right level of detail and context down to help others pick up the baton, knowing no amount of words will be enough to cover all that tacit knowledge. My second favourite thing from Dave Snowden (after cynefin) is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cynefin.io/wiki/Principles_for_managing_knowledge&#34;&gt;7 principles of knowledge management&lt;/a&gt;, trying to hold them close this week.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unordered Note 28/11/25</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/unorderednote-281125/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/unorderednote-281125/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m trying to get back in the habit of weeknoting, but I can&amp;rsquo;t be too specific about the work, so this is the random thoughts I&amp;rsquo;m dwelling on this week:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;progress&#34;&gt;Progress.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Palpable progress this week, it feels good! Not only that but being able to see a semblence of structure emerging.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pitching&#34;&gt;Pitching&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Selling your wares is a constant thing where I am at the moment, honing those &amp;lsquo;sales&amp;rsquo; skills of picking valuable leads, assessing whats a goer or not quickly is a real art.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unordered Note 21/11/25</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/unorderednote-141125/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/unorderednote-141125/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Continuing the effort of chucking down end of the week thoughts, as an attempt to keep up the weeknote habit, without talking about specifics of the day job. Week 2, go me!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;things-on-my-mind-at-the-end-of-this-week&#34;&gt;Things on my mind at the end of this week:&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;future-of-delivery-management&#34;&gt;Future of delivery management&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Heard this week that the BBC are getting rid of their entire delivery management function, which pissed me right off. But after a few days of feeling angry, I became more reflective:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unordered Note 14/11/25</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/unorderednote-211125/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/unorderednote-211125/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m back at work this month, I’ve found weeknoting this year difficult due to balancing clients comfort with open notes. The situation is unlikely to change in the near future. The thing I miss the most about the process is getting things that are looping around my brain down on paper and in public, this is because:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;It gets it out of my brain before the weekend!&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Writing helps me order swirly thoughts&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;People more intelligent than me usually chip in with ideas and answers I haven’t thought of!&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So with that in mind I’m going to try ‘Unordered thoughts notes’ (nowhere near as catchy!) A list of things I’m grappling with, in more abstract terms to see if that scratches the weeknotes itch. Here’s this week’s unordered thoughts…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monthnote September 24</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/monthnote-september2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/monthnote-september2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been a bit naff keeping up the weeknotes cadence in September so attempting a Month note. PD has a bibliography of common phrases, one of them is &amp;ldquo;laptop in the pond&amp;rdquo; that feeling when you get to the end of the week and just want to not look at a screen for a while. That&amp;rsquo;s partially why my cadence has dropped off,publishing to my blog is a bit of a faff. It&amp;rsquo;s a static site, all the content is in GitHub and pushed to netlify for hosting, the publishing process is a little esoteric and very dependent on me editing the file on my Mac and invoking terminal git commands to push the content. It&amp;rsquo;s the last thing I want to do at the end of a week, it also doesn&amp;rsquo;t really support a busy life well. So I&amp;rsquo;m trying something different today, I&amp;rsquo;m typing this directly in a file via the GitHub browser that means I can do it on my phone whilst Phoebe is at the gym.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknote 02/08/24</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-020824/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-020824/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So funemployment is over. I&amp;rsquo;m back doing work and it&amp;rsquo;s straight in at the deep end as the client engagement kicked off this week too. This week has been all the usual things of getting a large project moving, meeting people, establishing ways of working, chasing accounts, setting up how we’re going to track all the things we need to do.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My role is delivery lead (not engagement manager) as I stated last week, so I’m working out how to balance myself to support the 4 teams that are merging on the project, help them to be successful, and keep track of deliverables we’ve signed up to. I’m aiming to take a very ‘Governance as a service’ approach, but working with such a large organisation balancing that with existing governance structures will need to happen, at least in the short term.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknote 26/07/24</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-260724/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-260724/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;monday&#34;&gt;Monday&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My z fold 4 has been playing up for weeks. Since upgrading to the latest version of android, wifi hasn’t worked, on Monday it stopped charging and is pretty much now a brick, just when I need a phone as contract conversations heat up. I dug out my old oneplus 6t, a 6 year old phone and it worked well, and is noticeably quicker than the Samsung with all its bloatware. I’ve now ordered a oneplus open as a replacement. I should have trusted my better judgement and not got a Samsung in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknote 19/07/24</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-190724/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-190724/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;monday&#34;&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Freya had an inset day, Han and I couldn’t figure out the logic of having an inset day on the Monday of the last week of term. On Sunday night as we sat down to watch the Euro’s final with the kids it dawned on us. Well played Mr West, well played!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was looking after Freya’s friend Martha too, I had planned to drive up to Bude to meet Darwin and go surfing (well mainly pushing the girls on their boards) It was a 3 hour round trip for around 40 minutes of surfing in the rain, but it was fun nonetheless and good to catchup with Darwin. The van survived with no problems!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknote 12/07/24</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-120724/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-120724/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another week that’s felt like I haven’t done that much, but on reflection I’ve done quite a bit, I think it’s more of a case that I’m doing lots of disjointed things wily-nily rather than having a coherent purpose to anything. I dunno, probably overthinking it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;monday&#34;&gt;Monday.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Wet and horrible day, I didn&amp;rsquo;t do a great deal, polished up my contracting post, went out for lunch with Han, that was about it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknote 05/07/24</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-050724/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-050724/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A bitty week this week, one of those that feels like it&amp;rsquo;s been busy but nothing really done.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;monday&#34;&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Monday started well, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/priyanca-ux/&#34;&gt;Priyanca&lt;/a&gt; and I had a great chat with some product folks from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/scottcolfer/&#34;&gt;Scott Colfer’s&lt;/a&gt; Product whatsapp community about discoveries. This is in preparation for our talk at &lt;a href=&#34;https://govservicedesign.net/&#34;&gt;SDinGov&lt;/a&gt; in September, we wanted to practise what we preach and validate some of our own experiences. The talk was productive and has led to some interesting further conversations about how we might improve the visibility of discovery practices, warts and all, looking forward to seeing how that develops.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknote 28/06/24</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-280624/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-280624/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week has been mainly catching up with lots of folks so I thought I would structure the weeknote by who I have talked to:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;olihttpswwwlinkedincominoli-l-670a22254&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/oli-l-670a22254/&#34;&gt;Oli&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Oli and I are both based in the south west and both part of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://agileintheether.co.uk/&#34;&gt;agile in the ether community&lt;/a&gt; but we’ve never met face to face before. On Monday we righted that wrong and met for lunch at Double Locks in Exeter. Oli has just joined &lt;a href=&#34;https://public.digital/&#34;&gt;Public Digital&lt;/a&gt; after 20+ years in the civil service. We had a lot of experiences in common (I was a civil servant for 14 years) and have worked with similar people or the same/adjacent organisations we even sussed out we were at Plymouth University at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknote 21/06/24</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-210624/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-210624/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;monday&#34;&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dropped Phoebe off later into school, her condition means she tires easily so she has a reduced timetable on certain days. After that I headed to Wickes to get paint stuff to paint the dining room. Han needs a bigger space to demonstrate larger exercises for her &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCuAYbWUsnnLbBTyq-_1V8bA&#34;&gt;nurse tutoring YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;. The wall is kind of a meh beige so I&amp;rsquo;ve painted it white for now. I really hate painting, any job that takes longer to prepare for than to do won&amp;rsquo;t float my boat. I&amp;rsquo;m not very good at it too, I suspect these two facts are related!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknote 14/06/24 Bikes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-140624/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-140624/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week my brother &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/amesmark/&#34;&gt;Mark&lt;/a&gt; and I cycled around the Netherlands. Mark lives in Australia and we&amp;rsquo;ve kind of formed this little tradition of going on cycling holidays when he&amp;rsquo;s back over. This is our third one, our first was 12 years ago where we &lt;a href=&#34;https://photos.app.goo.gl/7LaRRdEFLGnCEFf69&#34;&gt;cycled over Dartmoor&lt;/a&gt;. 2 years ago we picked the &lt;a href=&#34;https://photos.app.goo.gl/Hdn2ECYyhKyFFRhp8&#34;&gt;Somerset levels&lt;/a&gt;. We both enjoyed the lack of hills last time and Mark is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.strategic-cities.com/&#34;&gt;active travel consultant&lt;/a&gt;, so of course we picked the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknote 07/06/24 Funemployment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-070624/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknote-070624/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello its been a while, so long in fact I&amp;rsquo;ve moved platforms since the last time I weeknoted. I never bothered to port my old notes over from medium, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure why but I wont bother now. I had a quick look, my last &lt;a href=&#34;https://weeknot.es/weeknotes-wb-16-08-19-3918539f3152&#34;&gt;weeknote was 2019&lt;/a&gt;, the before times, so much has changed, and perhaps not that much at all.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve found it hard weeknoting as a contractor, I&amp;rsquo;m never really sure what I can and can&amp;rsquo;t say, when I was a fulltime civil servant I was always pretty honest about how work made me feel as well as what we were doing, that feels more high stakes as a contractor, it probably isn&amp;rsquo;t, it probably just the fear of the unknown.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknotes NHS Digital Episode 5</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknotes-nhs-digital-episode5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknotes-nhs-digital-episode5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m on the train back from Leeds after kicking off Patient Encounter History with the team. My brain is a bit mushy and so this weeknote may be incoherent and full of typos, apologies!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It was lovely to meet everyone in person for the first time, build relationships, work through our understanding of the project and what we hope to acheive in the next 8 weeks. I still haven&amp;rsquo;t found a better way to start new peices of work (or anything with high levels of uncertainty) than face to face workshops to be honest, for me its the last remaining part of remote work that isn&amp;rsquo;t quite as good as face to face.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknotes NHS Digital Episode 4</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknotes-nhs-digital-episode4/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknotes-nhs-digital-episode4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week has been a good one, our discovery team is starting to form with one of our user researchers joining, and the other one due to start on Monday we are starting to get our plans together for discovery. In some ways the slight delay in starting has been useful as its given me and the PM (who&amp;rsquo;s also new to this space) the opportunity to really start to understand the context of the area we are exploring.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknotes NHS Digital Episode 3</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknotes-nhs-digital-episode3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknotes-nhs-digital-episode3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Been a while since the last weeknotes, its been pretty busy we&amp;rsquo;ve been getting going on a new Discovery which has been filling my brain up as Disco&amp;rsquo;s always do. I&amp;rsquo;m going to use this weeknotes to capture what I understand so far, quick reminder that weeknotes are for me to reflect what I know, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that this is exactly correct, there are holes in my knowledge, the NHS is a vast complex system, I probably understand about 1% of it, writing stuff down helps my understanding though.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknotes NHS Digital Episode 2</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknotes-nhs-digital-episode2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknotes-nhs-digital-episode2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Time is really flying, I found myself introducing myself and saying I was on my 3rd week last week (I was on my 4th) I&amp;rsquo;m genuinely not sure where those 4 weeks have gone, thats a good sign! Writing these weeknotes is taking longer too as I&amp;rsquo;m not in a space where I fully know what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about yet, the act of doing it is helping me understand where I don&amp;rsquo;t know stuff yet and I go and find out more to add detail, but its making publishing slow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weeknotes NHS Digital Episode 1</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknotes-nhs-digital-episode1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 12:12:52 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/weeknotes-nhs-digital-episode1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t weeknoted in public for a couple of years now for various reasons but starting a new phase of my work-life feels like a good time to get back into it. I have recently taken the plunge into contracting and have started at NHS Digital with the 111 online teams.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always done weeknotes primarily for myself to reflect on what I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt and I am learning LOADS at the moment, not just about how NHS digital works but what contracting life involves and how that differs from being a full time member of staff.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
